<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description>Random musings on books, code, and tabletop games.</description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 17:47:14 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Playing Classic Traveller in 2020</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/16/playing-classic-traveller-in-2020/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="section" id="finally-playing-classic-traveller"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finally playing Classic Traveller&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine who was in my gaming group back in the 1980s read the
article &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tor.com/2020/01/10/traveller-a-classic-science-fiction-simulator/"&gt;Traveller: A Classic Science Fiction Simulator&lt;/a&gt; at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tor.com"&gt;Tor.com&lt;/a&gt; and found it interesting.  We discussed it, and he
downloaded &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/80190/CTSTStarter-Traveller"&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/"&gt;Drivethrurpg.com&lt;/a&gt; (it is free)
and started reading it.  I had the PDF already, and I printed it out
and started reading it as well.  I also found a physical copy for sale
on the Internet, so I ordered that as well, and it was much more
convenient to use than my printout in binders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition admonition-my-gaming-history"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;My Gaming History&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience with Traveller back in the 1980s was minimal: another
friend had the little black box with the three little black books
(LBBs), and we rolled up characters (which at the time seemed way
more complicated than &lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt;, which we were used to).  Then we tried
to figure out what to do, which was not immediately obvious to us.
&lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; has the obvious core activity of going down in a dungeon and
killing monsters, but Traveller was a lot more wide-open.  My
friend hadn't bought an adventure (which I find very useful for
getting an idea of core activity of a game) and he'd bought the
&lt;cite&gt;Basic Set&lt;/cite&gt;, so there wasn't an adventure in the box.  We didn't
realize that we could use the various checklists and procedures to
improvise an adventure on the spot.  So we didn't get far, alas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought several new editions of Traveller over the years
(&lt;cite&gt;Megatraveller&lt;/cite&gt;, &lt;cite&gt;Traveller: The New Era&lt;/cite&gt;, &lt;cite&gt;Traveller 4, Traveller
5&lt;/cite&gt;) but never found the chance to play them.  But my interest in
Classic Traveller grew once I found it being talked about in
Internet forums and blogs.  I bought a copy of the original rules
and several other LBBs, and some of the farfuture.net CD-ROMs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, yesterday afternoon I went over to my friend's house with my
&lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; box and some other Classic Traveller materials for
show and tell, and then we rolled up three characters each, 2D6 for
attributes in order.  I had two survive character generation (because
we were using the hardcore “you can die in character generation” rule
that was the default in Classic Traveller), both had been in the Army,
both having miserable strengths (one of them couldn't carry his rifle
&lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; a clip of ammo; don't know how he made it through the Army),
and the weakest only had one term and the other only had two terms,
though he made Lieutenant.  My friend had one character survive
character generation, also from the Army, and he had more terms that
either of my characters, though I don't remember how many, and ended
up a Lt. Colonel if I remember correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we ran a practice combat between my friend's character and my
better character: Submachine Guns at short range (1–5 meters) in a
forest!  Classic Traveller doesn't have initiative, so everything
happens simultaneously, and we both shot the other and each had an
attribute reduced to zero, so we both fell unconscious.  After ten
minutes we both woke up, and decided to &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; try to kill each other
again.  Since he had Medical-1 he used his medical kit and healed us
both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we tried our hand at what some think is &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;‘s core
activity: shipping cargo to another planet (once we finally figured
out that standard shipping of non-speculative cargo is covered in the
“REVENUE” subsection of “STARSHIP ECONOMICS”, and not near “TRADE AND
COMMERCE” section that we mistakenly thought it would be near).  So,
we rolled up some cargoes and High, Middle, and Low passages for our
arbitrarily chosen world.  Then we worked out all the expenses for our
ship, the standard Type-A Free Trader, to see if we could keep up with
them.  And we could, though there seemed to be little slack.  Success!
This lead us back to the “REQUIRED STARSHIP COMPONENTS” subsection of
the “STARSHIPS” section to figure out how much fuel was available for
maneuvering in-system after a jump.  (10 tons out of 30 tons of fuel
was available for the maneuver drive and the power plant, if I
remember correctly.)  We looked at speculative cargoes a bit, but
didn't actually try them.  We weren't sure how you found the selling
price once you were at your destination.  (A second roll on the
“Actual Value” table?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point we looked at experience and character development in
Classic Traveller.  As far as we can tell, that section is missing
from &lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;, though it is in the 1981 LBBs and &lt;cite&gt;The
Traveller Book&lt;/cite&gt;.  Is it in the 1977 LBBs?  I'll have to check.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we had a lot of fun.  Next time we get together we're going to
design a starship or two and try space combat!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="reflections-afterward"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections Afterward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version of &lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; available at DrivethruRPG.com seems
to be a better scan than the one off the Classic Traveller CD-Rom at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.farfuture.net/"&gt;farfuture.net&lt;/a&gt;, and is arranged in three separate PDF files, one for
each of the three books in the set, which is much more convenient for
printing and for viewing more than one at once on a screen.  Alas,
neither of them had select-able text, each page being a scanned image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had brought my copy of the 1977 edition of Classic Traveller, 3
digest sized (5½×8½ inches) booklets in the classic box, along with
some of the other books/supplements/adventures in that format, the
Quick Link Interactive reprint of the 1981 LBBs in one volume, and the
hardcover edition of &lt;cite&gt;The Traveller Book&lt;/cite&gt;.  I find the pamphlet format
of the original Classic Traveller books charming: they're an easy size
for reading away from the table, they seem to have lasted pretty well
over the years, and it is relatively easy to refer to two of them at
once.  On the other hand, &lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;'s division into a book
of the &lt;cite&gt;Core Rules&lt;/cite&gt;, another book of &lt;cite&gt;Charts and Tables&lt;/cite&gt;, and a final
book with adventures, is very handy at the table where you have room
enough to have both &lt;cite&gt;Core Rules&lt;/cite&gt; open and &lt;cite&gt;Charts and Tables&lt;/cite&gt; open to
the the specific pages for the tables matching what you're reading in
&lt;cite&gt;Core Rules&lt;/cite&gt;.  Also &lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; has a “TYPICAL ACTIVITIES”
checklist on p. 9 of &lt;cite&gt;Charts and Tables&lt;/cite&gt; (that I can't find in the
3LBBs) that basically outlines how you could improvise a Free
Trader-based adventure at the table.  The hardback &lt;cite&gt;The Traveller
Book&lt;/cite&gt; is sturdy and easy to use at the table, but not as convenient as
&lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;‘s split into &lt;cite&gt;Core Rules&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Charts and
Tables&lt;/cite&gt;.  The &lt;cite&gt;Core Rules&lt;/cite&gt; booklet had helpful page references to
&lt;cite&gt;Charts and Tables&lt;/cite&gt; for each of the major sections, and these were
usually a 2-page spread with all (or nearly all) of the tables for the
subject being discussed.  Despite the charming nature of the LBBs, I
think having the separate &lt;cite&gt;Charts and Tables&lt;/cite&gt; book from &lt;cite&gt;Starter
Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; is so convenient that we'll continue using it at the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found it useful to have multiple versions of Traveller available
while reading &lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; to cross-check things: I found an
erratum in &lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>classic traveller</category><category>d&amp;d</category><category>my gaming history</category><category>rpg</category><category>starter traveller</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/16/playing-classic-traveller-in-2020/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 14:11:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>TAS Form 2 Revised at Tales To Astonish</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/15/tas-form-2-revised-at-tales-to-astonish/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Tales to Astonish blog has an &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://talestoastound.wordpress.com/2015/01/16/modified-character-sheet-for-classic-traveller/"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; with a revised version of
TAS Form 2, the character sheet for Traveller.  The article
includes a direct link to a fairly large JPG (in height and width, not
data size) that thus can be printed. &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/15/tas-form-2-revised-at-tales-to-astonish/#seann" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; It has places for each weapon to
write the modifiers for each type of armor, each range, the required
attribute and the Dice Modifier (DM) for if you are under the required
level, the advantageous attribute and the DM for if you meet or are
over the advantageous level, where it delivers a blow, a swing, or a
shot, the weakened blow or swing DM, and the hits of damage a
successful blow does.  Having this information for each weapon on the
character sheet so you don't have to look it up each combat is very
useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="seann"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/15/tas-form-2-revised-at-tales-to-astonish/#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;He links to a blog &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://seann-mcanally.blogspot.com/2010/07/tas-form-2-revised.html"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; that seems to be the original
source of that character sheet, which is on a blog only open to
invited readers now, but the Internet Archive has the blog page
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20180910140807/http://seann-mcanally.blogspot.com/2010/07/tas-form-2-revised.html"&gt;saved&lt;/a&gt;, and on it there is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.gonensworld.com/seann/tas-form2-revised.pdf"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to the PDF.  The Internet
Archive didn't have the PDF saved, but the original link itself
still worked.  I also added &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200316034554/http://www.gonensworld.com/seann/tas-form2-revised.pdf"&gt;it&lt;/a&gt; to the Internet Archive, so
hopefully it is saved forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>character sheet</category><category>classic traveller</category><category>rpg</category><category>traveller</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/15/tas-form-2-revised-at-tales-to-astonish/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 03:22:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Interesting Article Found Recently</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/14/interesting-article-found-recently/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I found an interesting &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dmrbooks.com/test-blog/2019/12/29/sword-amp-planet-a-genre-of-mashups"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sword_and_planet"&gt;Sword &amp;amp; Planet&lt;/a&gt; fiction.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>planetary romance</category><category>sword &amp; planet</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/14/interesting-article-found-recently/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 22:04:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Recent Reading: Under the Green Star</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/13/recent-reading-under-the-green-star/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Under the Green Star&lt;/cite&gt;, by Lin Carter, copyright 1972; DAW Books No. 30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a slight volume, with only 144 pages long, and is a member
of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sword_and_planet"&gt;Sword &amp;amp; Planet&lt;/a&gt; genre.  It is an enjoyable action tale,
obviously influenced by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edgar_Rice_Burroughs"&gt;Edgar Rice Burroughs&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Carter_of_Mars"&gt;John Carter of
Mars&lt;/a&gt; stories.  While perhaps not the equal of the John Carter of
Mars stories, it has attractions of its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While reading &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/01/recent-reading-flame-and-crimson/"&gt;Flame &amp;amp; Crimson&lt;/a&gt; I was reminded of many &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sword_and_sorcery"&gt;Sword &amp;amp;
Sorcery&lt;/a&gt; authors, and was introduced to many new ones.  I decided
that I needed to reread and read anew these authors.  Along the way I
broadened my ambit to include Sword &amp;amp; Planet authors, and have begun
with this Lin Carter volume.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>edgar rice burroughs</category><category>john carter of mars</category><category>lin carter</category><category>sword &amp; planet</category><category>sword &amp; sorcery</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/13/recent-reading-under-the-green-star/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 00:45:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Making digest-sized pages with pandoc and ms output</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/13/making-digest-sized-pages-with-pandoc-and-ms-output/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I wrote this post, I made a last minute check of the options
to &lt;span class="app"&gt;pandoc&lt;/span&gt; and found that the &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--pdf-engine-opt=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; option
does exactly what I want.  How embarrassing.  So I changed this
post, showing both the easy way and the hard way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://pandoc.org/"&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt; to produce digest-sized pages (5½×8½ inches) in PDF
documents from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ReStructuredText"&gt;ReStructuredText&lt;/a&gt;.  I have a &lt;span class="app"&gt;ms&lt;/span&gt; output template,
&lt;span class="file"&gt;digest2.ms&lt;/span&gt; in &lt;span class="file"&gt;~/pandoc/templates&lt;/span&gt; that sets the page
width and page height correctly.  Unfortunately, there is no way to
set the papersize properly in the template. &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/13/making-digest-sized-pages-with-pandoc-and-ms-output/#heirloomtroff" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, &lt;span class="app"&gt;pandoc&lt;/span&gt; has the &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--pdf-engine-opt=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; option to pass
options to the PDF engine that &lt;span class="app"&gt;pandoc&lt;/span&gt; is using, in this case
&lt;span class="app"&gt;pdfroff&lt;/span&gt;.  In the case of &lt;span class="app"&gt;ms&lt;/span&gt; output the thing to do is
pass the argument &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--pdf-engine-opt=-P-p8.5i,5.5i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/13/making-digest-sized-pages-with-pandoc-and-ms-output/#recursively" id="id2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;,
like below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/listings/GNUmakefile.pandoc-digest-pdf-engine-opt.html"&gt;GNUmakefile.pandoc-digest-pdf-engine-opt&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/listings/GNUmakefile.pandoc-digest-pdf-engine-opt"&gt;(Source)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code make"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_5a65b95088cf441a969e67aec685c364-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;%.digest.ms.pdf &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; %.&lt;span class="n"&gt;rst&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_5a65b95088cf441a969e67aec685c364-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        pandoc -s -r rst -w ms --template&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;digest2 &lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;VARIABLES&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_5a65b95088cf441a969e67aec685c364-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;                --output&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$@&lt;/span&gt; --pdf-engine-opt&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;-P-p8.5i,5.5i $&amp;lt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately when I originally had this need for digest pages I
hadn't realized that the &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--pdf-engine-opt=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; option existed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I used &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;pandoc &lt;span class="pre"&gt;--verbose&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; and found the &lt;span class="app"&gt;pdfroff&lt;/span&gt; invocation
&lt;span class="app"&gt;pandoc&lt;/span&gt; uses, and made my &lt;span class="app"&gt;pandoc&lt;/span&gt; invocation output
&lt;span class="app"&gt;ms&lt;/span&gt; instead of PDF, then passed it through a &lt;span class="app"&gt;pdfroff&lt;/span&gt;
command with the added &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-P-p8.5i,5.5i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; argument.  Here's what I put
in my &lt;span class="file"&gt;GNUmakefile&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/listings/GNUmakefile.pandoc-digest-save-ms.html"&gt;GNUmakefile.pandoc-digest-save-ms&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/listings/GNUmakefile.pandoc-digest-save-ms"&gt;(Source)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code make"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_d5dd0856f39440da89e5b4d09932f3bc-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;%.digest.ms.pdf &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; %.&lt;span class="n"&gt;rst&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_d5dd0856f39440da89e5b4d09932f3bc-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        pandoc -s -r rst -w ms -s --template&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;digest2 &lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;VARIABLES&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_d5dd0856f39440da89e5b4d09932f3bc-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;               --output&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$*&lt;/span&gt;.ms $&amp;lt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_d5dd0856f39440da89e5b4d09932f3bc-4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        pdfroff -ms -mpdfmark -e -t -k -KUTF-8 --no-toc-relocation &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_d5dd0856f39440da89e5b4d09932f3bc-5"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;                -P-p8.5i,5.5i &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$*&lt;/span&gt;.ms &amp;gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$@&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or, if you don't care about having the &lt;span class="app"&gt;ms&lt;/span&gt; output for debugging,
you could do it as a pipeline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/listings/GNUmakefile.pandoc-digest-pipeline.html"&gt;GNUmakefile.pandoc-digest-pipeline&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/listings/GNUmakefile.pandoc-digest-pipeline"&gt;(Source)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code make"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_f39314aab2a64179b2106446ce792930-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;%.digest.ms.pdf &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; %.&lt;span class="n"&gt;rst&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_f39314aab2a64179b2106446ce792930-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        pandoc -s -r rst -w ms -s --template&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;digest2 &lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;VARIABLES&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_f39314aab2a64179b2106446ce792930-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;               --output&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;- $&amp;lt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_f39314aab2a64179b2106446ce792930-4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        pdfroff -ms -mpdfmark -e -t -k -KUTF-8 --no-toc-relocation &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_f39314aab2a64179b2106446ce792930-5"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;                -P-p8.5i,5.5i - &amp;gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$@&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are still some instances where this technique of having
&lt;span class="app"&gt;pandoc&lt;/span&gt; output the &lt;span class="app"&gt;ms&lt;/span&gt; source directly and pass it through
&lt;span class="app"&gt;pdfroff&lt;/span&gt; yourself.  For instance, if you have to do some
massaging of the &lt;span class="app"&gt;ms&lt;/span&gt; source, like changing &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;.RS/.RE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; to
&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;.QS/.QE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; to get around the problem with block quotes in &lt;span class="app"&gt;ms&lt;/span&gt;
output in the current &lt;span class="app"&gt;pandoc&lt;/span&gt; release, discussed &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/11/pandoc-discuss-post-can-the-rsre-macros-in-ms-output-be-replaced-with-qsqe/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="heirloomtroff"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/13/making-digest-sized-pages-with-pandoc-and-ms-output/#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heirloom Troff (originally at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://heirloom.sourceforge.net/doctools.html"&gt;H1&lt;/a&gt;, but now &lt;em&gt;I
think&lt;/em&gt; more up to date at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://n-t-roff.github.io/heirloom/doctools.html"&gt;H2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/n-t-roff/heirloom-doctools"&gt;H3&lt;/a&gt;) has the &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;.mediasize&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;.papersize&lt;/code&gt; commands for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="recursively"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/13/making-digest-sized-pages-with-pandoc-and-ms-output/#id2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Amusingly, &lt;span class="app"&gt;pandoc&lt;/span&gt; passes the
&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--pdf-engine-opt=-P-p8.5i,5.5i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; argument to &lt;span class="app"&gt;pdfroff&lt;/span&gt;,
which passes the &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-P-p8.5i,5.5i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; part to &lt;span class="app"&gt;groff&lt;/span&gt;, which
passes the &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-p8.5i,5.5i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; part to the (final) post processor — I'm
not sure if &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;span class="app"&gt;grops&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="app"&gt;gropdf&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>computer</category><category>groff</category><category>make</category><category>ms macros</category><category>pandoc</category><category>pdfroff</category><category>text processing</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/13/making-digest-sized-pages-with-pandoc-and-ms-output/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2020 18:01:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Karl Edward Wagner's Horror Stories</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/12/karl-edward-wagners-horror-stories/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I primarily know &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Edward_Wagner"&gt;Karl Edward Wagner&lt;/a&gt;'s work from his “heroic
fantasy” &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/12/karl-edward-wagners-horror-stories/#hf" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; novels and stories of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Karl_Edward_Wagner#Kane,_the_Mystic_Swordsman"&gt;Kane&lt;/a&gt; which I picked up in
paperback in the mid 1980s, but he was equally talented as a writer
and editor of horror.  I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; read his British Fantasy Award-winning
story &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20110708122112/http://www.thecimmerian.com/the-terror-of-the-absurd-karl-edward-wagners-sticks/"&gt;Sticks&lt;/a&gt; and it had a considerable effect on me, but I don't
remember every reading any of his other horror stories.  The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.isfdb.org/"&gt;ISFDB&lt;/a&gt;
has what seems a very complete &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.isfdb.org/cgi-bin/ea.cgi?153"&gt;page&lt;/a&gt; listing his writings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I aim to fix that.  I've now got copies of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Centipede_Press"&gt;Centipede Press&lt;/a&gt;
collections &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.isfdb.org/cgi-bin/pl.cgi?372768"&gt;Where the Summer Ends&lt;/a&gt; (2012) and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.isfdb.org/cgi-bin/pl.cgi?372769"&gt;Walk on the Wild
Side&lt;/a&gt; (2012) and I'll be reading them soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="hf"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/12/karl-edward-wagners-horror-stories/#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;A term he vastly preferred to “Sword &amp;amp; Sorcery”.  Or maybe he
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://thesilverkey.blogspot.com/2019/10/remembering-karl-edward-wagner-1945-1994.html"&gt;preferred&lt;/a&gt; (note 1 at the bottom of the post) “epic fantasy” or
“dark fantasy”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dark fantasy</category><category>epic fantasy</category><category>fiction</category><category>heroic fantasy</category><category>horror</category><category>kane</category><category>karl edward wagner</category><category>sword &amp; sorcery</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/12/karl-edward-wagners-horror-stories/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2020 19:35:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Dale E. Rippke's Kane Timeline &amp; Reflections on Planned but Unfinished Novels</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/12/dale-e-rippkes-kane-timeline-reflections-on-planned-but-unfinished-novels/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dale E. Rippke over at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thedarkstormfiles.blogspot.com/"&gt;The Darkstorm Files&lt;/a&gt; has a wonderful
timeline, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thedarkstormfiles.blogspot.com/2011/12/lord-of-chaos.html"&gt;Lord of Chaos&lt;/a&gt;, of Kane's adventures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also has two interesting articles on the planned but unfinished
Kane novels, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thedarkstormfiles.blogspot.com/2011/12/reflections-of-midnight-sun-by-dale.html"&gt;Reflections of a Midnight Sun&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thedarkstormfiles.blogspot.com/2011/12/phantasmal-tomes-by-dale-e.html"&gt;Phantasmal Tomes&lt;/a&gt;,
and another interesting article on the Kane/Elric crossover,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thedarkstormfiles.blogspot.com/2011/12/rethinking-gothic-touch.html"&gt;Rethinking The Gothic Touch&lt;/a&gt;, and a world gazetteer of Kane, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thedarkstormfiles.blogspot.com/2015/12/the-age-of-shattered-empires.html"&gt;The Age of
Shattered Empires&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ID-4IjCaXow/U8x0X2HHe7I/AAAAAAAAByI/85ODFbkJSBg/s1600/Kane-Map.jpg"&gt;map&lt;/a&gt; of Kane's world (pinterest tells me that site is
banned because it “leads to spam”) which I gather was drawn after
Dale E. Rippke's original, which I can find no trace of on the
Internet.  I did find his original Kane &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20091127065103/http://home.mchsi.com/~moonblossom/kane.htm"&gt;page&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://archive.org/"&gt;archive.org&lt;/a&gt;, but
sadly none of the linked pages was saved by archive.org.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I stumbled over the post &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sorcerersskull.blogspot.com/2010/02/gaming-kane.html"&gt;Gaming Kane&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sorcerersskull.blogspot.com/"&gt;From The Sorcerer's
Skull&lt;/a&gt; which gives some information about Kane in &lt;cite&gt;Dragon Magazine&lt;/cite&gt;
#26 (June 1979) as a D&amp;amp;D character.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dale e. rippke</category><category>kane</category><category>kane timeline</category><category>karl edward wagner</category><category>planned kane novels</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/12/dale-e-rippkes-kane-timeline-reflections-on-planned-but-unfinished-novels/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2020 15:25:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>pandoc-discuss post: Can the .RS/.RE macros in ms output be replaced with .QS/.QE?</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/11/pandoc-discuss-post-can-the-rsre-macros-in-ms-output-be-replaced-with-qsqe/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;On March 9, 2020 I made a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/pandoc-discuss/zulmB6uujgc"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; on the pandoc-discuss mailing list
that explains some changes to pandoc to better handle block quotes in
ms output, and a workaround for it until the version with changes
comes out, but I forgot to mention it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, use a pipeline like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/listings/GNUmakefile.change-RS-RE-to-QS-QE.html"&gt;GNUmakefile.change-RS-RE-to-QS-QE&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/listings/GNUmakefile.change-RS-RE-to-QS-QE"&gt;(Source)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code make"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_91b358cd08b940bf91a0055197241376-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;%.qs.ms.pdf &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; %.&lt;span class="n"&gt;rst&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_91b358cd08b940bf91a0055197241376-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        pandoc --verbose -r rst -w ms &lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;PANDOCOPTS&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_91b358cd08b940bf91a0055197241376-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;                --output&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;- $&amp;lt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; gsed -e &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'s/^\.RS$$/.QS/'&lt;/span&gt; -e &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'s/^\.RE$$/.QE/'&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="se"&gt;\&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_91b358cd08b940bf91a0055197241376-4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;        pdfroff -ms -mpdfmark -e -t -k -KUTF-8 -i --no-toc-relocation &amp;gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$@&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>.QS/.QE</category><category>.RS/.RE</category><category>block quotes</category><category>groff</category><category>ms macros</category><category>pandoc</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/11/pandoc-discuss-post-can-the-rsre-macros-in-ms-output-be-replaced-with-qsqe/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 12 Mar 2020 00:35:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Steve Tompkins on Sergio Leone and Karl Edward Wagner</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/11/steve-tompkins-on-sergio-leone-and-karl-edward-wagner/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Over at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.leogrin.com/CimmerianBlog/"&gt;The Best of the CIMMERIAN&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dmrbooks.com/test-blog/2019/3/23/steve-tompkins-ten-years-gone"&gt;Steve Tompkins&lt;/a&gt; had a series of
articles in 2008 about Sergio Leone and Karl Edward Wagner: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://leogrin.com/CimmerianBlog/something-to-do-with-deathlessness-part-one-violence-reigns/"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://leogrin.com/CimmerianBlog/something-to-do-with-deathlessness-part-two-eyes-we-dare-not-meet-in-dreams/"&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://leogrin.com/CimmerianBlog/something-to-do-with-deathlessness-part-three-splintered-shards-of-times-reflection/"&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>karl edward wagner</category><category>movies</category><category>sergio leone</category><category>sword &amp; sorcery</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/11/steve-tompkins-on-sergio-leone-and-karl-edward-wagner/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2020 22:37:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Robert E. Howard's The Hyborian Age at Gutenberg.org</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/11/robert-e-howards-the-hyborian-age-at-gutenbergorg/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Here's the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.gutenberg.org"&gt;Project Gutenberg&lt;/a&gt; ebook edition of Robert E. Howard's
essay “The Hyborian Age”, in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/42182"&gt;different versions&lt;/a&gt; and in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.gutenberg.org/files/42182/42182-h/42182-h.htm"&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt;.  (See
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hyborian_Age"&gt;essay&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyborian_Age"&gt;age&lt;/a&gt;.)  All here for later reference.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>fiction</category><category>hyborian age</category><category>robert e. howard</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/11/robert-e-howards-the-hyborian-age-at-gutenbergorg/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2020 21:28:58 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>