<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description>Random musings on books, code, and tabletop games.</description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 03:42:26 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Powers &amp; Perils is Oddly Fascinating</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/14/powers-perils-is-oddly-fascinating/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I bought &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://powersandperils.org/"&gt;Powers &amp;amp; Perils&lt;/a&gt; when it first came out.  While I was
never able to complete building a character, I did have fun reading
the rules and the setting details.  It was oddly fascinating.  So
complicated.  Every so often, I circle back to look at it again,
usually starting at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://powersandperils.org/"&gt;Powers &amp;amp; Perils&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I noticed this time is that a second edition is available on the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://powersandperils.org/books.htm"&gt;rules&lt;/a&gt; page, which includes both a PDF of the complete rules and a
PDF of the &lt;cite&gt;Perilous Lands&lt;/cite&gt; setting information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules are extensively hyperlinked, both in the table on contents
and in cross-references, which should make using such a complicated
system easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now I can't imaging finding a group that would be interested in
playing &lt;cite&gt;Powers &amp;amp; Perils&lt;/cite&gt;, but there is always a lingering impulse to
do something with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>powers &amp; perils</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/14/powers-perils-is-oddly-fascinating/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 03:15:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>BESM 4E - Initial Look</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/12/besm-4e-initial-look/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I took advantage of the Late Pledges option on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/370924922/besm-fourth-edition-big-eyes-small-mouth-rpg"&gt;BESM 4th
Edition&lt;/a&gt; kickstarter and have access to the PDFs they've released so
far.  It is a further refinement of &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt; with some point costs
re-balanced.  Interestingly, the combat system in the BESM 4E core
book is very, very simple, with only an Attack roll versus a Defence
roll.  And the detailed list of skills from &lt;cite&gt;BESM 2ER&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;
have been replaced with 12 “Skill Groups”, separated into three types
based on how expensive the skill group is, rated by utility.  I'm
hoping that the planned &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/370924922/besm-fourth-edition-big-eyes-small-mouth-rpg/posts/2569713"&gt;BESM Extras&lt;/a&gt; book will include more combat
options and the more detailed skill rules.  (The &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E Character
Folio&lt;/cite&gt; seems to indicate the detailed skills will be in &lt;cite&gt;BESM
Extras&lt;/cite&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;'s switch to roll over, which is continued in &lt;cite&gt;BESM
4E&lt;/cite&gt;. There are 25 race templates and 25 class templates, up from &lt;cite&gt;BESM
3E&lt;/cite&gt;'s 20 each, and 20 Humanoid Companions templates that can easily be
converted into race or class templates. &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt; introduces &lt;em&gt;edges&lt;/em&gt;
and &lt;em&gt;obstacles&lt;/em&gt;, which add 1 (for minor) or 2 (for major) dice to a
roll, keeping the 2 best (for edges) or 2 worst (for obstacles),
similar to &lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D 5E&lt;/cite&gt;'s advantage and disadvantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way Standard and Custom Variables and Restrictions in &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;
worked has changed and been renamed.  They are now Enhancements and
Limiters, and instead of having a character point cost they reduce or
increase the Effective Level of an attribute.  For instance, If you
have bought the Weapon Attribute up to 10 Levels and add the Accurate
Weapon Enhancement (1 assignment) and the Area standard Enhancement
for 10 metres radius (2 assignments) and the Range standard
Enhancement for 100 metres (3 assignments) and Ammo Weapon Limiter for
2-3 shots available (2 assignments) makes the Effective Level 6 (10 -
1 - 2 - 3 + 2).  This makes the cost of Enhancements and Limiters
proportional to the base cost of an Attribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like the point costs for things are one-third to one-quarter
those of &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;, which keeps things a little simpler.  Here are the
suggested power levels:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 47%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 53%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Power Level&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Character Points&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sub-Human&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;25-49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adventurer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;50-74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heroic&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;75-99&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mythical&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;100-149&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Superhuman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;150-199&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Superpowered&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;200-249&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Godlike&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;250+&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a 10 page index, which I was happy to see, but alas the
entries are not hyperlinked.  There are copious cross references by
page number, which is very useful, but again not hyperlinked.  The
table of contents is reasonably detailed, though again not
hyperlinked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt; is firmly in the “GMs should fudge dice rolls if it will
make the game better.”  I'm ambivalent about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an 8-page section on Shojo roleplaying that seems
interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “Anime Multiverse” chapter seems identical between 3E and 4E and
presents an interesting short take on a multiverse cosmology, if you
need one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;, &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt; has lots of colors.  Lots and lots of
colors.  (I can see no reason for one column of text on each page to
have a background color.)  I recognize most of the art from earlier
editions.  I liked it then and still like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a simple character sheet, in color and black-and-white
versions in the PDF of the core rulebook, or for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dyskami.ca/downloads/BESM4_character_sheets.pdf"&gt;download&lt;/a&gt; from the
Dyskami &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dyskami.ca/besm.html"&gt;BESM RPG&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the &lt;cite&gt;Dramatis Personae&lt;/cite&gt; PDFs give 15 example characters, with
backgrounds, personalities, discussion of their Attributes and
Defects, three Adventure Hooks, and a personal quote.  These are
useful in seeing how the various Attributes work.  The backgrounds are
tied into the Anime Multiverse from the core book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I think it looks good.  If the things are in &lt;cite&gt;BESM Extras&lt;/cite&gt;
that I hope are there, I can definitely see switching from &lt;cite&gt;BESM 2ER&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>besm</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/12/besm-4e-initial-look/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 18:13:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Slings in RPGs: Often Nerfed</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/07/slings-in-rpgs-often-nerfed/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to reading &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-4541318/Roman-sling-bullets-deadly-44-Magnum.html?fbclid=IwAR2IZhVYW4-4_BcuQDOq2yGXwwurzBd3HNSo1BzN7XUwZLKHF4XZ54yy0VU"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; article, headlined “Roman sling bullets
used against Scottish tribes 2,000 years ago were as deadly as a .44
Magnum”, I was thinking about slings in RPGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've often thought that sling bullets are woefully nerfed in many
RPGs, especially D&amp;amp;D.  In D&amp;amp;D 5E, for instance, they're only 1d4,
while a short bow is 1d6 and a long bow is 1d8. For comparison,
daggers are 1d4 and longswords are 1d8.  In OD&amp;amp;D using Greyhawk's
“Damage Done by Weapon Type” table sling &lt;em&gt;stones&lt;/em&gt; are 1d4, and the
same in B/X D&amp;amp;D's optional “Variable Weapon Damage” table.  AD&amp;amp;D has
sling &lt;em&gt;bullets&lt;/em&gt; as 1d4+1 and sling &lt;em&gt;stones&lt;/em&gt; as 1d4.  D&amp;amp;D 3.5E has them
as 1d4.  So the D&amp;amp;D editions pretty consistently have it as
1d4. Definitely nerfed.  Except in 3-book OD&amp;amp;D and B/X D&amp;amp;D without the
“Variable Weapon Damage” table, where all weapons did 1d6 damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savage_Worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt; slings are Str+d4, while a bow is 2d6.  For
comparison, a dagger is Str+d4 and a long sword is Str+d8.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RuneQuest"&gt;RuneQuest&lt;/a&gt; 2E they are 1d8, similar to a Composite bow at 1d8+1
and broadsword at 1d8.  In Elric! (a member of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stormbringer_(role-playing_game)"&gt;Stormbringer&lt;/a&gt; line
of games, appearing between 4th Edition and 5th Edition, but the rules
were substantially equivalent to Stormbringer 5E; It is relative of
RuneQuest mechanically, part of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Role-Playing"&gt;Basic Roleplaying (BRP)&lt;/a&gt; family
of games) a sling is 1d8+1, similar to a Desert Recurve Bow at 1d8+2,
and a broadsword at 1d8+1.  So in the BRP games they are not nerfed.
In DragonQuest their Damage Modifier is +1, while a dagger is +0, a
long bow is +4 and a broadsword is +4.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talislanta"&gt;Talislanta&lt;/a&gt; 4E a sling's Damage Rating is 4, as is a dagger, while a
long bow and broadsword are 8.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hero_System"&gt;Hero&lt;/a&gt; 5E, sling damage is 1d6+1, same as a medium bow or a light
long bow, while a medium long bow is 1 ½ d6 (that's 1 and ½ d6)
and a heavy long bow is 2d6.  A dagger is 1d6-1 and a broadsword is
1d6+1.  Note that strong enough characters add damage to this based on
how strong they are. Not nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GURPS#Prior_RPG_history"&gt;GURPS&lt;/a&gt; 4E, damage is based on your strength, and the only dice used is
d6.  We'll use an average Strength 10 character as an example.  Their
Thrust damage is 1d-2 and their Swing damage is 1d. An opponent's
Damage Resistance (DR) is subtracted from the rolled damage and any
damage left is multiplied by a modifier for each type of damage.
Piercing damage has a ×1 modifier, cutting has a ×1.5 modifier, and
impaling has a ×2 modifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, sling damage is swing piercing, and the damage for that for our
average character is 1d.  A longbow is thrust+2 impaling. and the
damage for that is 1d, and whatever makes it past DR is doubled.  A
regular bow is thrust+1 impaling, and the damage for that is 1d+1
(minus DR) ×2.  A dagger is thrust-1 impaling, so that is 1d-3 (minus
DR) ×2.  A thrusting broadsword is swing+1 cutting (1d+1 (minus DR)
×1.5) or thrust+2 impaling (1d+2 (minus DR) ×2).  I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; that's
nerfed a little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I'd like to note that when actually playing GURPS I think this is
simpler to do at the table than it sounds like. The damage values for
each attack is figured out at character creation :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fantasy_Trip"&gt;The Fantasy Trip&lt;/a&gt;, which like GURPS only uses d6, slings do
1d-2, small bows do 1d-1, longbows do 1d+2, daggers do 1d-1, and
broadswords do 2d.  A little bit nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Eyes,_Small_Mouth"&gt;Big Eyes Small Mouth (BESM)&lt;/a&gt; 2nd Edition Revised, slings are not
listed, but a long bow does 5 damage, a longsword does 10 damage, and
a dagger does 5 damage.  In BESM 3rd Edition, an average person has an
Attack Combat Value (ACV) of 4 and a Damage Multiplier of 5.  Each weapon has
a Level, which is multiplied by the Damage Multiplier and added to the
ACV for the final damage.  Slings are Level 1 (1 × 5 + 4 = 9), as are
daggers.  Longbows are Level 3 (3 × 5 + 1 = 16), as are longswords.
Definitely nerfed.  (It is the same in &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H%C3%A2rnMaster"&gt;HarnMaster&lt;/a&gt;, weapon impact (damage) for Melee weapons has three
Aspects, Blunt (B), Edge (E), and Point (P).  A dagger's impact is B
1, E 2, P 5, while a broadsword is B 3, E 5, and P 3.  A Missile
weapon's impact depends on the type of missile weapon and the range:
short, medium, long, and extreme.  Slings are Short 4, Medium 3, Long
2, and Extreme 2.  Shortbows are Short 6, Medium 5, Long 4, Extreme 3.
Longbows are Short 8, Medium 8, Long 6, Extreme 5.  Nerfed.  I'll note
that these weapon or missile impacts are added to a Strike Impact is
decided by a table indexed by how well the attacker did on opposed
rolls of attack skill against the defender's skill in Block,
Counterstrike, Dodge, or if the defender ignored the attack. For Melee
attacks this can result in the defender having blocked the attack,
either the attacker or the defender fumbling or stumbling, the
defender gaining a Tactical Advantage (a free action), or either or
both having made a Strike, which generates from 1 to 4 d6s.  For
Missle attacks this can result in a Miss (with a chance to hit an
adjacent combatant, a Wild (a fumble roll), a Block, or a Strike,
which generates from 1 to 3 d6s.  The Armor Protection value is
subtracked and the result is the total Effective Impact, which is then
referenced on the Injury Table to determine where the on the body the
injury is and how serious it is.  There are no Hit Points like D&amp;amp;D or
Wounds like Savage Worlds.  Instead the character accumulates injuries
like “1 Minor Slash Left Upper Arm, 1 injury level”.  The total injury
level determines the difficulty of the character staying conscious and
penalty to any skill roll.  Some of the injuries may immediately kill
the injured character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a good thread by Robert S. Conley (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://batintheattic.blogspot.com/"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.batintheattic.com/index.php"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rpggeek.com/rpgdesigner/22847/robert-conley"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;) on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.rpgpub.com/threads/the-one-where-i-sing-the-praises-of-harnmaster.2363/"&gt;RPG PUB&lt;/a&gt;
that talks some more about HarnMaster combat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In West End Games' &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D6_Fantasy"&gt;D6 Fantasy&lt;/a&gt;, attributes are measured in d6s and 2D
is an average human.  Bow and sling damage and melee damage as d6s
added to a number of d6s determined by your Strength Damage, which is
determined by your Physique attribute or Lifting skill (both measured
in d6s), drop any adds, divided by 2.  So our average human's Strength
Damage is 1D.  Then longbows add +2D+2, shortbows add +1D+2, and
slings add +1D.  For comparison, daggers add +1D and broad/long swords
ad +2D+2.  So, nerfed, although it is hard to make precise
distinctions at this level of resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tunnels_%26_Trolls"&gt;Tunnels &amp;amp; Trolls&lt;/a&gt; only uses d6s and weapons are measured in “Dice +
Adds”, that is the number of d6s to roll and the number of points to
add to the dice total.  The common sling is 2d.  A very light self bow
is 2d, a light self bow is 3d, a medium self bow is 4d, a heavy self
bow is 5d, and a extra-heavy self bow is 6d.  These all have
increasing Strength Required to use the weapon.  For comparison, a
Dirk is 2D+1 and a broadsword is 3d+4.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dragon_Warriors"&gt;Dragon Warriors&lt;/a&gt; weapon damage has two parts: an armor
penetration die (measured in dice: d4, d6, d8, etc.) and damage
points.  The armor penetration die is rolled against the Armour Factor
of the defender's armour: a Gambeson has an Armour Factor of 2 while
Plate has an Armor Factor of 5, and the attacker has to roll &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt;
than the Armour Factor to inflict damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sling has Damage (d6, 3 points) while a Bow has Damage (d6, 4
points).  For comparison, a dagger has Damage (d4, 3 points) and a
sword has Damage (d8, 4 points).  Slightly nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I GM games that I think nerf slings, like D&amp;amp;D, I often use a
house rule that sling bullets are higher damage than sling stones, and
more similar to the damage of a short bow, 1d6, for example.  I may
have been underestimating them and should consider them closer to a
long bow, 1d8, as Chaosium's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Role-Playing"&gt;Basic Roleplaying (BRP)&lt;/a&gt; variants
(RuneQuest, Elric) do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>d&amp;d</category><category>dragonquest</category><category>rpg</category><category>runequest</category><category>slings</category><category>talislanta</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/07/slings-in-rpgs-often-nerfed/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 19:40:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>I often read webcomics backwards</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/27/i-often-read-webcomics-backwards/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I often go a month or two between reading the webcomics I regularly
follow.  When I got back and read them, I usually start with the
current comic and just click the “Prev” button to go back, so I end up
reading significant portions of the story backwards.  Eventually it
all makes sense anyway.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>backwards</category><category>webcomics</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/27/i-often-read-webcomics-backwards/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2019 19:27:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Failing at Ada Again</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/10/failing-at-ada-again/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back on May 20th, 2019 I ordered a copy of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/110742481X/"&gt;Programming in Ada&lt;/a&gt; by
John Barnes and spent some time reading it and working with Ada.  I
get interested again in Ada &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/07/24/2003-07-24-ada-cohen/"&gt;periodically&lt;/a&gt;.  In theory, I ought to like
programming in Ada — it's one of the last remaining widely used members
of the Pascal language family, which I like.  There is a distribution
of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.adacore.com/download"&gt;GNAT Community Edition&lt;/a&gt; for macOS which bundles the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNAT"&gt;GNAT&lt;/a&gt; Ada
compiler and some useful libraries.  But I could never get
comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;GNAT Community Edition for macOS doesn't include GtkAda, so I
couldn't easily write GUI programs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Getting programming libraries was back to the old download and
install it from scratch yourself method.  I find it much easier to
use systems like Chicken Scheme's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.call-cc.org/chicken-projects/egg-index-5.html"&gt;Eggs Unlimited&lt;/a&gt; to find and
install software, or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://ocaml.org/"&gt;OCaml&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://opam.ocaml.org/"&gt;opam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://brew.sh"&gt;Brew&lt;/a&gt;, a package manager for macOS, doesn't include GNAT and
GtkAda. The case is better in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.macports.org/"&gt;MacPorts&lt;/a&gt; and much better on Fedora,
but not good on Ubuntu.  I think there are are fewer packaged Ada
libraries across the open source Unixes in general.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lack of a garbage collector is annoying.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The type system is strict and not very flexible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;And especially irritating to me, I tried using  the Ada mode on GNU &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://elpa.gnu.org/"&gt;Elpa&lt;/a&gt;
and it didn't indent Ada code properly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think in my current programming environment using Ada is still a
difficult task.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ada</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/10/failing-at-ada-again/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 21:24:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Converting my emacs-lisp repository to GIT and putting it online</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/10/converting-my-emacs-lisp-repository-to-git-and-putting-it-online/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've had a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.mercurial-scm.org/"&gt;mercurial&lt;/a&gt; repository for my Emacs Lisp initialization
files since Thursday, Oct 29, 2009, but had actually used it very
little.  Recently I had occasion to untangle my initialization files
somewhat — they had over 12,000 lines of code when I started, and I've
reduced that to 6,137 lines and switched over to using &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://elpa.gnu.org/"&gt;Elpa&lt;/a&gt; packages
for as much stuff as I can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided I'd put it in one of the online repositories, and since I'm
already using &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/tkurtbond"&gt;github.com&lt;/a&gt; for my blog I decided to put it &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/tkurtbond/emacs-lisp"&gt;there&lt;/a&gt;.
But that meant converting it to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://git-scm.com/"&gt;GIT&lt;/a&gt;.  I used the directions &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-and-Other-Systems-Migrating-to-Git#_mercurial"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
using &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/frej/fast-export"&gt;fast-export&lt;/a&gt; which seemed to work fine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>conversion</category><category>emacs lisp</category><category>git</category><category>mercurial</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/10/converting-my-emacs-lisp-repository-to-git-and-putting-it-online/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 19:09:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fixing more broken links in this blog</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/10/fixing-more-broken-links-in-this-blog/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I did another round of searching for broken internal links on this
blog and fixing them.  It took several hours.  Along the way I
annotated some old blog posts with notes from the present and fixed
typos. I think the blog is in pretty good shape now, though.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>blog</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/10/fixing-more-broken-links-in-this-blog/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 10:55:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>macOS Catalina doesn't have a FTP client!</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/09/macos-catalina-doesnt-have-a-ftp-client/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ack!  macOS Catalina doesn't have an FTP client!  Yes, I know it is
terribly insecure, but I only use it inside our firewall to access one
legacy computer system.  I was glad &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://brew.sh/"&gt;brew&lt;/a&gt; had &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://lftp.yar.ru/"&gt;LFTP&lt;/a&gt;, and I figured out
how to use active mode in &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;LFTP&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code bash"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_325baa6af1144cb988025e3826dc01c2-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;set&lt;/span&gt; ftp:passive-mode off
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;because that machine's FTP server only works with active mode.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>catalina</category><category>ftp</category><category>macos</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/09/macos-catalina-doesnt-have-a-ftp-client/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 03:00:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple Podcasts doesn't recognize my iPod Shuffle</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/09/apple-podcasts-doesnt-recognize-my-ipod-shuffle/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, after the most recent upgrade to macOS Catalina my &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPod_Shuffle"&gt;iPod
Shuffle&lt;/a&gt; is not recognized by Apple Podcasts, so I have no way of
loading more podcasts on it.  This is a pity, because it was the only
mp3 player that I actually liked, though I liked the second generation
one better than the fourth generation.  It had no screen, which is an
advantage since I mostly listen to podcasts in the car.  The controls
were very intuitive and were designed to be easy to operate without
looking at them.  They were also reasonably hard to press by
mistake. I shall miss it.  Oh, cruel modern world to have cast it out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also had what appears to be an atypical workflow for the Shuffle.
In iTunes I would manually pick the episodes of the podcasts I was
interested and download them, then copy them manually to the Shuffle.
After I listened to them on the Shuffle I'd delete the download
manually in iTunes.  I never automatically synced the contents of my
Shuffle from iTunes.  With the second generation Shuffle I could copy
the files onto the Shuffle in the specific order I wanted.  The reason
I didn't like the fourth generation Shuffle was it organized the files
alphabetically by podcast name and then by episode date released, and
you had to hit a specific button and listen to it enumerate the
podcasts to move from one podcast to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have another MP3 player, a SanDisk Clip Sport (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://downloads.sandisk.com/downloads/um/clipsport-um.pdf"&gt;manual&lt;/a&gt;) which I
tried some time ago and didn't like as much as the Shuffle.  My main
problem with it was that it was harder to operate without looking at
it: it has a screen, which you have to look at sometimes, and its
controls are not as easy to use without looking at them.  The controls
are also much more sensitive to pressure than the controls on the
Shuffle, so it is easier to activate them accidentally.  (I've
fast forwarded when my arm accidentally touched the controls while
carrying something near my chest.)  And, of course, the interface for
copying podcasts onto the Clip Sport is just copying files onto
external drive the Clip Sport shows up as, into the proper folder for
podcasts. So the “listened to” status and the time into each podcast
you've reached is not something the podcatcher application can help
you track.  And the Clip Sport itself doesn't keep track of where you
were in a particular podcast, though it does remember which one you
were listening to, and where in the podcast you had reached.  It's
really easy to mess up with the forward button and move on to the next
podcast and when you use the reverse button to move back the Clip
Sport has forgotten where in the podcast you were.  Sigh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh well.  I guess I'll have to give the Clip Sport another try.
Luckily I had exported my podcast feed from iTunes before I converted
to macOS Catalina — I had 122 podcast subscriptions.  I installed
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gpodder.github.io/"&gt;gpodder&lt;/a&gt; on my macOS laptop to manage the podcasts. (I was glad a
version of it as a macOS application was available.) It told me that
several of my subscriptions didn't have valid feeds any more, or
simpler weren't there, so now I have 105 podcast subscriptions.  To
download a podcast I can right click on the episode name in the
episode list and choose “Download”.  (It would be convenient if the
not downloaded/downloading/downloaded indication icon was an active
button to download it with one click.)  It has an option, when you
right click on a podcast, to open the download directory for that
podcast, which makes it easy to copy the files to the Clip Sport.  Of
course, they end up on the Clip Sport alphabetically by filename, and
some podcasts have really weird names — I'd swear some of them were
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universally_unique_identifier"&gt;UUID&lt;/a&gt;s.  There is a gpodder option to rename the files to the title
of the episode, which is good when episodes include the episode number
in the title.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>apple podcasts</category><category>clip sport</category><category>ipod</category><category>mp3 player</category><category>shuffle</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/09/apple-podcasts-doesnt-recognize-my-ipod-shuffle/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 00:00:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Playing with Hashlife</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/08/playing-with-hashlife/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;C.P. found &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/stylewarning"&gt;Robert Smith&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/stylewarning/lisp-random/tree/master/hashlife"&gt;implementation&lt;/a&gt; of Bill Gosper's HASHLIFE
algorithm and wanted my help with running it.  I cloned the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/stylewarning/lisp-random"&gt;repo&lt;/a&gt; it
was in and ran &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;sbcl&lt;/code&gt; in the &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;hashlife&lt;/code&gt; directory.  Then I
entered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code lisp"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_52040d4b1e944afc9b8eec8a904c08e0-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;asdf:operate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'asdf:load-op&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'charmlife&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;That resulted in a &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;Component CHARMLIFE not found&lt;/code&gt; error in sbcl.  I
thought that was odd — it was right there in the current directory.  I
looked at &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;asdf:*central-registry*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, and the only thing in it was
the quicklisp directory.  The ASDF &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://common-lisp.net/~mmommer/asdf-howto.shtml#sec11"&gt;howto&lt;/a&gt; showed an example of setting
&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;asdf:*central-registry*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code lisp"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_deb3b08fbc7442b38b159d9038057776-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;setf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;asdf:*central-registry*&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_deb3b08fbc7442b38b159d9038057776-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; Default directories, usually just the ``current directory''&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_deb3b08fbc7442b38b159d9038057776-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;span class="o"&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="vg"&gt;*default-pathname-defaults*&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_deb3b08fbc7442b38b159d9038057776-4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_deb3b08fbc7442b38b159d9038057776-5"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; Additional places where ASDF can find&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_deb3b08fbc7442b38b159d9038057776-6"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;;; system definition files&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_deb3b08fbc7442b38b159d9038057776-7"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="l l-Other"&gt;#p"/home/foo/lisp/systems/"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_deb3b08fbc7442b38b159d9038057776-8"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    &lt;span class="l l-Other"&gt;#p"/usr/share/common-lisp/systems/"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Noticing that it had the symbol &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;*default-pathname-defaults*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; in the
new value, I guessed that it being missing from mine caused ASDF to
not find the system in the current directory.  So I added it and tried
again.  This time ASDF couldn't find &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;cl-charms&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  I guessed and
used &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.quicklisp.org/"&gt;Quicklisp&lt;/a&gt; to load it.  That worked.  Then I looked at
&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;charmlife.lisp&lt;/code&gt; and looked at the &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;main&lt;/code&gt; function and figured out
how to run it and how to interact with the program when it was running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's what I had to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code lisp"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_448de6992ef3498f8acca91b537163cd-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;setf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;asdf:*central-registry*&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_448de6992ef3498f8acca91b537163cd-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;      &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;cons&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'*default-pathname-defaults*&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_448de6992ef3498f8acca91b537163cd-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;            &lt;span class="nv"&gt;asdf:*central-registry*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_448de6992ef3498f8acca91b537163cd-4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;ql:quickload&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"cl-charms"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_448de6992ef3498f8acca91b537163cd-5"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;asdf:operate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'asdf:load-op&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ss"&gt;'charmlife&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_448de6992ef3498f8acca91b537163cd-6"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;charmlife:main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>common lisp</category><category>hashlife</category><category>life</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/08/playing-with-hashlife/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2019 14:43:19 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>