<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about AFF1e)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/aff1e.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 23:30:23 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>AFF1e: Dungeoneer Adventure II: Revenge of the Sorcerer, Part 2</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/01/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-ii-revenge-of-the-sorcerer-part-2/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing “Dungeoneer Adventure II: Revenge of the Sorcerer”,
from &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to
skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwise, starting with the Director:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Director&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — Grimbold Tornhelm, Alexa Wolfrica (L.B. wasn't here)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. — Gordo Brondwyn, Aspen Darkfire (E.A. wasn't here)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They explored the tunnel the centipede came out of, and took the 5
tridents in the nest at the end, in want of some better loot.  Headed
back to the main tunnel and continued on.  They were soon captured by
the Fish People, who tied them up and marched them off toward a
wizard!  After a while they came to an open area, held up by pillars,
and the Fish Men seemed to get very nervous.  A white light appeared
in the open area, and the Fish Men all screamed and ran off, dropping
the characters' possessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The white light gradually resolved into a ghost, who seemed pleasant
enough, and introduced himself as Sargon.  Eventually the PCs made a
deal with Sargon to bring him a magic Crystal of Power that the Fish
Men were keeping in the Temple of Hydana, in return for which Sargon
would tell them how to defeat Xorton Throg.  They snuck into the
temple through a secret door Sargon told them about and killed the
Fish Men priest who was there before he could alert the guards.  They
took the Crystal and a magic sword that was also on the altar.  They
searched the room and found a secret door that lead to stairs that
lead up to a tavern. They found out it was the Mermaid Tavern, and
then escaped back down into the cellar followed by a bouncer, but
escaped down the hidden trap door before he reached the cellar, and he
didn't follow them.  They continued down the stairs to the temple.  They
returned to Sargon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Crystal returned Sargon to life and he told them how to find and
defeat Xorton Throg by getting him to throw a powerful spell at them and
reverse it onto him by bringing out the crystal.  He also restored the
magic sword to good condition.  They followed his advice and killed
Xorton Throg, after killing some skeletons and a skeletal
tyransaurous. They got 300 GP each loot and 4 swords each from the
remains of the skeleton army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They returned to Nicodemus and gave the Crystal to him, then slipped
out of Port Blacksand and back to Salamonis, where the king rewarded
them with 500 GP each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They each got 3 XP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>advanced fighting fantasy</category><category>aff1e</category><category>fighting fantasy</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/01/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-ii-revenge-of-the-sorcerer-part-2/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 20:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>AFF1e: Dungeoneer Adventure II: Revenge of the Sorcerer, Part 1</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/12/27/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-ii-revenge-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing “Dungeoneer Adventure II: Revenge of the Sorcerer”,
from &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to
skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwise, starting with the Director:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Director&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — Grimbold Tornhelm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. — Gordo Brondwyn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;L.B. — Alexa Wolfrica&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. — Aspen Darkfire&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCs attended court, where their part in rescuing Princess Sarissa
was explained, along with the fact that Xortan Throg was still at
large.  The PCs are assigned the task of killing Xortan Throg, and
told to get assistance from Nicodemus in Port Blacksand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCs got 500 GP as a reward for thwarting Xortan Throg's
earlier efforts and for rescuing Princess Sarissa.  They were also
given 60 GP each as an advance for their next efforts, and
a healing potion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help them slip into Port Blacksand in disguise, they were given a
wagon of goods and Merchant Passes for each of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They entered the city and found their way to the Dragon's Tooth Inn,
where they turn over the wagon to their contact, Halim Thrumbar.  He
gave them directions to where Nicodemus lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gordo wanted to gamble in the inn, but Grimbold tried to drag him
away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They went to Nicodemus's and after a little discussion were admitted.
Nicodemus told them that Xortan Throg lives in Port Blacksand, where
he can study the ruins of Carsepolis, in the sewers of Port Blacksand,
and has some dealings with the Fish People. He suggests that they
start by looking near the old sluice-gates down by the docks at dusk.
They do, and see pirates entered the sewers guided by Fish Men, and
decide to follow them at a distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way they fight a giant centipede that attacks them.  Gordo
strikes the blow that kills the centipede.  Aspen is knocked into the
sewer and starts to drown.  Alexa pulls her out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>advanced fighting fantasy</category><category>aff1e</category><category>fighting fantasy</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/12/27/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-ii-revenge-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2012 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>AFF1e: Dungeoneer Adventure I: Tower of the Sorcerer, Part 2</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/13/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-2/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing “Dungeoneer Adventure I: Tower of the Sorcerer”, from
&lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to skip
this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/06/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/"&gt;Previously&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scheduling didn't work out again, so L.B. couldn't join us via Google
Hangouts, alas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwise, starting with the Director:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Director&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — Grimbold Tornhelm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. — Gordo Brondwyn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. — Aspen Darkfire; she also played Alexa Wolfrica, L.B.'s
character, since L.B. couldn't attend&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Griffin's door, they unlocked the door, they unbarred the door,
and then Aspen (at Alexa's suggestion) listens at the door and hears
very interesting things.  They decided to rebar the door and go on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They opened the Giant Lizard's door, saw the saddle, saw the lizard,
and pulled the door shut and barred it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Guardroom, there was a lot of throwing chairs, by both sides.
Alexa was reduced to –1 STAMINA by an opponent's &lt;em class="mech"&gt;Mighty Blow&lt;/em&gt;.
Aspen cast &lt;em class="spell"&gt;Stamina&lt;/em&gt;, bringing Alexa back to 5 STAMINA, and
then Gordo was taken to –1 STAMINA by another opponent's &lt;em class="mech"&gt;Mighty
Blow&lt;/em&gt;, and was brought back to 5 STAMINA by another &lt;em class="spell"&gt;Stamina&lt;/em&gt;
from Aspen.  All through the fight the Ogre had been laughing at the
Heroes and throwing stuff at them that knocked them down, but Aspen
had been steadily sniping at them, and despite one impressive
&lt;em class="ss"&gt;Dodge&lt;/em&gt;, where the Ogre interposed a Goblin haunch from his supper
and blocked an arrow she had steadily brought his STAMINA down.  When
the Orcs were finally disposed of and he threw the table on the Heros,
Aspen was far enough back to escape the spill, and switched from
arrows to &lt;em class="spell"&gt;Fire Bolt&lt;/em&gt;, rolled a 6 for damage, and the Ogre fell
down dead!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the battle Alexa cast &lt;em class="spell"&gt;Stamina&lt;/em&gt; (which for her is
just a natural ability, a “second wind”, not a spell), and got an
&lt;em class="mech"&gt;Oops!&lt;/em&gt;, and E.A. rolled a 13 on the “Oops! Table”, and Alexa
ended up with a pair of small goat horns!  Eventually everybody was
back up to full STAMINA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the sorcerer's chambers they killed Xortan Throg and tried &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt;
to kill evil Prince Barinjhar by pulling their blows, hoping to return
him to his father for rehabilitation.  However, he died while they
were searching Xortan Throg's study and freeing Princess Sarissa.
They found him dead when the returned to the main chamber.  The real
Xortan Throg clued them in, via a vision in the fire in the fireplace,
that they had killed a fake, and that he was still alive and looking
forward to destroying them and Salamonis.  Since they'd killed the
Prince, they decided traveling to Salamonis with Princess Sarissa was
a good idea, and headed back out through the Goblin cave to avoid
Prince Barinjhar's soldiers, outside, and set off in direction of the
fabled city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All characters got &lt;strong&gt;+3 XP&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kids picked up on throwing things pretty quickly; I'll have to see
what other sorts of tactical twists we use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed running this, and the kids had fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>advanced fighting fantasy</category><category>aff1e</category><category>fighting fantasy</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/13/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-2/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2012 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>AFF1e: Dungeoneer Adventure I: Tower of the Sorcerer, Part 1</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/06/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing “Dungeoneer Adventure I: Tower of the Sorcerer”, from
&lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to skip
this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I've mentioned &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#at-my-table"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; I've been trying to use the RPGs derived
from the &lt;cite&gt;Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt; gamebooks for pickup games with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;.
This time around I switched from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#fighting-fantasy-the-introductory-role-playing-game"&gt;Fighting Fantasy — The Introductory
Role-playing Game&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;cite&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/cite&gt;) to Dungeoneer, the first book of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#advanced-fighting-fantasy-aff"&gt;Advanced
Fighting Fantasy&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;cite&gt;AFF1e&lt;/cite&gt;), and started “Dungeoneer Adventure I: Tower of the
Sorcerer”, the first introductory scenario in the book, using the
pre-generated characters from the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to get L.B. in the game through Google Hangouts, but
unfortunately the scheduling didn't work out.  She did pick a
character, Alex Wolfric, and I turned modified the character sheet
turning the character in Alexa Wolfrica.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwise, starting with the Director:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Director&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — Grimbold Tornhelm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. — Gordo Brondwyn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. — Aspen Darkfire; she also played Alexa Wolfrica, L.B.'s
character, since L.B. couldn't attend&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="previously"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Previously&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the occasion that the kids picked out their characters from the
pre-gens I ran a combat between Gordo Brondwyn and Grimbold Tornhelm
so they could see how combat and skills worked.  Gordo threw daggers
at Grimbold and kept out of his reach, but didn't have much recourse
once he'd thrown all his daggers.  I stopped the combat there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="more-rules-familiarization"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More Rules Familiarization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started out with some combat with Aspen Darkfire and Alexa Wolfrica
versus Gordo Brondwyn, so E.A. could see how combat and surprise
rounds worked, and how spells worked, since she was the only player
who would be running spellcasters this episode, and everybody could
see how combat between one character on one side and multiple
characters on the other side worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I had them do some tunnel exploring under an abandoned temple to
show them how some of the other Special Skills worked, including
&lt;em class="ss"&gt;Trap Sense&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em class="ss"&gt;Underground Lore&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em class="ss"&gt;Dark Sense&lt;/em&gt;, and
&lt;em class="ss"&gt;Awareness&lt;/em&gt;.  There were pressure plates, a rolling boulder (ala
Indiana Jones), and a chasm across the tunnel that the boulder herded
them toward.  Aspen and Alexa both noticed the chasm, but Gordo and
Grimbold, behind them, did not, and right out into midair, luckily
crashing into and grabbing hold of the other side of the chasm, and
narrowly missed by the boulder.  Alexa and Aspen helped them up
afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-adventure"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Adventure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kids' characters talked with Prince Barinjhar and Morval for a
while, then headed off down the indicated path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They entered the tunnel, and found the main cave full of Goblins, who
they handily defeated, each killing three.  Alexa managed to pick up
the portcullis blocking the tunnel to the tower all by herself, an
impressive deed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later she broke open both doors to the prisoner cells, freeing Xortan
Throg's experimental subjects, the peasants Rufus (hunchback, one arm
6 inches longer than the other) and Sam (triangular head and deformed
legs).  The characters escorted them back through the portcullis and
provided them with torches and directions out of the tunnel, then
returned to the stairs leading upwards beyond the cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kids seemed to enjoy the game: E.A. and M.A. said so explicitly,
and T.A. liked that the characters started out as super competent
Heroes rather than 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;-level nobodies.  They all liked how they
mowed down the Goblins.  T.A. liked the fact that it added detail to
&lt;cite&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/cite&gt;, since he likes game systems with more detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think next time I'll add some examples of improvised tactical SKILL
use, to show how combat can be something besides just opposed SKILL
rolls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>advanced fighting fantasy</category><category>aff1e</category><category>fighting fantasy</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/06/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2012 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>