<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about advanced fighting fantasy)</title>
  <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/advanced-fighting-fantasy.atom</id>
  <updated>2022-12-06T16:09:30Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/advanced-fighting-fantasy.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/advanced-fighting-fantasy/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Updated my post on slings for Advanced Fighting Fantasy</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/07/19/updated-my-post-on-slings-for-advanced-fighting-fantasy/</id>
    <updated>2021-07-19T23:11:14-04:00</updated>
    <published>2021-07-19T23:11:14-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/07/19/updated-my-post-on-slings-for-advanced-fighting-fantasy/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I updated my post on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/07/slings-in-rpgs-often-nerfed/#aff"&gt;slings&lt;/a&gt; with information about Advanced Fighting
Fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff-1e" label="aff 1e"/>
    <category term="aff-2e" label="aff 2e"/>
    <category term="nerfed" label="nerfed"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
    <category term="slings" label="slings"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>In AFF 1E armour didn't make magic harder</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/07/13/in-aff-1e-armour-didnt-make-magic-harder/</id>
    <updated>2021-07-13T02:47:58-04:00</updated>
    <published>2021-07-13T02:47:58-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/07/13/in-aff-1e-armour-didnt-make-magic-harder/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Going &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/07/06/another-thing-i-really-liked-about-advanced-fighting-fantasy-1e/"&gt;back&lt;/a&gt; to Axel Wolfric, one of the example characters for
Advanced Fighting Fantasy 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; Edition, he has spells
despite being a sorcery-hating barbarian.  This works in AFF 1E
because &lt;strong&gt;every&lt;/strong&gt; Hero and adversary is assumed to be wearing
appropriate armour.  If they &lt;em&gt;remove&lt;/em&gt; their armour then all rolls on
the Damage Table against them adds 2 to the roll.  (See &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoner&lt;/cite&gt;,
p. 163 and 164.  That's also where it talks about shields.)  So any
character can put points into the &lt;em&gt;Magic&lt;/em&gt; Special Skill (at the cost
of reducing their SKILL characteristic by an equal amount), so anybody
can have magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always liked fantasy RPG systems where anybody can cast spells.
(Thanks, &lt;cite&gt;DragonQuest&lt;/cite&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this doesn't work as well in Advanced Fighting Fantasy
2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; Edition.  AFF 2E allows anybody to put points into the
MAGIC characteristic (similarly reducing the number of points that can
be allocated to other characteristics), but casting spells in armour
requires additional magic points, the better the armour the more magic
points must be spent.  (See &lt;cite&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt;, 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt;
Edition, p. 72, bottom of the 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; column and the top of the
2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; column.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder how much it would affect things in a game if I just ignored
that rule?  I'll have to try it sometime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="later"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Later&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, that takes away some from the users of Sorcery in AFF 2E,
who spend STAMINA instead of MAGIC POINTS to cast a completely
different set of spells (many of which require material components)
than Wizardry, &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; can cast in armour.  Hmm.  I'll have to think
about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last edited: 2021-08-09 23:55:19 EDT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Local Variables:
time-stamp-format: "%Y-%02m-%02d %02H:%02M:%02S %Z"
time-stamp-start: "\\*Last edited:[ \t]+\\\\?"
time-stamp-end: "\\*\\\\?\n"
time-stamp-line-limit: -20
End: --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff1e" label="aff1e"/>
    <category term="aff2e" label="aff2e"/>
    <category term="armour" label="armour"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
    <category term="shields" label="shields"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Advanced Fighting Fantasy 2E Combat Companion</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/07/07/advanced-fighting-fantasy-2e-combat-companion/</id>
    <updated>2021-07-07T13:45:09-04:00</updated>
    <published>2021-07-07T13:45:09-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/07/07/advanced-fighting-fantasy-2e-combat-companion/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got my printed copy of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/357479/Combat-Companion"&gt;Combat Companion&lt;/a&gt; for Advanced
Fighting Fantasy 2E a couple of weeks ago.  Overall I liked it.  There
were some typos, but nothing that prevented me from from understanding
the rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the table of contents, with brief notes on what is in them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 1 - Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Optional Rules Checklist&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 2 - Hero Creation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to create Heroes at different power levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 3 - New Skills and Talents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Special Skills:&lt;/strong&gt; Martial Arts, Monster Lores (Animal, Construct,
Demon, Humanoid, Monster, Plant, Undead), Assess Enemy, Running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talents:&lt;/strong&gt; Barfighter, Battle Rider, Combat Caster, Defender, Duelist,
Evasive, Hunter, Inspiring Leader, Lucky Punch, Resilient, Sniper,
Specialist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was most interested in the Martial Arts Skill, which makes unarmed
strikes more and more dangerous at higher skill levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 4 - Alternative Rules&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critical Tables:&lt;/strong&gt; Melee Attack, Martial Arts Attack, Natural
Attack, Missile Attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fumble Tables:&lt;/strong&gt; Martial Arts Attack, Natural Attack, Missile Attack.
(Use the default Fumble Table in the core rulebook is for Melee
Attacks.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alternative Combat Rules:&lt;/strong&gt; Leaving Combat, Revised Armour special
skill requirements, Powerful Blows, Ranged Attack Target Number,
Ubiquitous Dodging, LUCK in Combat, Weapon Reach, Hero Death,
Multiple Monster Attacks, Fluid Modifiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Combat Options:&lt;/strong&gt; Assist, Bypass Armour, Cautious Attack, Charging
Attack, Disarm, Dodging Attack, Double Shot, Frenzied Attack, Stand
Firm, Sniper Shot, Tumbling Attack, Whirlwind Attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 5 - Martial Arts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the schools get a bonus in one set of circumstances, but a
penalty the rest of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Styles:&lt;/strong&gt; Cangui School, Hac-Quel-Rat School, Kappa School, Ki-Rin
School, Kreehul School, Mukade School, Pelagine School, Shikome
School, Tatsu School.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 6 - Combat Magic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new special skill Magic-Warrior Mage and associated new spells:
Bladerune, Combat Reactions, Enhancement, Fireblade, Iceblade,
Lesser Magical Shield, Magical Armour, Protective Field, Accuracy,
Catseyes, Dancing Blade, Duplicate, Greater Magical shield, Weapon
Master, Concussive Blast, Elemental Shield, Avatar of War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 7 - New Equipment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Master Weapons and Armour, Silver Weapons, Acquired Traits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Equipment.&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;strong&gt;General:&lt;/strong&gt; Ball Bearings, Caltrops, Firedust.
&lt;strong&gt;Weapons:&lt;/strong&gt; Armoured Fist, Bastard Sword, Cleaver, Greathammer,
Repeating Crossbow, Scimitar.  &lt;strong&gt;Armour:&lt;/strong&gt; Armoured Fist, Great Helm,
Leather Jack, Scale Armour, Tower Shield.  &lt;strong&gt;War Mounts:&lt;/strong&gt; Giant Ant,
Black Elk, Giant Chameleon, Chaos Steed, Demon Steed, Gunderwal,
Horse (Warhorse), Giant Lizard, Ophidiotaur, Rhinoceros, Wyvern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 8 - Mounted Combat&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discusses the Suitable Mounts, with separate costs for various
levels of training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expands on the Mounted Combat Rules from the core rulebook p. 60.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mounted Combat Options:&lt;/strong&gt; Barge, Break Out, Charging Attack, Rear Up,
Trample, Whirl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rules for Training Mounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chapter 9 - Monster Templates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Templates to be applied to any monster to increase their abilities
and make them a greater threat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Humanoid Templates:&lt;/strong&gt; Berserker, Champion, Chief, Enforcer, Hero,
Scout, Shaman, Veteran, Wizard.  &lt;strong&gt;Monster Templates:&lt;/strong&gt; Chaos-, Dire-,
Enchanted-, Huge-, Large-.  &lt;strong&gt;Construct Templates:&lt;/strong&gt; Charged,
Enhanced, Reinforced.  &lt;strong&gt;Demon Templates:&lt;/strong&gt; Greater, Lord, Major.
&lt;strong&gt;Undead Templates:&lt;/strong&gt;  Ancient-, Burning-, Cursed-.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Appendices&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consolidated Weapon Damage Tracks, Armour Protection Tracks,
Special Skills, Talents, miscellaneous tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think having this would have made AFF more interesting to at least
one group I played it with.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff2e" label="aff2e"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Another Thing I Really Liked About Advanced Fighting Fantasy 1E</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/07/06/another-thing-i-really-liked-about-advanced-fighting-fantasy-1e/</id>
    <updated>2021-07-06T14:34:22-04:00</updated>
    <published>2021-07-06T14:34:22-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/07/06/another-thing-i-really-liked-about-advanced-fighting-fantasy-1e/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I liked that one of the example characters in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fightingfantasy.fandom.com/wiki/Dungeoneer_(book)"&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/a&gt;, Axel Wolfric
(who in my game was played by L.B. as Alexa Wolfrica), has several
abilities which mechanically are spells, but which the character
doesn't regard as magic, something they regard as evil.  Doing this
sort of thing in a fantasy game makes a lot of sense, where characters
might have weird one-off abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I really liked the trade paperback format, and found it convenient
at the table.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff1e" label="aff1e"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I like Advanced Fighting Fantasy</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/06/21/why-i-like-advanced-fighting-fantasy/</id>
    <updated>2021-06-21T12:48:21-04:00</updated>
    <published>2021-06-21T12:48:21-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/06/21/why-i-like-advanced-fighting-fantasy/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have a great fondness for the original &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced_Fighting_Fantasy"&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy&lt;/a&gt;
series, even though I didn’t get them until 2011 or so.  I think the
the Arion Games &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced_Fighting_Fantasy#Advanced_Fighting_Fantasy_titles_published_by_Arion_Games_(2011-present)"&gt;2nd edition&lt;/a&gt; of Advanced Fighting Fantasy is
probably a slightly better game, especially for campaigns (it made a
few adjustments, so character creation is not as random, and a few
other things), but I like it’s layout and typography less.  Also,
there is something about the presentation of the game in &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;
as something for people new to RPGs that made it appealing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is it about the Advanced Fighting Fantasy series that makes
it so cool?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the original &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fighting_Fantasy"&gt;Fighting Fantasy&lt;/a&gt; gamebooks were neat.  The
series was started by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ian_Livingstone"&gt;Ian Livingstone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Jackson_(British_game_designer)"&gt;Steve Jackson&lt;/a&gt;.
(That's the British Steve Jackson, not the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Jackson_(American_game_designer)"&gt;American&lt;/a&gt; one.)  They
included a really simple RPG and a choose your own adventure style
adventure.  That’s where the book is made up at numbered paragraphs,
and when you get to a decision point you can choose among two or more
choices, and those point you at different paragraphs depending on the
choice you make.  For instance, you might have a choice to attack,
retreat to an earlier location, or try something off the wall.  The
addition of the simple RPG added a lot, in my opinion, increasing
replayability.  Anyway, that addition made the Fighting Fantasy books
some of the most popular gamebooks.  Many of them are classics of the
genre.  Most of them are fantasy, and set in the world of Titan, which
was popular enough that there was a world book devoted to it,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titan_(Fighting_Fantasy_book)"&gt;Titan&lt;/a&gt;, and a book of monsters from that word, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fightingfantasy.fandom.com/wiki/Out_of_the_Pit"&gt;Out of the Pit&lt;/a&gt;.
And the art used in illustrating the books was very evocative.  (I
particularly liked Russ Nicholson's art (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://russnicholson.blogspot.com/"&gt;R1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russ_Nicholson"&gt;R2&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mini RPG used in the Fighting Fantasy books was really simple: the
reader’s character has three stats, SKILL, which measures their
general level of skill, STAMINA, which measures the character’s energy
and fitness and how much damage they can take, and LUCK, which
measures how lucky the character is.  SKILL is 1d6+6, STAMINA is
2d6+12, LUCK is 1d6+6.  NPCs and creatures just have SKILL and
STAMINA.  Generally, if the character is trying to do something
outside combat, they roll 2d6 &amp;lt;= their SKILL to succeed.  Combat is
simple, the player rolls 2d6 and adds their skill, their opponent
rolls 2d6 and adds their skill, and the one with the higher total
subtracts 2 from the other’s STAMINA total.  If they tie neither win.
LUCK is used to see how lucky the character is.  For instance, if a
cave is collapsing a character will “Test their LUCK” and roll 2d6 &amp;lt;=
their LUCK to succeed at escaping the collapse.  Every time a
character Tests their LUCK, they reduce their current luck by 1.
Luck can also be used in Combat to increase the wounds they deal or
decrease the wounds they take.  If a character has wounded an
opponent, they can Test their LUCK, and if they are Unlucky the
opponent takes only 1 damage instead of 2, but if they are Lucky the
opponent takes 4 damage instead of 2.  If the character has been
wounded, they can Test their Luck and if Lucky they take only 1
damage, but if they are unlucky they take 3 damage.  So it is a
tradeoff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, that system works well for a gamebook, but doesn’t have enough
detail for most RPG players.  (Although it was published as an intro
RPG, in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fightingfantasy.fandom.com/wiki/Fighting_Fantasy_-_The_Introductory_Role-playing_Game"&gt;Fighting Fantasy: The Introductory Role-playing Game&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy, written by Marc Gascoigne, takes that
framework and adds to it in a way that increases the interesting
detail of the system, without overcomplicating it too much.
Primarily, they add Special Skills, which allow characters to
specialize.  For instance, if a character wanted to be good with a bow
and able to follow people through the forest they’d pick up the
Special Skills Bow and Awareness.  Then, when shooting arrows at
opponents they’d add the rating for their Bow Special Skill to their
SKILL.  When tracking someone through the forest, they’d add their
Awareness Special Skill to their SKILL.  And so on.  A sneaky person
might have the Special Skills Locks, Sleigh of Hand, Sneaking, and
Trap Knowledge.  And so on.  Someone from a noble background might
have Etiquette, Law, and Leadership.  A merchant might have Bargan,
City Lore, and Evaluate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like that characters are competent in general, due to SKILL, but can
be more competent in their areas of interest, using Special Skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can build important NPCs just like characters if you want the
detail, but for run-of-the-mill opponents you can just use SKILL and
STAMINA, so stating out NPCs and opponents is very easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Advanced Fighting Fantasy added more detail to weapons and armor,
still keeping to the use of six sided dice only. So, instead of each
attack doing 2 STAMINA damage every time, you roll a die and depending
on the weapon, that tells you how much damage you do, by looking up
the weapon’s damage chart.  For instance, a dagger might do 1 damage
on a 1 or 2, 2 damage on a 3 through 6, and 3 damage on a 7+ (because
there are a few things that add one to the damage roll, but not
directly to the resulting damage), while a great sword does 2 damage
on 1, 3 damage on a 2 or 3, 4 damage on a 4 or 5, 5 damage on a 6, and
6 damage on a 7+.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, here's the damage for Dagger, Club, and Two-handed Sword:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 68%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 8%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weapon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;7+&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Club&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dagger&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two-handed Sword&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's an interesting way to get variable damage when you are limited
to using just six sided dice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course there was a Magic Special Skill, and if you learned that
you could learn and cast spells, each spell costing an amount of
STAMINA to cast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Advanced Fighting Fantasy had a nice mass combat system, and lots
of setting detail from &lt;cite&gt;Titan&lt;/cite&gt; and opponents from &lt;cite&gt;Out of the Pit&lt;/cite&gt;
(both republished in trade paperback to go with the AFF trade
paperbacks), and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Advanced Fighting Fantasy (AFF1e) was published in three trade
paperback sized books, &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt; (1989), &lt;cite&gt;Blacksand&lt;/cite&gt; (1990), and
&lt;cite&gt;Allansia&lt;/cite&gt; (1994).  &lt;cite&gt;Titan&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Out of the Pit&lt;/cite&gt;, were republished in
1989 in trade paperback sized books to match.  &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt; had the
basic rules, &lt;cite&gt;Blacksand&lt;/cite&gt; added more options and described the city of
Blacksand (a fantasy hive of scum and villainy), and &lt;cite&gt;Allansia&lt;/cite&gt; added
more options and described the continent of Allansia in more detail.
The books were less available in the US than in Great Britain where
they originated, and I never saw them in either bookstores (where they
were sold alongside the Fighting Fantasy gamebooks, hence the trade
paperback size) or in gaming stores.  I got my copies in 2011, when
AFF 2nd Edition came out, for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2011 Graham Bottley of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://arion-games.com/"&gt;Arion Games&lt;/a&gt; got the license to publish a
2nd edition of Advanced Fighting Fantasy (AFF2e).  It was a more
familiar A4 sized book (the international paper size closest to the US
Letter paper size), and while I didn’t particularly care for its
layout choices, I did like the way it made the game better for running
campaigns (character creation was less random, and gave characters
more room for growth), its addition of a MAGIC stat and Magic Points
from which the costs for spells were deducted instead of STAMINA, and
its additions of multiple types of magic (one, Sorcery, was based on a
different gamebook series, the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Jackson%27s_Sorcery!"&gt;Sorcery!&lt;/a&gt; series, from Steve
Jackson), and talents, which were special things a character could do.
I wasn’t so thrilled that priests now used a completely separate magic
system not based on casting spells costing Magic Points; in 1st
Edition priests had different spell lists they could learn from, but
otherwise used the same mechanics as Mages.  AFF2e also added more
detailed armour, which works similarly to damage — roll a die, look up
how much damage is blocked on the armour chart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's Leather Cuirass and Plate Armour:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 67%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 8%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Armour&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;7+&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leather Cuirass&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plate Armour&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AFF1e, by contrast, said that the Damage Table had been carefully
constructed to take into account armour (&lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, p. 163), and
assumed Heroes (the player characters) and their adversaries all wore
armor (&lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, p. 164), and if anyone took off their armour,
then any Damage Rolls (which was an index into a table, remember, not
the actual damage) had 2 added to them.  I expect this explains why
the damage values on the Weapon chart all changed in AFF2e.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I played some AFF 1st Edition games with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;the kids&lt;/a&gt;, which
was a lot of fun.  I also played some AFF 2nd Edition games with some
of them, which was also fun.  I played AFF1E with some of the folks
from work, and it was fun, but they wanted something with more
detailed combat.  I could see why, even AFF2e combat is fairly simple.
They rest of the game they liked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Arion Games has gone on to publish slightly more than a book a
year since 2011, covering the same ground as the original AFF’s three
books did, plus a lot more, including two more monster books (&lt;cite&gt;Beyond
the Pit&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Return to the Pit&lt;/cite&gt;), more options for heroes in the
&lt;cite&gt;Heroes Companion&lt;/cite&gt;, a new area of Titan (&lt;cite&gt;Travels in Arion&lt;/cite&gt;), a
herbal, and a smaller book on creatures from a particular area of
Titan (&lt;cite&gt;Creatures of Mishna&lt;/cite&gt;).  And just recently they published the
&lt;cite&gt;Combat Companion&lt;/cite&gt;, which adds extra options for combat that the
gamers from my work mentioned earlier would have liked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Titan, the world of Fighting Fantasy and Advanced Fighting Fantasy
is a very nice little bit of everything fantasy setting, anchored by
locations and characters from 59 Fighting Fantasy gamebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, Advanced Fighting Fantasy is a role-playing game with
simple mechanics that still provide ample detail, set in an
interesting fantasy world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arion Games also publishes &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/214183/Stellar-Adventures"&gt;Stellar Adventures&lt;/a&gt;, a science fiction
game that uses the same rules, customized for science fiction
adventures, which has several supplements as well.  The &lt;cite&gt;Stellar
Adventures&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt;, 2nd Edition lines are all
available in PDF on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/667/Arion-Games/subcategory/1684_25223/Advanced-Fighting-Fantasy"&gt;DriveThruRPG.com&lt;/a&gt;, with most available in
print-on-demand as well, very important in these days of online
gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last edited: 2021-08-09 12:10:07 EDT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Local Variables:
time-stamp-format: "%Y-%02m-%02d %02H:%02M:%02S %Z"
time-stamp-start: "\\*Last edited:[ \t]+\\\\?"
time-stamp-end: "\\*\\\\?\n"
time-stamp-line-limit: -20
End: --&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="out-of-the-pit" label="out of the pit"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
    <category term="stellar-adventures" label="stellar adventures"/>
    <category term="titan" label="titan"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Slings in RPGs: Often Nerfed</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/07/slings-in-rpgs-often-nerfed/</id>
    <updated>2020-02-07T14:40:23-05:00</updated>
    <published>2020-02-07T14:40:23-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/07/slings-in-rpgs-often-nerfed/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In response to reading &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-4541318/Roman-sling-bullets-deadly-44-Magnum.html?fbclid=IwAR2IZhVYW4-4_BcuQDOq2yGXwwurzBd3HNSo1BzN7XUwZLKHF4XZ54yy0VU"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; article, headlined “Roman sling bullets
used against Scottish tribes 2,000 years ago were as deadly as a .44
Magnum”, I was thinking about slings in RPGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've often thought that sling bullets are woefully nerfed in many
RPGs, especially D&amp;amp;D.  In D&amp;amp;D 5E, for instance, they're only 1d4,
while a short bow is 1d6 and a long bow is 1d8. For comparison,
daggers are 1d4 and longswords are 1d8.  In OD&amp;amp;D using Greyhawk's
“Damage Done by Weapon Type” table sling &lt;em&gt;stones&lt;/em&gt; are 1d4, and the
same in B/X D&amp;amp;D's optional “Variable Weapon Damage” table.  However,
in 3-book OD&amp;amp;D and B/X D&amp;amp;D without the “Variable Weapon Damage” table
all weapons did 1d6 damage, so slings weren't nerfed there.  AD&amp;amp;D 1E
has sling &lt;em&gt;bullets&lt;/em&gt; as 1d4+1 vs. Size Small or Medium and 1d6+1
vs. Size Large.  Sling &lt;em&gt;stones&lt;/em&gt; are 1d4 vs. Size Small, Medium or
Large.  Compare that to arrows at 1d6 vs. Size Small, Medium, or
Large.  But all bows fire twice per round, so they can be doing up to
2d6 per round.  Interestingly, heavy quarrels are 1d4+1 vs. Size Small
or Medium, and 1d6+1 vs. Size Large with the heavy crossbow firing
once in two rounds, while light quarrels are 1d4 vs. all three sizes
and fire every round.  So, nerfed once you take into rates of fire.
D&amp;amp;D 3.5E has sling bullets as 1d4, while longbows are 1d8 and heavy
repeating crossbows are 1d10 and light repeating crossbows are 1d8.
Definitely nerfed.  In D&amp;amp;D 4E slings are 1d6, while longbows are 1d10,
shortbows are 1d8, and a crossbow is 1d8.  There is even more
variability among editions of D&amp;amp;D than I remembered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savage_Worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt; slings are Str+d4, while a bow is 2d6.  For
comparison, a dagger is Str+d4 and a long sword is Str+d8.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RuneQuest"&gt;RuneQuest&lt;/a&gt; 2E they are 1d8, similar to a Composite bow at 1d8+1
and broadsword at 1d8.  In Elric! (a member of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stormbringer_(role-playing_game)"&gt;Stormbringer&lt;/a&gt; line
of games, appearing between 4th Edition and 5th Edition, but the rules
were substantially equivalent to Stormbringer 5E; It is relative of
RuneQuest mechanically, part of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Role-Playing"&gt;Basic Roleplaying (BRP)&lt;/a&gt; family
of games) a sling is 1d8+1, similar to a Desert Recurve Bow at 1d8+2,
and a broadsword at 1d8+1.  So in the BRP games they are not nerfed.
In DragonQuest their Damage Modifier is +1, while a dagger is +0, a
long bow is +4 and a broadsword is +4.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talislanta"&gt;Talislanta&lt;/a&gt; 4E a sling's Damage Rating is 4, as is a dagger, while a
long bow and broadsword are 8.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hero_System"&gt;Hero&lt;/a&gt; 5E, sling damage is 1d6+1, same as a medium bow or a light
long bow, while a medium long bow is 1½ d6 (that's 1 and ½ d6)
and a heavy long bow is 2d6.  A dagger is 1d6-1 and a broadsword is
1d6+1.  Note that strong enough characters add damage to this based on
how strong they are. Not nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GURPS#Prior_RPG_history"&gt;GURPS&lt;/a&gt; 4E, damage is based on your strength, and the only dice used is
d6.  We'll use an average Strength 10 character as an example.  Their
Thrust damage is 1d-2 and their Swing damage is 1d. An opponent's
Damage Resistance (DR) is subtracted from the rolled damage and any
damage left is multiplied by a modifier for each type of damage.
Piercing damage has a ×1 modifier, cutting has a ×1.5 modifier, and
impaling has a ×2 modifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, sling damage is swing piercing, and the damage for that for our
average character is 1d.  A longbow is thrust+2 impaling. and the
damage for that is 1d, and whatever makes it past DR is doubled.  A
regular bow is thrust+1 impaling, and the damage for that is 1d+1
(minus DR) ×2.  A dagger is thrust-1 impaling, so that is 1d-3 (minus
DR) ×2.  A thrusting broadsword is swing+1 cutting (1d+1 (minus DR)
×1.5) or thrust+2 impaling (1d+2 (minus DR) ×2).  I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; that's
nerfed a little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I'd like to note that when actually playing GURPS I think this is
simpler to do at the table than it sounds like. The damage values for
each attack is figured out at character creation :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fantasy_Trip"&gt;The Fantasy Trip&lt;/a&gt;, which like GURPS only uses d6, slings do
1d-2, small bows do 1d-1, longbows do 1d+2, daggers do 1d-1, and
broadswords do 2d.  A little bit nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Eyes,_Small_Mouth"&gt;Big Eyes Small Mouth (BESM)&lt;/a&gt; 2nd Edition Revised, slings are not
listed, but a long bow does 5 damage, a longsword does 10 damage, and
a dagger does 5 damage.  In BESM 3rd Edition, an average person has an
Attack Combat Value (ACV) of 4 and a Damage Multiplier of 5.  Each weapon has
a Level, which is multiplied by the Damage Multiplier and added to the
ACV for the final damage.  Slings are Level 1 (1 × 5 + 4 = 9), as are
daggers.  Longbows are Level 3 (3 × 5 + 1 = 16), as are longswords.
Definitely nerfed.  (It is the same in &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H%C3%A2rnMaster"&gt;HarnMaster&lt;/a&gt;, weapon impact (damage) for Melee weapons has three
Aspects, Blunt (B), Edge (E), and Point (P).  A dagger's impact is B
1, E 2, P 5, while a broadsword is B 3, E 5, and P 3.  A Missile
weapon's impact depends on the type of missile weapon and the range:
short, medium, long, and extreme.  Slings are Short 4, Medium 3, Long
2, and Extreme 2.  Shortbows are Short 6, Medium 5, Long 4, Extreme 3.
Longbows are Short 8, Medium 8, Long 6, Extreme 5.  Nerfed.  I'll note
that these weapon or missile impacts are added to a Strike Impact is
decided by a table indexed by how well the attacker did on opposed
rolls of attack skill against the defender's skill in Block,
Counterstrike, Dodge, or if the defender ignored the attack. For Melee
attacks this can result in the defender having blocked the attack,
either the attacker or the defender fumbling or stumbling, the
defender gaining a Tactical Advantage (a free action), or either or
both having made a Strike, which generates from 1 to 4 d6s.  For
Missle attacks this can result in a Miss (with a chance to hit an
adjacent combatant, a Wild (a fumble roll), a Block, or a Strike,
which generates from 1 to 3 d6s.  The Armor Protection value is
subtracked and the result is the total Effective Impact, which is then
referenced on the Injury Table to determine where the on the body the
injury is and how serious it is.  There are no Hit Points like D&amp;amp;D or
Wounds like Savage Worlds.  Instead the character accumulates injuries
like “1 Minor Slash Left Upper Arm, 1 injury level”.  The total injury
level determines the difficulty of the character staying conscious and
penalty to any skill roll.  Some of the injuries may immediately kill
the injured character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a good thread by Robert S. Conley (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://batintheattic.blogspot.com/"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.batintheattic.com/index.php"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rpggeek.com/rpgdesigner/22847/robert-conley"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;) on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.rpgpub.com/threads/the-one-where-i-sing-the-praises-of-harnmaster.2363/"&gt;RPG PUB&lt;/a&gt;
that talks some more about HarnMaster combat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In West End Games' &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D6_Fantasy"&gt;D6 Fantasy&lt;/a&gt;, attributes are measured in d6s and 2D
is an average human.  Bow and sling damage and melee damage as d6s
added to a number of d6s determined by your Strength Damage, which is
determined by your Physique attribute or Lifting skill (both measured
in d6s), drop any adds, divided by 2.  So our average human's Strength
Damage is 2D.  Then longbows add +2D+2, shortbows add +1D+2, and
slings add +1D.  For comparison, daggers add +1D and broad/long swords
ad +2D+2.  So, nerfed, although it is hard to make precise
distinctions at this level of resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tunnels_%26_Trolls"&gt;Tunnels &amp;amp; Trolls&lt;/a&gt; only uses d6s and weapons are measured in “Dice +
Adds”, that is the number of d6s to roll and the number of points to
add to the dice total.  The common sling is 2d.  A very light self bow
is 2d, a light self bow is 3d, a medium self bow is 4d, a heavy self
bow is 5d, and a extra-heavy self bow is 6d.  These all have
increasing Strength Required to use the weapon.  For comparison, a
Dirk is 2D+1 and a broadsword is 3d+4.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dragon_Warriors"&gt;Dragon Warriors&lt;/a&gt; weapon damage has two parts: an armor
penetration die (measured in dice: d4, d6, d8, etc.) and damage
points.  The armor penetration die is rolled against the Armour Factor
of the defender's armour: a Gambeson has an Armour Factor of 2 while
Plate has an Armor Factor of 5, and the attacker has to roll &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt;
than the Armour Factor to inflict damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sling has Damage (d6, 3 points) while a Bow has Damage (d6, 4
points).  For comparison, a dagger has Damage (d4, 3 points) and a
sword has Damage (d8, 4 points).  Slightly nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I GM games that I think nerf slings, like D&amp;amp;D, I often use a
house rule that sling bullets are higher damage than sling stones, and
more similar to the damage of a short bow, 1d6, for example.  I may
have been underestimating them and should consider them closer to a
long bow, 1d8, as Chaosium's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Role-Playing"&gt;Basic Roleplaying (BRP)&lt;/a&gt; variants
(RuneQuest, Elric, Stormbringer) do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="addendum-classic-traveller-cepheus-engine"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2020-03-14 Addendum — Classic Traveller &amp;amp; Cepheus Engine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wiki.travellerrpg.com/Classic_Traveller"&gt;Classic Traveller&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;cite&gt;Supplement 04 Citizens of the
Imperium&lt;/cite&gt; (1979) has a section on bow weapons, on p. 16!  A sling does
2D wounds and a long bow does 2D wounds also.  For comparison, from
&lt;cite&gt;Book 01 Characters &amp;amp; Combat&lt;/cite&gt; (1981) on p. 47 on the “Range Table” (?)
dagger, blade, cutlass, and sword all do 2D wounds.  Not nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Cepheus Engine&lt;/cite&gt; (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/237247/Cepheus-Engine-RPG"&gt;C1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.paulelliottbooks.com/what-is-cepheus-engine.html"&gt;C2&lt;/a&gt;) doesn't have slings, but a bow is 2D6.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/304840/The-Sword-of-Cepheus"&gt;Sword of Cepheus&lt;/a&gt;, the fantasy variant, has sling as 2D, short bow
as 2D, long bow as 3D, dagger as 2D, and sword as 3D.  Maybe a little
nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="addendum-advanced-fighting-fantasy-1e-2e"&gt;
&lt;span id="aff"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;h2&gt;2021-07-19 Addendum — Advanced Fighting Fantasy 1E &amp;amp; 2E&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AFF 1E (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fightingfantasy.fandom.com/wiki/Dungeoneer_(book)"&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fightingfantasy.fandom.com/wiki/Blacksand_(AFF)"&gt;Blacksand&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fightingfantasy.fandom.com/wiki/Allansia_(book)"&gt;Allansia&lt;/a&gt;) does not, as far as I can tell,
mention slings at all.  Boo, hiss!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/667/Arion-Games/subcategory/1684_25223/Advanced-Fighting-Fantasy"&gt;AFF 2E&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; have slings.  Yay!  In AFF you roll a d6 (the Damage
roll) and look up the result on a table for your weapon.  You can have
bonuses to the d6 Damage roll that can give a result of 7 or above.
Here is the entry for sling, along with longbow, shortbow and sword
for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 31%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 10%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 10%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 10%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 10%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 10%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 10%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 12%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weapon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7+&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sling&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arrow - Longbow&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arrow - Shortbow&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sword&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, slings are a little nerfed.  I think I'll use a house rule that
says the sling damage in the book is for sling stones, and sling
bullets do the same damage as an arrow fired from a shortbow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last edited: 2021-08-09 12:15:25 EDT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Local Variables:
time-stamp-format: "%Y-%02m-%02d %02H:%02M:%02S %Z"
time-stamp-start: "\\*Last edited:[ \t]+\\\\?"
time-stamp-end: "\\*\\\\?\n"
time-stamp-line-limit: -20
End: --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="add-1e" label="ad&amp;d 1e"/>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff-1e" label="aff 1e"/>
    <category term="aff-2e" label="aff 2e"/>
    <category term="bx-dd" label="b/x d&amp;d"/>
    <category term="basic-roleplaying" label="basic roleplaying"/>
    <category term="besm" label="besm"/>
    <category term="big-eyes-small-mouth" label="big eyes small mouth"/>
    <category term="brp" label="brp"/>
    <category term="cepheus-engine" label="cepheus engine"/>
    <category term="classic-traveller" label="classic traveller"/>
    <category term="d6-fantasy" label="d6 fantasy"/>
    <category term="dd" label="d&amp;d"/>
    <category term="dd-35e" label="d&amp;d 3.5e"/>
    <category term="dd-4e" label="d&amp;d 4e"/>
    <category term="dragon-warriors" label="dragon warriors"/>
    <category term="dragonquest" label="dragonquest"/>
    <category term="elric" label="elric!"/>
    <category term="gurps" label="gurps"/>
    <category term="harnmaster" label="harnmaster"/>
    <category term="hero-system" label="hero system"/>
    <category term="nerfed" label="nerfed"/>
    <category term="odd" label="od&amp;d"/>
    <category term="opend6" label="opend6"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
    <category term="runequest" label="runequest"/>
    <category term="savage-worlds" label="savage worlds"/>
    <category term="slings" label="slings"/>
    <category term="stormbringer" label="stormbringer"/>
    <category term="sword-of-cepheus" label="sword of cepheus"/>
    <category term="tt" label="t&amp;t"/>
    <category term="talislanta" label="talislanta"/>
    <category term="tft" label="tft"/>
    <category term="the-fantasy-trip" label="the fantasy trip"/>
    <category term="traveller" label="traveller"/>
    <category term="tunnels-trolls" label="tunnels &amp; trolls"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>AFF1e: Dungeoneer Adventure II: Revenge of the Sorcerer, Part 2</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/01/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-ii-revenge-of-the-sorcerer-part-2/</id>
    <updated>2014-11-01T15:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2014-11-01T15:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/01/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-ii-revenge-of-the-sorcerer-part-2/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing “Dungeoneer Adventure II: Revenge of the Sorcerer”,
from &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to
skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwise, starting with the Director:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Director&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — Grimbold Tornhelm, Alexa Wolfrica (L.B. wasn't here)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. — Gordo Brondwyn, Aspen Darkfire (E.A. wasn't here)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They explored the tunnel the centipede came out of, and took the 5
tridents in the nest at the end, in want of some better loot.  Headed
back to the main tunnel and continued on.  They were soon captured by
the Fish People, who tied them up and marched them off toward a
wizard!  After a while they came to an open area, held up by pillars,
and the Fish Men seemed to get very nervous.  A white light appeared
in the open area, and the Fish Men all screamed and ran off, dropping
the characters' possessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The white light gradually resolved into a ghost, who seemed pleasant
enough, and introduced himself as Sargon.  Eventually the PCs made a
deal with Sargon to bring him a magic Crystal of Power that the Fish
Men were keeping in the Temple of Hydana, in return for which Sargon
would tell them how to defeat Xorton Throg.  They snuck into the
temple through a secret door Sargon told them about and killed the
Fish Men priest who was there before he could alert the guards.  They
took the Crystal and a magic sword that was also on the altar.  They
searched the room and found a secret door that lead to stairs that
lead up to a tavern. They found out it was the Mermaid Tavern, and
then escaped back down into the cellar followed by a bouncer, but
escaped down the hidden trap door before he reached the cellar, and he
didn't follow them.  They continued down the stairs to the temple.  They
returned to Sargon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Crystal returned Sargon to life and he told them how to find and
defeat Xorton Throg by getting him to throw a powerful spell at them and
reverse it onto him by bringing out the crystal.  He also restored the
magic sword to good condition.  They followed his advice and killed
Xorton Throg, after killing some skeletons and a skeletal
tyransaurous. They got 300 GP each loot and 4 swords each from the
remains of the skeleton army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They returned to Nicodemus and gave the Crystal to him, then slipped
out of Port Blacksand and back to Salamonis, where the king rewarded
them with 500 GP each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They each got 3 XP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff1e" label="aff1e"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>AFF1e: Dungeoneer Adventure II: Revenge of the Sorcerer, Part 1</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/12/27/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-ii-revenge-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/</id>
    <updated>2012-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2012-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/12/27/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-ii-revenge-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing “Dungeoneer Adventure II: Revenge of the Sorcerer”,
from &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to
skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwise, starting with the Director:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Director&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — Grimbold Tornhelm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. — Gordo Brondwyn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;L.B. — Alexa Wolfrica&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. — Aspen Darkfire&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCs attended court, where their part in rescuing Princess Sarissa
was explained, along with the fact that Xortan Throg was still at
large.  The PCs are assigned the task of killing Xortan Throg, and
told to get assistance from Nicodemus in Port Blacksand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCs got 500 GP as a reward for thwarting Xortan Throg's
earlier efforts and for rescuing Princess Sarissa.  They were also
given 60 GP each as an advance for their next efforts, and
a healing potion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help them slip into Port Blacksand in disguise, they were given a
wagon of goods and Merchant Passes for each of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They entered the city and found their way to the Dragon's Tooth Inn,
where they turn over the wagon to their contact, Halim Thrumbar.  He
gave them directions to where Nicodemus lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gordo wanted to gamble in the inn, but Grimbold tried to drag him
away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They went to Nicodemus's and after a little discussion were admitted.
Nicodemus told them that Xortan Throg lives in Port Blacksand, where
he can study the ruins of Carsepolis, in the sewers of Port Blacksand,
and has some dealings with the Fish People. He suggests that they
start by looking near the old sluice-gates down by the docks at dusk.
They do, and see pirates entered the sewers guided by Fish Men, and
decide to follow them at a distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way they fight a giant centipede that attacks them.  Gordo
strikes the blow that kills the centipede.  Aspen is knocked into the
sewer and starts to drown.  Alexa pulls her out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff1e" label="aff1e"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lessons from Titan and Advanced Fighting Fantasy</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/16/lessons-from-titan-and-advanced-fighting-fantasy/</id>
    <updated>2012-10-16T10:07:04-05:00</updated>
    <published>2012-10-16T10:07:04-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/16/lessons-from-titan-and-advanced-fighting-fantasy/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back at the beginning of October I started a thread on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rpg.net/"&gt;rpg.net&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://forum.rpg.net/showthread.php?656478-Advanced-Fighting-Fantasy-Distinctive-elements-of-Titan-and-FF-for-an-adventure"&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy: Distinctive elements of Titan and FF for
an adventure?&lt;/a&gt; to collect ideas for what should go in a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.arion-games.com/aff.html"&gt;AFF&lt;/a&gt;
adventure I want to write for my gaming group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I ran across a blog post, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://drbargle.blogspot.co.uk/2012/07/titanic-bullet-points.html"&gt;Known World, Old World: Titanic
Lesson Plan&lt;/a&gt;, which also talks about distinctive elements of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Titan_-_The_Fighting_Fantasy_World"&gt;Titan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff" label="aff"/>
    <category term="ff" label="ff"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="gamebooks" label="gamebooks"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
    <category term="titan" label="titan"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>AFF1e: Dungeoneer Adventure I: Tower of the Sorcerer, Part 2</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/13/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-2/</id>
    <updated>2012-10-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2012-10-13T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/13/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-2/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing “Dungeoneer Adventure I: Tower of the Sorcerer”, from
&lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to skip
this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/06/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/"&gt;Previously&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scheduling didn't work out again, so L.B. couldn't join us via Google
Hangouts, alas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwise, starting with the Director:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Director&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — Grimbold Tornhelm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. — Gordo Brondwyn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. — Aspen Darkfire; she also played Alexa Wolfrica, L.B.'s
character, since L.B. couldn't attend&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Griffin's door, they unlocked the door, they unbarred the door,
and then Aspen (at Alexa's suggestion) listens at the door and hears
very interesting things.  They decided to rebar the door and go on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They opened the Giant Lizard's door, saw the saddle, saw the lizard,
and pulled the door shut and barred it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Guardroom, there was a lot of throwing chairs, by both sides.
Alexa was reduced to –1 STAMINA by an opponent's &lt;span class="mech"&gt;Mighty Blow&lt;/span&gt;.
Aspen cast &lt;span class="spell"&gt;Stamina&lt;/span&gt;, bringing Alexa back to 5 STAMINA, and
then Gordo was taken to –1 STAMINA by another opponent's &lt;span class="mech"&gt;Mighty
Blow&lt;/span&gt;, and was brought back to 5 STAMINA by another &lt;span class="spell"&gt;Stamina&lt;/span&gt;
from Aspen.  All through the fight the Ogre had been laughing at the
Heroes and throwing stuff at them that knocked them down, but Aspen
had been steadily sniping at them, and despite one impressive
&lt;span class="skill"&gt;Dodge&lt;/span&gt;, where the Ogre interposed a Goblin haunch from his supper
and blocked an arrow she had steadily brought his STAMINA down.  When
the Orcs were finally disposed of and he threw the table on the Heros,
Aspen was far enough back to escape the spill, and switched from
arrows to &lt;span class="spell"&gt;Fire Bolt&lt;/span&gt;, rolled a 6 for damage, and the Ogre fell
down dead!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the battle Alexa cast &lt;span class="spell"&gt;Stamina&lt;/span&gt; (which for her is
just a natural ability, a “second wind”, not a spell), and got an
&lt;span class="mech"&gt;Oops!&lt;/span&gt;, and E.A. rolled a 13 on the “Oops! Table”, and Alexa
ended up with a pair of small goat horns!  Eventually everybody was
back up to full STAMINA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the sorcerer's chambers they killed Xortan Throg and tried &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt;
to kill evil Prince Barinjhar by pulling their blows, hoping to return
him to his father for rehabilitation.  However, he died while they
were searching Xortan Throg's study and freeing Princess Sarissa.
They found him dead when the returned to the main chamber.  The real
Xortan Throg clued them in, via a vision in the fire in the fireplace,
that they had killed a fake, and that he was still alive and looking
forward to destroying them and Salamonis.  Since they'd killed the
Prince, they decided traveling to Salamonis with Princess Sarissa was
a good idea, and headed back out through the Goblin cave to avoid
Prince Barinjhar's soldiers, outside, and set off in direction of the
fabled city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All characters got &lt;strong&gt;+3 XP&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kids picked up on throwing things pretty quickly; I'll have to see
what other sorts of tactical twists we use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed running this, and the kids had fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff1e" label="aff1e"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
