<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about art)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/art.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2023 00:36:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Color versus Black and White Art in RPGs</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/07/11/color-versus-black-and-white-art-in-rpgs/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I recently read of a review of an RPG that criticized it for having
black and white art as well as color art.  I think this is misguided,
for several reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I like black and white art.  It takes skill to do properly, and
can be very effective at setting a mood or providing inspiration.  The
RPG that the review mentioned above was about used color art for full
pages or double page spreads, and I thought it was very effective and
attractive.  I also found the use of black and white art on the other
pages, mostly taking up part of a page, very effective and
attractive.  I don't mind the mix, if it is done in a manner that
harmonizes well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I don't mind RPG materials that contain only black and white
art.  Again, if the art is good, then it improves the work, and is
welcome to the eyes.  Some RPG publishers simply don't have the money
for full color art throughout the work.  I don't think it is fair to
criticize their work simply on the basis that it isn't full color.  In
fact, if the work is well written and has no art I'm more likely to
enjoy it and get what I want from it than if it is badly written and
has good art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, if the work has pages that are completely covered from edge
to edge, especially on the paper used for the best reproduction of
color art, the ink is much more likely to smear and leave ugly tracks
from normal handling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fifthly, fully covered pages often have background art
that reduces the readability of the page.  For instance, the brown
background to the first page of chapters in D&amp;amp;D 3E and 3.5E, and the
broken brown lines under the text of the other pages in the chapters
detracts from the readability noticeably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sixthly, when working with maps for RPGs, while I find judicious use
of color to make things stand out is useful, I find that maps that are
fully colored, while impressive to look at, are much harder to adapt
and to record changes on.  When I run “B2 Keep on the Borderlands” or
Jennell Jaquay's “Dark Tower” I can write notes directly on the map
and draw in changes such as collapsed sections or new excavations.  I
can't do that with full color printed art — the changes don't show up
well or in some cases at all, depending on the paper and the ink used.
This is less important if working with digital images, because you can
always use sharply contrasting colors for text and line drawings, but
full color “painted” battle maps are harder to &lt;em&gt;adapt&lt;/em&gt; for most people
because the skill it takes to modify it and have it looks good is much
greater than most people have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I don't think color art, especially full color pages, is a
requirement for good RPG books and materials.  It is impressive when
it is used well, but can actually be a drawback in some cases.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>art</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/07/11/color-versus-black-and-white-art-in-rpgs/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 01:33:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Erol Otus — not just Nostalgia</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/04/25/erol-otus-not-just-nostalgia/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;When I started playing D&amp;amp;D back in my mid teens and the early 1980s I
did not particularly like the artwork of Erol Otus.  I think at the
time I preferred more realistic artwork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I got back into playing D&amp;amp;D regularly with 3.5E, I also started
looking back at the older versions of D&amp;amp;D, and found that I now really
liked Erol Otus's artwork.  I think it is the fever dream aspect of it
that I like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, my enjoyment of Otus's work has nothing to do with nostalgia.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>art</category><category>d&amp;d</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/04/25/erol-otus-not-just-nostalgia/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2011 00:56:19 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>