<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about aubrey and maturin)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/aubrey-and-maturin.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2020 16:46:32 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Recent Viewing</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/11/15/2003-11-15/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Master and Commander: the Far Side of the World&lt;/cite&gt;.  Inspired by the
novels by Patrick O'Brian, directed by Peter Weir, screenplay by Peter
Weir and John Collee.  This is a good movie, providing a vivid and
realistic depiction of life on board a frigate in the British Royal
Navy of the Napoleonic era, and that is its primary merit.  Although it
is not based on any one of the novels directly, drawing on events from
several novels, the resulting story is reasonable, and reasonably
focused.  The movie does capture to some degree the relationship
between Jack Aubrey and Stephen Maturin, but it is less successful
here, since most of the formative events in their friendship take
place long before the movie starts, and would take too much time to
explore in full.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I think &lt;cite class="series"&gt;Aubrey and Maturin&lt;/cite&gt; would have been
better served by a film of the the book &lt;cite&gt;Master and Commander&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>aubrey and maturin</category><category>old blog</category><category>patrick o'brian</category><category>recent viewing</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/11/15/2003-11-15/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2003 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Aubrey and Maturin</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/04/16/2003-04-16/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I think that one of the things that helps Patrick O'Brian's
&lt;cite class="series"&gt;Aubrey and Maturin&lt;/cite&gt; series transcend its genre is the
skillful embedding of the main character's lives in their world.  In
most Napoleonic-era-military genre fiction the characters are seen
through the events of their lives as members of the military
establishment.  For example, all of Rifleman Dodd's actions in
&lt;cite&gt;Rifleman Dodd and the Gun&lt;/cite&gt; by C.S.  Forester concern his military
mission.  Aubrey and Maturin, however, often do things that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt;
part of their military life: music, natural history, local politics,
and so forth, and places them in a wider scope than many characters
from the genre.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>aubrey and maturin</category><category>c.s. forester</category><category>old blog</category><category>patrick o'brian</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/04/16/2003-04-16/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2003 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>