<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about bd&amp;d)</title>
  <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/bdd.atom</id>
  <updated>2023-02-19T19:01:06Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/bdd.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/bdd/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>System Complexity and Gamer Preferences</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/03/15/system-complexity-and-gamer-preferences/</id>
    <updated>2012-03-15T17:31:45-05:00</updated>
    <published>2012-03-15T17:31:45-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/03/15/system-complexity-and-gamer-preferences/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120504101948/http://www.koboldquarterly.com/k/front-page11985.php"&gt;Howling Tower: Complexity and Option Fatigue « Kobold
Quarterly&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.howlingtower.com/"&gt;Steve Winter&lt;/a&gt; (ex-TSR, ex-WotC):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the late 1980s, TSR studied the sales appeal of AD&amp;amp;D compared to
“Basic” D&amp;amp;D (Basic/Expert, B/X, or BECMI, as it’s now known). The
common wisdom was that Basic D&amp;amp;D was the best choice for beginning
players because it was a simpler game—it had fewer rules. New and
inexperienced players, however, actually saw that paucity of rules as
a drawback. To them, Basic D&amp;amp;D was more complex than Advanced D&amp;amp;D, not
less, because the DM and players were faced with more situations that
had no clear solution. In contrast, AD&amp;amp;D told you exactly (or
approximately) what to do in an enormous range of situations. The
answers might be hard to find, but they were in those books
somewhere. Extensive rules that covered more situations translated to
the DM spending more time flipping pages in a search for answers but
less time sifting through options. The end result was a perception
that while AD&amp;amp;D had more rules than Basic D&amp;amp;D, all those rules made it
easier to play. Inexperienced players liked the confidence that came
from AD&amp;amp;D providing all the answers, so they gravitated toward
AD&amp;amp;D. Experienced players liked having open-ended options and were the
main audience for Basic D&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That result surprised a lot of people inside TSR. It was an
eye-opener, and it affected design and marketing philosophy for years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See also the comments &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.howlingtower.com/2012/03/complexity-and-option-fatigue.html"&gt;thread&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="add" label="ad&amp;d"/>
    <category term="bdd" label="bd&amp;d"/>
    <category term="dd" label="d&amp;d"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
    <category term="steve-winter" label="steve winter"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Keep on the Borderlands Session C4: Character Generation, part 4</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/05/03/c004-ll/</id>
    <updated>2009-05-03T13:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2009-05-03T13:45:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/05/03/c004-ll/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;L.B. was in town visiting the other side of her family, so I got to
take her to dinner Sunday.  Since she would be playing in the
Labyrinth Lord game with the rest of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt; when she was here this
summer, I thought we could create her characters during lunch.  She
thought that was a great idea.  She did wonder if people would mind us
playing D&amp;amp;D in the restaurant, but I told her nobody would mind —
everybody in the restaurant would be talking anyway, and all we'd be
doing is talking and rolling dice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was pretty scatterbrained that morning, and had managed to forget my
dice, but we stopped at &lt;span class="store"&gt;Dollar Tree&lt;/span&gt; on the way to the
restaurant and picked up some cheap &lt;span class="dice"&gt;d6&lt;/span&gt;s.  While we were
waiting to be seated she started rolling up her characters, and
finished rolling them up after we'd been seated and while we were
waiting to be served.  I'd also managed to forget a pencil, but did
have a pen, so instead of writing directly on the character sheets we
wrote on some 3×5 cards I had. She'd already decided she wanted one to
be a sorceress and one to be a halfling, so we figured out which
scores should go to which character &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/05/03/c004-ll/#arranging-scores" id="footnote-reference-1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;1&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and then
rolled &lt;span class="dice"&gt;4d6&lt;/span&gt; for the characters' starting money, since we didn't
have &lt;span class="dice"&gt;d8&lt;/span&gt;s.  After that we worked through buying equipment for
her halfling, mostly while waiting for our food.  Once the food
arrived, though, not much else happened but eating. &lt;strong&gt;:-)&lt;/strong&gt; She did
have a name for her magic-user/sorceress, Alice the Sorceress, and we
decided she'd pick a name for her halfling later, perhaps the next
time she's at my house.  (I‘ve got some books that would be useful for
inspiration for halfling names.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, after lunch when I dropped her off I gave her some character
sheets and told her I'd e-mail her the information about the
characters — that way we'd both have the information — and that we'd
buy equipment for Alice the Sorceress later.  After I dropped her off
I stopped by the office and sent the e-mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="footnote-list brackets"&gt;
&lt;aside class="footnote brackets" id="arranging-scores" role="note"&gt;
&lt;span class="label"&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a role="doc-backlink" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/05/03/c004-ll/#footnote-reference-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than the strict “Roll 3d6 in order for
STR, DEX, CON, INT, WIS, and CHA” that &lt;em&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/em&gt; gives as
the main way to generate abilities, I let the kids roll 3d6 and
arrange the scores the way they liked them, and let them roll a
couple of extra characters and take the highest set of scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</summary>
    <category term="actual-play" label="actual-play"/>
    <category term="b2" label="b2"/>
    <category term="bdd" label="bd&amp;d"/>
    <category term="gaming" label="gaming"/>
    <category term="keep-on-the-borderlands" label="keep on the borderlands"/>
    <category term="kids" label="kids"/>
    <category term="labyrinth-lord" label="labyrinth lord"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
