<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about building)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_building.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 15:17:49 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Books about Building: Part 1</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/08/17/books-about-building-part-1/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I got interested in the idea of building a house when I stumbled
across cob houses on the web.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>building</category><category>cob</category><category>natural building</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/08/17/books-about-building-part-1/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2008 17:18:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What do I want in a house?</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/08/10/what-do-i-want-in-a-house/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A house that fits me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A house were I can leave the windows open and not worry about rain coming in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A house that's warm in the winter and cool in the summer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A house that has enough room for my books.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(More later.)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>building</category><category>house</category><category>life</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/08/10/what-do-i-want-in-a-house/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2008 04:51:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Building</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/08/10/building/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I've decided that I want to build a house.  I've been reading
various books about different construction techniques, and this
weekend I wandered over the family farm, once with my Dad and once
with my friend H.H. looking at various possible building sites.  The
most picturesque sites, unfortunately, are rather remote, and would
involve long, long driveways and long runs of new electric lines.
There are several locations closer to electricity and the road that
would be nice building spots, but some are closer to neighbors than
I'd prefer, and another is someplace already in use by the farm, so
there's not anything that immediately jumps to mind as perfect.  I
plan to spend a lot of time over the next year observing condiations
at each of the better sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd like to use a many materials as I can from the family farm in the
construction of the building.  I'm considering building a cob house,
which has a number of very attractive features, but which depends
heavily on the local soil for construction material.  Cob houses need
a clay-sand mix.  Almost all of the local soils have plenty of clay,
according to the soil survey, but rather than sand the rest of the
soil is mostly silt, which seems like it would be a problem for Cob.
I can probably obtain sand relatively economically to add to the mix,
but will the existing silt make the mix too weak?  That's what I have
to find out.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>building</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/08/10/building/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2008 02:46:03 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>