<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about gaming)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 18:49:44 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Fantastic Medieval Campaigns</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/fantastic-medieval-campaigns/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://traversefantasy.itch.io/fmc"&gt;Fantastic Medieval Campaigns&lt;/a&gt; (FMC) by Marcia B. is a great
retroclone and restatement of Original D&amp;amp;D: it's clearly written, well
organized, contains a table of contents for the book and then a table
of contents in each section, has a glossary and indices for monsters,
spells, and tables, and uses the color backgrounds of the pages well
to make finding the different sections easy.  The art is charming and
appropriate for a OD&amp;amp;D retroclone, and the layout is clean.  It
includes a retroclone of Chainmail, which is rare.  I like it very
much.  And the PDF is free!  I got the hardback color book and read it
and want to run at least two campaigns with it, the first using its
Chainmail retroclone, “Chain of Command”, and the next with the d20
based combat system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, but, but!  The back cover text says “problematize our
preconceptions of a text (or even a whole genre)” and mentions
“falsehood”.  And the contents of the last page of the text,
which is labeled “This Page Intentionally Left Blank.”, are certainly
not blank, and expresses opinions of D&amp;amp;D that must surely
offend many D&amp;amp;D players.  I'll quote it here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fantastic Medieval Campaigns is a recreation of what is at best a
deeply reactionary work of art—if not a fascist one altogether.
We recognize now that the authors, as well as some who were in
their circle, thought quite badly of women, indigenous people, and
others.  However, we should let the text speak for itself because
it speaks loudly.  The book is a guide to fantastic war game
campaigns, where the players take on the roles of
sword-and-sorcery adventurers seeking greatness.  They will begin
in the Underworld simply slaying monsters and retrieving treasure
in the form of gold, legal tender ready to be exchanged on the
open market.  As characters accumulate treasure, they acquire
superhuman abilities and political power to boot.  Heroes,
Thaumaturgists, and Bishops emerge from their colonial katabasis
conquering land by which to become Lords, Wizards, and Patriarchs.
They will establish sanctuaries and, with their vast armies, turn
the tide against the forces of evil chaos they have always
‘resisted' thus far.  The setting in general is one where might
makes right, where the violent extraction of resources is central
to the protagonists activity, and where participation in these
things is rewarded with not only political power bu the sort of
physiological and supernatural power which colonizers and fascists
imagined themselves to have.  It is a mirror to the desires and
fantasies of its original authors, a bunch of white, straight,
cissexual men in the Midwest, just as it is a reflection of boys'
pulp literature at the height of American culture about crushing
one's enemies and driving them before oneself and hearing the
lamentations of their women.  All in all, this work was not
written in a vacuum nor did it spring fully formed from the heads
of its creators.  You can use this book however you like or even
attempt to play it with the mindset of a midcentury American  man,
but do not delude yourself with regards to its content or to the
fantasy which it encodes.  That being said, as the author, I offer
up this work for analysis, critique, and reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, that certainly put the coyote in the chicken house!  It is
definitely controversial in OSR circles.  Honestly, though, I'm not
sure &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; furor was worth following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just want to point out that, whatever the author's opinions of D&amp;amp;D,
they wrote FMC so they could more easily understand the rules, so
they could better play D&amp;amp;D with their friends, and according to a
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.paperspencils.com/fantastic-medieval-campaigns/"&gt;friend of theirs&lt;/a&gt; they spent over a year working on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of whether I agree with their views or not, FMC is a well
written game and its author should be proud of it.  It can be used to
run some great games.  If you don't agree with the author's views, just
ignore them and &lt;strong&gt;play the game&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>controversy</category><category>dnd</category><category>fantastic medieval campaigns</category><category>fmc</category><category>odnd</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/fantastic-medieval-campaigns/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 04:13:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Fantasy Trip</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;[I should have posted this a long time ago.  Oh well.  At least it's
being posted now.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="back-in-the-day"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Back in the Day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really wish I'd gotten a copy of Steve Jackson's Melee in 1977 and
Wizard in 1978 when they were published by Metagaming, and Advanced
Melee, Advanced Wizard, and In the Labyrinth when those came out in
1980. Together those make up the game The Fantasy Trip (TFT). Melee and
Wizard are the basic combat and magic rules, published as board games.
Advanced Melee and Advanced Wizard are the full combat rules. And In the
Labyrinth adds all the other stuff necessary for a complete roleplaying
game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metagaming_Concepts"&gt;Metagaming at
Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Melee_board_game_1977.png"&gt;Melee, 1977&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Wizard_Metagaming_1978.png"&gt;Wizard, 1978&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I never saw them in any store in my area. I did meet one person who
played The Fantasy Trip, probably in 1981 or so, but never got to talk
to him about it; we were both quite busy with other things at the summer
camp from hell. Wish he'd brought his rulebooks…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melee_(game)"&gt;Melee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wizard_(board_game)"&gt;Wizard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fantasy_Trip"&gt;The Fantasy Trip at
Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="modern-times"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Modern Times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I picked up my copies of the original Advanced Melee, Advanced Wizard,
and In the Labyrinth much more recently. Probably in 2018 or so. Thank
goodness for Internet game stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Advanced_Melee_1980.jpg"&gt;Advanced Melee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Advanced_Wizard_1980.jpg"&gt;Advanced Wizard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_In_the_Labyrinth_1980.jpg"&gt;In the Labyrinth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="legacy-edition"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Legacy Edition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018 Steve Jackson Games kickstarted The Fantasy Trip Legacy Edition,
with new versions of Melee and Wizard and a new version of In the
Labyrinth that contained everything from the original as well as the
rules from Advanced Melee and Advanced Wizard, and I backed it, and got
a LOT of stuff. I liked the new edition of The Fantasy Trip a lot. But I
didn't have a good chance to play it for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some interesting changes from the Metagaming version of The
Fantasy Trip to the Legacy edition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Melee_Legacy_Edition.jpg"&gt;Melee, Legacy Edition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Wizard_Legacy_Edition.jpg"&gt;Wizard, Legacy Edition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_In_the_Labyrinth_Legacy_Edition.jpg"&gt;In the Labyrinth, Legacy
Edition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Pocket_Box_Melee_and_Wizard.png"&gt;Pocket Box edition of Melee &amp;amp;
Wizard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sjgames.com/"&gt;Steve Jackson Games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fantasy_Trip#The_Fantasy_Trip_Legacy_Edition_2"&gt;The Fantasy Trip Legacy
Edition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://thefantasytrip.game/"&gt;The Fantasy Trip at Steve Jackson
Games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.hcobb.com/tft/legacy_first.html"&gt;The Fantasy Trip, Legacy vs First edition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the PDF of Melee is available from Steve Jackson Games for free!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://warehouse23.com/products/the-fantasy-trip-melee"&gt;Melee for
Free!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="playing-melee-online"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Playing Melee Online&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got to play Melee online in 2023 and had fun. It took a while for
everybody to get used to the way combat works — it's a hex-based
tactical combat system that strives for verisimilitude, and is quite
different from anything that the others were used to. This group has
been playing Mini Six from Antipaladin Games mostly before this, with some
of Deep7's 1PGs thrown in; previously we've played a lot of Labyrinth
Lord from Goblinoid Games and Savage Worlds from Pinnacle Entertainment
Group, and while Savage Worlds is played on a square grid battle map,
it's still not tactical in the same way as TFT, DragonQuest from SPI, or
GURPS from Steve Jackson Games. I played a lot of DragonQuest and GURPS
(TFT's younger relative) in the 80s and 90s, which both have hex-grid
based tactical combat, and enjoyed them a lot, so TFT's system wasn't
such a shock to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/144558/Mini-Six-Bare-Bones-Edition"&gt;Mini
Six&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.antipaladingames.com/"&gt;AntiPaladin Games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/tkurtbond/Minimal-OpenD6"&gt;Minimal OpenD6 SRD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://deep7.com/"&gt;Deep7 Press&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://deep7.com/?page_id=664"&gt;1PG - 1 Page Games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/78524/Advanced-Edition-Companion-Labyrinth-Lord-noart-version"&gt;Labyrinth Lord (free no-art
version)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/64331/Labyrinth-Lord-Revised-Edition-noart-version"&gt;Advanced Edition Companion for Labyrinth Lord (free no-art
version)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/259983/Advanced-Labyrinth-Lord-Dragon-Cover"&gt;Advanced Labyrinth
Lord&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.goblinoidgames.com/"&gt;Goblinoid Games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://peginc.com/"&gt;Pinnacle Entertainment Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savage_Worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds at
Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DragonQuest"&gt;DragonQuest at
Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sjgames.com/gurps/"&gt;GURPS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I backed Steve Jackson Games' TFT kickstarters as well as Gaming
Ballistic's kickstarters, so I've got a lot of the stuff published for
The Fantasy Trip Legacy Edition. It's a pity I'm not playing face to
face these days, because most of those kickstarters were loaded with
neat stuff for face to face play — megahex tiles, cards of all kinds,
neoprene battle maps, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gamingballistic.com/"&gt;Gaming Ballistic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gaming-ballistic.myshopify.com/collections/all?filter.v.price.gte=&amp;amp;filter.v.price.lte=&amp;amp;filter.p.m.my_fields.collection=The+Fantasy+Trip"&gt;Gaming Ballistic's TFT
products&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continued playing Melee online, and added in Wizard.  Eventually I
plan to start running a TFT campaign using the many adventures
released by Steve Jackson Games and Gaming Ballistic. And they've
released a number of solo adventures, so I plan on playing those as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now I'm working on a hexcrawl using TFT, to be played somewhat
in the West Marches style, with a long past apocalypse that destroyed
a huge empire.  The idea is the people are moving back into the areas
left abandoned for centuries after the apocalypse due to inimical
magic that has recently retreated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="description-of-melee"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description of Melee&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Melee is a person-to-person combat board game. A Melee character has two
stats, Strength (ST) and Dexterity (DX), and a secondary stat, Movement
Allowance (MA). ST determines what weapons you can use. DX determines
how hard it is for you to hit your opponents: you roll 3d6 equal to or
under your (adjusted) DX to hit (noted as a 3/DX roll). MA determines
how fast you can move on the hex grid battlemap. Human characters start
with 8 in ST and DX and have 8 more points to allocate however you want
between the two, for a total of 24 points. There are NO dump stats, and
every combination of stats, weapons, and armor results in quite
differently performing characters, which interact with the combat system
in interesting ways. Unarmored humans start with MA 10, but most armor
reduces a characters MA. Armor also lowers your DX. When you are
familiar with the system you and one or more friends can create
characters and fight a battle in an hour or so, but when you are first
starting out it will take a while to internalize the system so it runs
quickly. Melee also has various nonhuman opponents: bears, wolves, giant
snakes, giants, and gargoyles. It also has fantasy fighters: elves,
dwarves, halflings, orcs, goblins, and hobgoblins, who start with
different minimum ST and DX, sometimes with different maximum total
points. Characters gain experience and when they have 100 they can trade
it in for a point to increase ST or DX. Up to 8 points can be gained
this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="description-of-wizard"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description of Wizard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wizard adds a third stat, Intelligence (IQ), and a lot of
spells. You've still only got 8 points to spend between the three
stats, so characters can have 32 points total.  Wizards can know as
many spells as they have IQ points. Spells are rated by the IQ
necessary to learn them.  Wizards roll 3/DX to see if they've cast
their spells correctly.  Each spell has a ST cost to cast; some spells
can be continued with a different ST cost.  Typically if a wizard
fails the roll to cast the spell it still costs 1 ST.  Wizard also adds
a couple more monsters, Myrmidons, and two sizes of dragon: 4 hex and 7
hex. Wizard is scaled well to work beside Melee as a person to person
combat board game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="description-of-in-the-labyrinth"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description of In the Labyrinth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Labyrinth (ITL) adds some elaborations to combat and magic, as
well as all the things necessary to make The Fantasy Trip a complete
roleplaying game. In particular, they add talents, non-magical
abilities. Talents allow a character to try to do something, or makes
something anybody can do easier. Talents are rated by the IQ necessary
to learn them, and by how many points IQ points they cost to get at
character creation. Talents cost twice as much (in IQ points at
character creation and in XP after character creation) for wizards as
they do regular “hero” characters. Regular heroes can learn spells, but
they cost triple (in IQ points at character creation and in XP after
character creation) what they cost wizards. ITL adds lots of spells,
many of which have non-combat uses, as you'd expect from an RPG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding out if your character succeeds is a matter of rolling dice
equal to or lower than your stats. For easy things you roll 2 dice or
even 1 die, normal things take 3 dice, while difficult things take 4,
5, even or &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; dice! Look at the chance to roll a 14 or less on
6d6! Yikes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/d6-dice-odds.png" src="https://tkurtbond.github.io/d6-dice-odds.png"&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="random-things-i-like-about-tft"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Random things I like about TFT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Melee and Wizard are relatively simple person to person combat board
games that serve as an introduction to the full system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Uses only six sided dice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tactical hex grid based combat with verisimilitude.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The RPG is a complete fantasy roleplaying game in one 176 page book.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;ITL's one page Quick Character Generation lets you quickly roll up a
new character with interesting features and personality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Table of Jobs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating Magic Items.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;ITL's mini setting of the Village of Bendwyn and Southern Elyntia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Characters, even complicated ones, fit on a 3×5 card.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's got a free app, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://thefantasytrip.game/products/accessories/tft-helper/"&gt;TFT Helper&lt;/a&gt;,
for iOS and Android!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>android</category><category>ios</category><category>melee</category><category>metagaming</category><category>sjg</category><category>steve jackson games</category><category>tft</category><category>tft helper</category><category>the fantasy trip</category><category>wizard</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 22:31:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>D&amp;D Retro-clones and Neo-clones</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;(See &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/pages/rpg-vocabulary/#Retro-clone"&gt;Retro-clone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/pages/rpg-vocabulary/#Neo-clone"&gt;Neo-clone&lt;/a&gt; for definitions.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the retro-clones and neo-clones mentioned below are games with
which I have some familiarity.  Many of them I've played.  The others
I've read.  All of them have something interesting to recommend them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was a time when Wizards of the Coast hadn't made old versions of
D&amp;amp;D available easily, and the retro-clones were very important then.
Even now some retro-clones or neo-clones have better presentation than
the original rules (&lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#old-school-essentials-classic-fantasy"&gt;Old-School Essentials Classic Fantasy&lt;/a&gt;) or
present a simpler version of classic rules (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/64332/Labyrinth-Lord-Revised-Edition"&gt;Labyrinth Lord: Revised
Edition&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/78523/Advanced-Edition-Companion-Labyrinth-Lord"&gt;Advanced Edition Companion&lt;/a&gt; for AD&amp;amp;D), or provide
additional details and further development of a particular D&amp;amp;D version
(&lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#adventurer-conqueror-king-system"&gt;Adventurer, Conqueror, King System&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, of course, if you are playing with kids who might not have the
money to buy PDFs of old versions of D&amp;amp;D, many of the retro-clones are
available in PDF or online legally for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="what-do-you-want"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What do you want?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want a simple, clear, exceptionally well organized and presented
version of the classic &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Basic_Set#1981_revision"&gt;Basic/Expert D&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt; (B/X) rules?  See
&lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#old-school-essentials-classic-fantasy"&gt;Old-School Essentials Classic Fantasy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want races separate from classes and the most of the extra classes,
races, and many spells from AD&amp;amp;D 1E, all on the 1 to 14 level scale of
the classic &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Basic_Set#1981_revision"&gt;Basic/Expert D&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt; (B/X)?  See &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#old-school-essentials-advanced-fantasy"&gt;Old-School Essentials
Advanced Fantasy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want to play classic AD&amp;amp;D 1E modules with all races, classes, and most
spells from AD&amp;amp;D 1E, on a mostly 1 to 20 level scale, with 9&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; level magic user spells and 7&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; cleric spells, but
with simpler mechanics?  See &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#labyrinth-lord-revised-edition-advanced-edition-companion"&gt;Labyrinth Lord: Revised Edition &amp;amp;
Advanced Edition Companion&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#advanced-labyrinth-lord"&gt;Advanced Labyrinth Lord&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want something almost like AD&amp;amp;D 1E?  See &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#osric"&gt;OSRIC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want something that feels like &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_(1974)"&gt;Original D&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt;, just what was in the
three original Little Brown Books?  See &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/matthew-finch/swords-wizardry-whitebox-rules-softcover/paperback/product-1wzw887q.html?page=1&amp;amp;pageSize=4"&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Whitebox&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;cite&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/cite&gt;'s &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#original-edition-characters"&gt;Original Edition Characters&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#delving-deeper"&gt;Delving Deeper&lt;/a&gt;,
or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://traversefantasy.itch.io/fmc"&gt;Fantastic Medieval Campaigns&lt;/a&gt;, especially if you want a
Chainmail-style system for individual and mass combat.  Do you also
want the thief class?  See &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/matthew-finch/swords-wizardry-core-rules-softcover/paperback/product-1yvrdzg2.html?"&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Core&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want something that feels like &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_(1974)"&gt;Original D&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt;, just before AD&amp;amp;D 1E
came out, with the races and classes (except for gnomes and
illusionists) and spells familiar from AD&amp;amp;D 1E, but simpler, on a
mostly 1 to 20+ level scale, with up to 9&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; level magic user
spells and 7&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; level cleric spells?  See &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.froggodgames.com/product/swords-wizardry-complete-rulebook/"&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry
Complete&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the 1 to 14 level scale and the lower hit dice of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Basic_Set#1981_revision"&gt;Basic/Expert
D&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt;, but want more detailed rules, especially magic research,
economics, and domain play (the D&amp;amp;D end game, where the players build
strongholds and rule), with rules for building campaign specific
classes and races, and don't mind some slightly different mechanics?
See the &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#adventurer-conqueror-king-system"&gt;Adventurer, Conqueror, King System&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Want the 1 to 36 level scale of Frank Mentzer's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Basic_Set#1983_revision"&gt;BECMI&lt;/a&gt; rules or Aaron
Allston's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Basic_Set#1991_revision"&gt;Rules Cyclopedia&lt;/a&gt;?  See &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#dark-dungeons"&gt;Dark Dungeons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="basic-fantasy"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Basic Fantasy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; I looked at &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.basicfantasy.org/"&gt;Basic Fantasy&lt;/a&gt; first, but it wasn't what I
was looking for at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All its PDFs are free, and the print on demand books are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt;
inexpensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I notice that the character class tables all go to
level 20.  I wonder if this is a residual artifact of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Editions_of_Dungeons_%26_Dragons#Dungeons_&amp;amp;_Dragons_3rd_edition"&gt;D&amp;amp;D 3E&lt;/a&gt;
character classes going to level 20, since it doesn't match the B/X
model that that is implied by the Basic Fantasy website with the
statement “The Basic Fantasy Role-Playing Game is a rules-light game
system modeled on the classic RPG rules of the early 1980's.”
Compare that to Labyrinth Lord's rescaling of B/X to match
AD&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="labyrinth-lord"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="original-edition-characters"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Original Edition Characters&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Original Edition Characters&lt;/cite&gt; is a player's supplement for &lt;cite&gt;Labyrinth
Lord&lt;/cite&gt; that provides characters more like those of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_(1974)"&gt;Original D&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt;.
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/58558/Original-Edition-Characters?manufacturers_id=760"&gt;OECPDF&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/daniel-proctor/original-edition-characters/paperback/product-1yvzkkwd.html"&gt;OECPOD&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="labyrinth-lord-revised-edition-advanced-edition-companion"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Labyrinth Lord: Revised Edition &amp;amp; Advanced Edition Companion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/64332/Labyrinth-Lord-Revised-Edition"&gt;Labyrinth Lord: Revised Edition&lt;/a&gt; (LLRE; PDF and POD) has been
criticized for not being a completely faithful retro-clone of the
Moldvay/Cook/Marsh Basic/Expert D&amp;amp;D rules (B/X), I think it still
holds a useful spot.  The changes that were made in the revised
version of &lt;cite&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/cite&gt; made it easier to be used with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/78523/Advanced-Edition-Companion-Labyrinth-Lord"&gt;Advanced
Edition Companion&lt;/a&gt; (AEC).  It adapted the 1–14 level scale of B/X to
the scale of AD&amp;amp;D 1E, generally about 20 levels, and with AEC it added
the separate races and the additional classes, spells, monsters, and
magic items of AD&amp;amp;D 1E.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are versions of LLRE and AEC available for free: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/64331/Labyrinth-Lord-Revised-Edition-noart-version"&gt;No-art LLRE&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/78524/Advanced-Edition-Companion-Labyrinth-Lord-noart-version"&gt;no-art AEC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="advanced-labyrinth-lord"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Advanced Labyrinth Lord&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Advanced Labyrinth Lord&lt;/cite&gt; compiles the information from &lt;cite&gt;Labyrinth
Lord: Revised Edition&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Advanced Edition Companion&lt;/cite&gt; into one
convenient book (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/259983/Advanced-Labyrinth-Lord-Dragon-Cover"&gt;ALL&lt;/a&gt;, PDF and POD).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="swords-wizardry"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry&lt;/cite&gt; is inspired by the original D&amp;amp;D booklets and
associated magazine articles.  It comes in various versions, depending
on how much of the supplemental material you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find the original D&amp;amp;D booklets very interesting from a historical
standpoint, but find &lt;cite&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry&lt;/cite&gt; easier to use at the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="swords-wizardry-white-box"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry White Box&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is inspired by the original three booklets of D&amp;amp;D, so it includes
only the Fighter, Magic-User, and Cleric, so it strips away everything
but the absolute essentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="swords-wizardry-core"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Core&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This adds the thief class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="swords-wizardry-complete"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry Complete&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking to play something with the feel of AD&amp;amp;D 1E, but
want something even simpler than &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/64332/Labyrinth-Lord-Revised-Edition"&gt;Labyrinth Lord: Revised Edition&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/78523/Advanced-Edition-Companion-Labyrinth-Lord"&gt;Advanced Edition Companion&lt;/a&gt;, this is an excellent choice, as
long as you don't need half-orcs, gnomes or illusionists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like how it discusses different ways to interpret the original
rules, often giving more than option for use with S&amp;amp;WC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="old-school-essentials"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Old-School Essentials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Old-School Essentials&lt;/cite&gt; (OSE) is published by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/"&gt;Necrotic Gnome&lt;/a&gt; in two
flavors so far, &lt;cite&gt;Classic Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Advanced Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, OSE has improved the clarity, organization, and
presentation of its rules over the already very good &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Basic_Set#1981_revision"&gt;Basic/Expert
D&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt; rules.&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#although" id="footnote-reference-1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;1&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; As well as clear wording it uses layout and
typography to enhance its presentation of the rules, from the use of
one and two page spreads that completely cover one subject to the
careful use of bold and bullet points to call out important
information, OSE really shines.  The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/adventures"&gt;adventures&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/"&gt;Necrotic
Gnome&lt;/a&gt; have produced for it (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/adventures/products/the-hole-in-the-oak"&gt;The Hole in the Oak&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/adventures/products/dolmenwood-winters-daughter"&gt;Winter's
Daughter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/adventures/products/the-incandescent-grottoes"&gt;The Incandescent Grottoes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/adventures/products/the-isle-of-the-plangent-mage"&gt;The Isle of the Plangent
Mage&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/adventures/products/halls-of-the-blood-king"&gt;Halls of the Blood King&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/adventures/products/holy-mountain-shaker"&gt;Holy Mountain Shaker&lt;/a&gt;)
continue this excellent use of layout, bold, and bullet points to
present their information clearly and without the dreaded “wall of
text” or “read aloud text”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="footnote-list brackets"&gt;
&lt;aside class="footnote brackets" id="although" role="doc-footnote"&gt;
&lt;span class="label"&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a role="doc-backlink" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/#footnote-reference-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although it has been suggested to me that while OSE excels &lt;em&gt;as a
reference&lt;/em&gt;, the original &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Basic_Set#1981_revision"&gt;Basic/Expert D&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt; rules have more
explanations of why things work as they do.  I need to reread them
in light of this suggestion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="old-school-essentials-classic-fantasy"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Old-School Essentials Classic Fantasy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Old-School Essentials Classic Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt; (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/rules/products/old-school-essentials-rules-tome"&gt;OSECF&lt;/a&gt;) is the best organized
and presented version of the classic rules from the Moldvay/Cook/Marsh
Basic/Expert D&amp;amp;D sets.  This is the game that I wish had been around
when I started playing.  There is an SRD (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/"&gt;OSESRD&lt;/a&gt;).  I particularly
like the Classic Fantasy Rules Tome, which collects everything into
one substantial book, but there is also a version split into multiple
books covering separate sections of the rules, so that the magic-user
can look up his spells while the fighter is looking at the combat
rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="old-school-essentials-advanced-fantasy"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Old-School Essentials Advanced Fantasy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Old-School Essentials Advanced Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt; is the best organized and
presented version of the ideas of the classic rules from 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; edition AD&amp;amp;D, scaled to match the 1–14 level scope of the
Moldvay/Cook/Marsh Basic/Expert D&amp;amp;D sets.  If I was starting a new
D&amp;amp;D campaign these are the rules I'd use, all things being equal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Old-School Essentials Advanced Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt; is collected in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/rules/products/old-school-essentials-advanced-fantasy-players-tome"&gt;Player's
Tome&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/rules/products/old-school-essentials-advanced-fantasy-referees-tome"&gt;Referee's Tome&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="adventurer-conqueror-king-system"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Adventurer, Conqueror, King System&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The name of this system is usually abbreviated as ACKS.  One of its
explicit design goals for to supply more rules for the end of game of
Original D&amp;amp;D, where the players built strongholds and ruled, hence the
name.  It also has a more detailed economic system.  It is more
complicated than OD&amp;amp;D or B/X, but in a completely different way than
AD&amp;amp;D 1E.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It uses some different mechanics, especially for “to hit” roles, so it
might be considered a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/pages/rpg-vocabulary/#Neo-clone"&gt;Neo-Clone&lt;/a&gt;, but it is inspired by B/X D&amp;amp;D, and
keeps to the same 1 to 14 level scale of B/X.  I particularly like its
rules for building your own campaign specific classes from the
&lt;cite&gt;Player's Companion&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="osric"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;OSRIC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I looked at OSRIC (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.knights-n-knaves.com/osric/"&gt;OSRICKnK&lt;/a&gt;), (a free &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.knights-n-knaves.com/osric/download.html"&gt;OSRIC PDF&lt;/a&gt; is available, as
well as a free PDF of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/2411/Usherwood-Publishing"&gt;Usherwood Publishing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/111392/OSRIC-Pocket-SRD-PDF"&gt;OSRIC Pocket SRD&lt;/a&gt;
version) but was more interested in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Basic_Set#1981_revision"&gt;Basic/Expert D&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt; retroclones at
the time.  I think it is a well written, organized, and presented
restatement of AD&amp;amp;D 1E.  The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.facebook.com/BlackBladePublishing/"&gt;Black Blade Publishing&lt;/a&gt; print edition
is a very nice offset printed volume with a sewn spine.  The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/2411/Usherwood-Publishing"&gt;Usherwood
Publishing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/111392/OSRIC-Pocket-SRD-PDF"&gt;OSRIC Pocket SRD&lt;/a&gt; (PDF, POD) is quite affordable.  I
just wish OSRIC wasn't missing some of the classes.  (I miss the Monk
in particular.)  I was also surprised by how many of the little quirks
and restrictions of AD&amp;amp;D 1E have been ironed out, although many
remain.  &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/2411/Usherwood-Publishing"&gt;Usherwood Publishing&lt;/a&gt; has some supplements that add some of
the missing classes, though I'm not sure I like all their versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="dark-dungeons"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Dark Dungeons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Dark Dungeons&lt;/cite&gt; is available in a free PDF (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/177410/Dark-Dungeons"&gt;DDFreePDF&lt;/a&gt;), a hardback
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/blacky-the-blackball/dark-dungeons-hardback/hardcover/product-16q68rge.html"&gt;DDHardback&lt;/a&gt;), a paperback (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/blacky-the-blackball/dark-dungeons-softcover/paperback/product-18n6qr25.html"&gt;DDPaperback&lt;/a&gt;), and a deluxe color edition
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/blacky-the-blackball/dark-dungeons-deluxe/hardcover/product-1gvq52ng.html"&gt;DDDeluxe&lt;/a&gt;).  It has a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gurbintrollgames.wordpress.com/dark-dungeons/"&gt;home page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a retro-clone of The D&amp;amp;D Rules Cyclopedia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Dark Dungeons&lt;/cite&gt; does have &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.thepiazza.org.uk/bb/viewtopic.php?p=60695#p60695"&gt;changes&lt;/a&gt; from the Rules Cyclopedia,
integrating some optional rules, extrapolating, clarifying and
adjusting other rules, and integrating rules for Immortals.  It does
not include the Mystara setting and cosmology elements.  The
monsters &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.thepiazza.org.uk/bb/viewtopic.php?p=60126#p60126"&gt;differ&lt;/a&gt; somewhat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="delving-deeper"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Delving Deeper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Delving Deeper&lt;/cite&gt; (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.immersiveink.com/?page_id=22"&gt;Delving Deeper Description&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://forum.immersiveink.com/viewtopic.php?f=15&amp;amp;t=113"&gt;Delving Deeper
PDFs&lt;/a&gt;) works very hard to be as faithful to the 3 Little Brown Books
of Original D&amp;amp;D (along with the relevant partsof Chainmail, with which
they were intended to be used) as possible.  The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.lulu.com/shop/simon-j-bull/delving-deeper-reference-rules-compendium/paperback/product-21911339.html"&gt;Delving Deeper V4
Reference Rules Compendium&lt;/a&gt; is a Print-on-Demand version of the three
booklets.  There is also the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ddo.immersiveink.com/dd.html"&gt;Delving Deeper SRD&lt;/a&gt;.  I was
particularly interested in Version 5 of &lt;cite&gt;Delving Deeper&lt;/cite&gt;, as that
promised annotated versions of the three booklets, but only &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://download.immersiveink.com/DDRefRulesV5/HeroesAndMagicV5_Gamma_Annotated_Alpha_20180722.pdf"&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; of the
annotated versions has been completed so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="fantastic-medieval-campaigns"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fantastic Medieval Campaigns&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://traversefantasy.itch.io/fmc"&gt;Fantastic Medieval Campaigns&lt;/a&gt; (FMC) is a retro-clone of the three
Little Brown Books of Original D&amp;amp;D and Chainmail, available for free
in PDF and in print on demand.  I gather it was something the author
did just so they had something easier to follow when playing OD&amp;amp;D with
friends.  I'm glad they made it available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike a lot of clones of OD&amp;amp;D, FMC, as well as including the familiar
d20-based combat system, also includes a clone of the Chainmail rules,
which can be used either for individual combat or mass combat.  FMC is
very well organized, and could be used by someone new to D&amp;amp;D to
play in a group where everybody else is using the OD&amp;amp;D rulebooks, or
as the rules for a whole group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, FMC is a very well written and organized restatement of
Chainmail and the three LBB.  The layout and design are uncluttered;
the art is charming, the organization is superb, and the writing is
clear.  The physical book is an excellent example of the possibilities
of print-on-demand, with the different sections of the book printed on
different colored backgrounds, making finding specific sections much
easier.  The table of the contents at the front of the book is
reasonably detailed, and each section has its own table of contents as
its first page, opposite the title page for the section.  The book has
a glossary and indexes for monsters, spells, and tables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end this is an exceptional restatement and clarification of the
original game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="see-also"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;See Also&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want even more information, you could try &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://taxidermicowlbear.weebly.com/"&gt;Taxidermic
Owlbear&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://taxidermicowlbear.weebly.com/dd-retroclones.html"&gt;D&amp;amp;D Retroclones&lt;/a&gt; (and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://taxidermicowlbear.weebly.com/downloads.html"&gt;downloads&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_retro-clones"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also retro-clones of games other than D&amp;amp;D, if you go
looking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>acks</category><category>advanced edition companion</category><category>adventurer conqueror king system</category><category>aec</category><category>fantastic medieval campaigns</category><category>fmc</category><category>labyrinth lord</category><category>ll</category><category>neo-clone</category><category>old-school essentials</category><category>ose</category><category>retro-clone</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/dnd-retro-clones-and-neo-clones/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 18:43:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Explicit Procedures in Old School Essentials and Swords &amp; Wizardry</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/20/explicit-procedures-in-old-school-essentials-and-swords-wizardry/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Nothing I'm saying in this post is new; I'm sure other people have
pointed out these or similar things in the past.  I'm just trying to
get my observation down in concrete form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone asked why &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/pages/about-old-school-essentials"&gt;Old School
Essentials&lt;/a&gt;
(OSE) gets so much attention in the OSR world, and why &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.mythmeregames.com/collections/swords-wizardry"&gt;Swords &amp;amp;
Wizardry&lt;/a&gt;
(S&amp;amp;W) doesn’t get more. I like both games very much, and have pledged
for Kickstarters for both systems, but I think that the reason that OSE
gets more attention, especially from from those new to the OSR, is that
OSE provides specific and explicit step by step procedures for running
the game structures that are at the center of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the article from 6 September 2019, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://thealexandrian.net/wordpress/43568/roleplaying-games/game-structures-addendum-system-matters"&gt;Game Structures — Addendum:
System
Matters&lt;/a&gt;,
Justin Alexander talks about how the dungeon crawling structure that
originates in Original D&amp;amp;D is completely missing from D&amp;amp;D 5E. (The rest
of his series on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://thealexandrian.net/wordpress/15126/roleplaying-games/game-structures"&gt;Game
Structures&lt;/a&gt;
is also interesting.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OSE preserves (as you’d expect as a faithful retroclone of the 1981
Moldvay/Cook/Marsh Basic/Expert edition of D&amp;amp;D) those procedures and
presents them clearly. Much of the same information is available in
Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry, but the reader has to synthesize most of it from
paragraphs and pages of text, rather than having a step by step
procedure to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="old-school-essentials"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Old School Essentials.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at OSE, there are at least 12 procedures, most of which have
explicit lists of steps.  (Page numbers are to the &lt;em&gt;OSE Classic Fantasy
Rules Tome&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;†  Indicates step by step procedures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Dungeon_Adventuring"&gt;Dungeon
Adventuring†&lt;/a&gt;, p. 108.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Wilderness_Adventuring"&gt;Wilderness
Adventuring†&lt;/a&gt;, p. 110.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Waterborne_Adventuring"&gt;Waterbourne
Adventuring†&lt;/a&gt;, p. 112.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Encounters"&gt;Encounters†&lt;/a&gt;, p. 114.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Evasion_and_Pursuit"&gt;Evasion and
Pursuit&lt;/a&gt;, p. 116.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Combat#Combat_Sequence_Per_Round"&gt;Combat†&lt;/a&gt;, p. 120.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Strongholds#Construction"&gt;Strongholds,
Construction†&lt;/a&gt;, p. 134.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Adventuring_Parties"&gt;NPC Encounters, Adventuring
Parties&lt;/a&gt;, p. 212.  While not numbered this is sequence of bullet listed procedures for generating Basic and Expert NPC parties, and High Level NPCs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Designing_a_Dungeon"&gt;Designing a
Dungeon†&lt;/a&gt;, p. 224.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Designing_a_Wilderness"&gt;Designing a
Wilderness†&lt;/a&gt;, p. 226.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Designing_a_Base_Town"&gt;Designing a Base
Town†&lt;/a&gt;, p. 227.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Placing_Treasure"&gt;Placing Treasure&lt;/a&gt;, p. 229.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="loweralpha simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Sentient_Swords"&gt;Rolling a Sentient Sword†&lt;/a&gt;, p. 272.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/index.php/Sentient_Swords#Control_Checks"&gt;Control Checks†&lt;/a&gt;, p. 273.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that OSE has an online
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oldschoolessentials.necroticgnome.com/srd/"&gt;SRD&lt;/a&gt; is also an
advantage; S&amp;amp;W used to, but it is not currently available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="swords-wizardry"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="procedures"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Procedures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry there are only a couple of step-by-step procedures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Initiative and Order of Battle†, p. 35.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generating a Random Treasure Hoard†, p. 131.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry’s other procedures have to be extracted from one or
more paragraphs of running text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;S&amp;amp;W tends to rely on examples and prose descriptions rather than
explicitly numbered or bulleted lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Monsters in the Dungeon”, p. 76, could easily have been part of a
“Randomly Stoking the Dungeon” procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare OSE's “Wilderness Adventuring” to S&amp;amp;W's “Wilderness
Adventures” on p. 80.  The OSE version is an explicit list of steps,
while the S&amp;amp;W version is a wall of text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare OSE‘s bulleted Morale procedure, p. 123, to S&amp;amp;W's, p. 39.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare OSE's “Rolling a Sentient Sword” to S&amp;amp;W's “Intelligent
Weapons”, p. 138.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sure that the designer of S&amp;amp;W and its ardent players use
procedures much like OSE's to actually run the game published,
internalized as good practice from the original games over the users,
until they don't notice the lack of or more difficult presentation of
these procedures in S&amp;amp;W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the credit for OSE's procedures goes to Moldvay, Cook, and
Marsh, who designed the version of D&amp;amp;D it retroclones, but much also
goes to the exceptionally clear presentation of those rules by Gavin
Norman of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/"&gt;Necrotic Gnome&lt;/a&gt;.  The series
of OSE &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/adventures"&gt;adventures&lt;/a&gt; also published by Necro Gnome have also been
excellently presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been pleased to see S&amp;amp;W's presentation improving over time (the
use of two page spreads for most of the class presentations in the
most recent S&amp;amp;W Revised was a great improvement), and I expect to see
the presentation continue to improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>old-school essentials</category><category>ose</category><category>s&amp;w</category><category>swords &amp; wizardy</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/20/explicit-procedures-in-old-school-essentials-and-swords-wizardry/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jan 2024 23:09:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>OVA: Galactic Rangers — Session 1</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2023/03/24/ova-galactic-rangers-session-1/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;aside class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text in &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;{&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;}&lt;/code&gt; are out of game explanations.  Text in
&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;[&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;]&lt;/code&gt; are out of character comments from the players and
GM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Player Characters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strazin Kostra, tigerman Galactic Ranger!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yin, a shapechanging Galactic Ranger!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strazin fights Gary from Accounting (who looks like a humanoid
dragon), his boss, on his first day at work!  {This was just a
training exercise.} He defeats him in one blow!  But Gary says “You
may have beaten me, but Cheryl from HR is the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; challenge…” (Dun
dun dun!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gary sends us out after four criminal bosses: the Turtle does
protection, the Tiger does gambling, the Bird does illegal information
gathering and trading, and the Dragon does drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decide to go after the Bird later.  We'd have go off planet to the
satellite controlling space station around the planet of the bird
people.  On paper it is a telecommunication booster, but he uses it to
steal data.  Anyway, he's the hardest to approach, and we need
somebody smart, which is not playing to either of our strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to gather hard evidence of crimes, so they can be put away
for ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decide to go after the Tiger.  We are going to a casino with
associated brothel, Alpha Blue, under cover.  We are offered a hit of
a mild (and legal) drug at registration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{Drugs are not illegal unless really special: moon sugar, super
cocaine, etc. Crimes: illegal pit fighting where people die, contests
where people are expected to die, etc.}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yin goes straight to the tables, and breaks even, then gets the
feeling there is a disturbance in the force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strazin gets a mental image of a guy going back and to the left
through a secret passage to one of the arenas.  Strazin tells Yin
telepathically and they follow the guy to a death match.  They've got
five guys going over beams over a death drop, and they're betting on
who survives.  We end up in a lower box with the betters.  We've got a
martial arts guy, Fister, and Loud Strike, a wanted gun runner, who is
also wanted. {We are wired with audio and video.}  Fister and Loud
Strike are talking about going to the private suite of the Tiger to
get the winnings after the match.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Contestants are: Red &amp;amp; Blue tied for first, then Green &amp;amp; Black
tied, and trailing Yellow.  Yin and then Strazin bets on Yellow; none
of the betters can believe it.  Then Strazin uses Psychic to assist
Yellow, pushing twice then Green pushed black off in frustration and
lost his balance and fell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We win the jackpot, and Fister and the other guy take us up to the
Tigers office, where we see &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; tiger (not &lt;strong&gt;The Tiger&lt;/strong&gt;), who is
very rotund, not at all fit, Fat Tony, who asks if we want blue bucks
(the casino money) or to cash it out now.  We keep the blue bucks, for
later, and when he goes to pays recognizes Yin as infamous across the
Galaxy, and a fight breaks out.  It turns against us and we flee, Yin
uses &lt;em class="ability"&gt;Shape-Shifter&lt;/em&gt; to go down through the vents in the
floor and Strazin uses &lt;em class="ability"&gt;Psychic&lt;/em&gt; to read their weapon
patterns and to jump out the window and time it to catch the elevator
on the way down.  Yin says “We will never talk about this!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got &lt;strong class="xp"&gt;2 XP&lt;/strong&gt; each, and each get a bonus &lt;strong class="xp"&gt;1 XP&lt;/strong&gt;, for meta
reasons.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ova</category><category>ova galactic rangers</category><category>rpg</category><category>session logs</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2023/03/24/ova-galactic-rangers-session-1/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 01:08:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Simple OVA Character Sheet for LibreOffice Calc</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2023/02/20/simple-ova-character-sheet-for-libreoffice-calc/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I added a brutally simple character sheet for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.wiseturtle.com/games.html"&gt;OVA: The Anime
Role-Playing Game&lt;/a&gt; to my &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/pages/rpg-downloads/"&gt;RPG Downloads&lt;/a&gt; page.  It is for
LibreOffice Calc.  There is also a brutally simple PDF generated from
it as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>character sheet</category><category>libreoffice</category><category>libreoffice calc</category><category>ova</category><category>pdf</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2023/02/20/simple-ova-character-sheet-for-libreoffice-calc/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 03:26:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Downloads for various RPGs</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2023/02/19/downloads-for-various-rpgs/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I've made some stuff that I've used for some RPGs available for
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/pages/rpg-downloads/"&gt;download&lt;/a&gt;.  Right now it has reference sheets for several editions of
&lt;em&gt;Big Eyes, Small Mouth&lt;/em&gt; (Second Edition Revised, Third Edition, and
Fourth edition) and for &lt;em&gt;OVA: The Anime Role-playing Game&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>besm</category><category>besm2er</category><category>besm3e</category><category>besm4e</category><category>gaming</category><category>ova</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2023/02/19/downloads-for-various-rpgs/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 19:10:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Lord of the Rings Adventure Game from Iron Crown Enterprises</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2022/12/10/the-lord-of-the-rings-adventure-game-from-iron-crown-enterprises/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last edited: 2022-12-26 22:43:46 EST&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got an interesting game yesterday, and finished reading it today:
the 1991 &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings Adventure Game&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iron_Crown_Enterprises"&gt;Iron Crown
Enterprises&lt;/a&gt;, which was the first holder of the Tolkien franchise
for RPGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICE got its start with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rolemaster"&gt;Rolemaster&lt;/a&gt;, which started as a detailed
add-on combat system for D&amp;amp;D and developed into a very detailed RPG of
its own, based on open-ended d100 rolls: high is good and on very
high or low rolls you roll again and add the new roll for high or
subtracted for low, continuing infinitely in either direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICE then got the Tolkien franchise and developed &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middle-earth_Role_Playing"&gt;Middle-Earth Role
Playing&lt;/a&gt; (MERP) as a slightly simplified RPG for those who wanted to
play in Middle Earth, but did not want all the complexities of the
full Rolemaster system.  The adventures were written in such a way that
you could play them either with Rolemaster or MERP, and had some short
guidelines to help the GM adapt them for other games.  They had a lot
of success and their Middle Earth products were extensive and highly
regarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of folk used them with other RPG systems.  (I bought several for
the ideas.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in their run, ICE wanted to tap the larger Tolkien readership and
so wrote the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_the_Rings_Adventure_Game"&gt;Lord of the Ring Adventure Game&lt;/a&gt; as a much simpler
game that they hoped would draw interested readers and the viewers of
the animated Hobbit and Lord of the Rings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I have fond memories of the animated Hobbit, though I knew it only
through reading the graphic novel adaptation that used art from the
movie when I was at my uncle and aunt's place in New York one summer.
I finally saw it, probably on TV some years later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the Lord of the Rings Adventure Game (LOR hereafter, as seems
to be customary) comes in a box with a 32 page rulebook, a 64 page
adventure with 6 pre-generated characters, a 32 pamphlet of 4 pages of
backstory for the 6 pregens and area maps for the adventure, several
poster sized maps, including a nice color one of Middle Earth, and
(missing in my copy, as the seller had noted in the description) 2
six-sided dice and a sheet of standup cardboard figures of people and
creatures and the pregens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters have 12 stats: 6 capabilities (Strength, Agility,
Intelligence, Movement, and Endurance) and 6 skills (Defense, Melee
Offensive Bonus, Ranged Offensive Bonus, General, Subterfuge,
Perception, and Magical).  The value of each of these is called a
bonus, and can be less than zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You pick one of 9 character types (Hobbit Scout, Elf Scout, Human
Warrior, Dwarf Warrior, Elf Warrior, Human Ranger, Half-elf Ranger,
Human Bard, and Elf Bard), which sets your equipment and capability
values and starting skill values, and then you have six +1 bonuses to
add to your skills as you choose, no more than +3 to any one skill.
If you have +1 or more in magic you get two spells per +1 bonus.  Some
of your equipment gives bonuses to your stats.  I'll note that your
character type doesn't restrict what you can do: if you want your
Warrior to be able to use magic, put some of your starting skill
bonuses into Magical!  And they don't really have much to do with what
your characters occupation is: someone who takes one of the Warrior
character types can be a merchant, someone who takes one of the Scout
character types can be a healer.  It is all in how you assign your
starting skill bonuses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your character type sets your Endurance (basically your hit points),
with the dwarf warrior having the most at 60 points and the elf bard
the least at 30 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 15 spells, all with a fairly reasonable balance between
keeping with the magic seen in the novels, which is to say not
tremendously powerful, and what one would expect from a fantasy RPG.
The spells are Strength, Shield, Speed, Balance, Camouflage,
Concentration, Item Analysis, Clairvoyance, Healing, Luck, Protection
from Magic, Sustenance, Calm, Charm Animal, and Fire Bolt.  Magic
items typically add a plus to a stat, or let you do something you
couldn’t before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maneuvers are how you use your stats.  Some, like climbing a tree have
a set difficulty.  Others the GM sets the difficulty, from Routine (4)
to Absurd (18).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You roll 2d6 plus a stat bonus versus a target number or an opponent’s
roll.  Meet or exceed an unopposed roll to succeed, while you can tie
on opposed rolls.  In combat you take the attacker’s Offensive Bonus
minus the defenders Defensive Bonus and roll 2d6 and look the result
up in a chart to see how much damage is done and whether the defender
is knocked unconscious or killed outright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Activities are things that are normally automatically successful if
you have the equipment and time (tying up a captive, setting up camp,
digging a ditch), but turn into GM moderated maneuvers if you don’t
have the time or equipment (digging a ditch to hide in before the
opponents you want to ambush show up).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 14 action sequences.  These things like combat (one of the
action sequences) where there is a general sequence you follow to do
something, from sneaking through a town at night to tracking through a
wilderness or ambushing an enemy.  I like how these are written up as
a standard sequence of things to do and consider, just like how combat
is done in most system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These action sequences can be adjusted by the GM for circumstances and
they encourage you to make up your own.  You might make one up for
when someone is wanting to convince a crowd of something.  They are
multi-step procedures for doing something.  I think they would be
quite useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get Experience Points (EP) for successful maneuvers depending on
how hard the target number was, for every point of damage inflicted,
with unconsciousness and killed results worth more, and for every
point of damage the caster of a spell takes to cast the spell.  (Every
spell costs the caster Damage to cast!). You also get EP for good
ideas and for the group accomplishing significant goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The included adventure is a mix of programmed sequences to help the
new GM and players learn the system, where the choices the players
make determines what section you turn to next, and the sections are
broken up into action sequences and the results determine which
section the players go to next, GM notes on how to run or adjust
things, and descriptions of what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do notice that each of the pregens has a special ability: finding
lost items or people, eidetic memory, knowing if any creature within a
20 foot radius is aligned with forces of darkness, healing wounds
faster, being unusually skilled at bargaining and negotiation, and
always knowing which way is north and can follow known routes
perfectly.  But there is no rule for assigning these to characters.  I
imagine that if the GM wanted to have special abilities for other
characters the GM and the players should come up with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules encourage you to use figures or counters to represent
characters in combat, and movement is given in inches, to be measured
on the map, if you draw one, or on the table if you just set out the
figures at the right distances.  You could easily use a battle map
with a grid, if you have one.  Movement at a walk is 50 feet plus 10
feet multiplied by the characters Movement bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I like it.  I hope to run it this year for Christmas, if all
goes well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a Wikipedia &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_the_Rings_Adventure_Game"&gt;page&lt;/a&gt; about it, but it is even
briefer than this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a compatible game, The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://sites.google.com/site/ambarquenta/home/the-offical-games/meag"&gt;Middle-Earth Adventure Game&lt;/a&gt;
(MEAG), that was designed by Brian Gross and J.R. Gracen.  I knew of
it before I got the LotRAG, it seems to be a generalization and
expansion, and thus a little more complicated, but it doesn't look
&lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; complicated.  I'll read it and report what I think of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Local Variables:
time-stamp-format: "%Y-%02m-%02d %02H:%02M:%02S %Z"
time-stamp-start: "\\*Last edited:[ \t]+\\\\?"
time-stamp-end: "\\*\\\\?\n"
End: --&gt;</description><category>ice</category><category>iron crown enterprises</category><category>lor</category><category>lord of the rings adventure game</category><category>lotrag</category><category>merp</category><category>rolemaster</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2022/12/10/the-lord-of-the-rings-adventure-game-from-iron-crown-enterprises/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2022 23:30:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Demonicity, a Tri-Stat boxed game by Dyskami</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2022/12/02/demonicity-a-tri-stat-boxed-game-by-dyskami/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I finished reading Dyskami Publishing’s &lt;em&gt;Demonicity&lt;/em&gt; tonight (&lt;a href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/369442/Demonicity-RolePlaying-Adventures-TriStat-System"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;).  I liked the document design and found it easy to read, except the “Demon City” two page spread which I found a pain to read because of the body font.  I liked the artwork; it was not particularly anime or manga like, unlike &lt;em&gt;BESM Fourth Edition&lt;/em&gt;.  There were a few typos, missing words, and other minor mistakes, but there was only one that hindered comprehension, and that one I figured out eventually from the context.  The rules are easy to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The setting of &lt;em&gt;Demonicity&lt;/em&gt; is the titular “Demon City”, a city that is the location of an attack by demons from an different world/dimension.  It is obviously inspired by their earlier licensed RPG, &lt;em&gt;Demon City Shinjuku&lt;/em&gt;, which I quite liked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Demonicity&lt;/em&gt; has a very interesting stripped down version of the Tri-Stat system that makes character generation and play much simpler.  In some ways it reminds me of &lt;em&gt;BESM First Edition&lt;/em&gt;, though it is even simpler. The three Stats are Body, Mind, and Soul, of course, so that’s the same.  There are also Attributes, which are the special things a character can do.  Stats can be determined randomly or assigned by the player, and they and Attributes always cost points.  And there are some Derived Values: Combat, Health, Sanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You roll 2d6 and add a stat or a derived value (like Combat), plus optionally an Attribue’s level, and compare the result to a target number or an opposed roll.  Things that make something easier are Edges: you get an extra die or two on your dice roll, and you keep the highest two.  Things that make something harder, like trying to use two weapons at once without training, gives you Obstacles: an extra die or two on your dice roll, but you keep the two &lt;em&gt;lowest&lt;/em&gt; rolls.  Edges cancel out Obstacles and vice versa.  Combat is theater of the mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Demoicity&lt;/em&gt;’s version of &lt;em&gt;BESM&lt;/em&gt;’s Attributes are quite stripped down.  There are only nine: Adaptability, Damage, Demonicity, Fighting, Knacks, Movement, Resistance, Resources, and Skills.  These are bought in levels as usual, but associated with each are a number of Foci (as many as one has levels in the Attribute), which gives the character a special ability.  Demonicity is the Attribute that allows a character to do most of the more impressive supernatural things, for instance.  A few of its Foci are Healing, Meld (mere with inanimate objects), and Shadow Form.  The Fighting Attribute makes a character more proficient at combat than their Stats would suggest, and it’s Foci specify which kinds of Fighting you are better at (Melee or Ranged), or makes it easier to do certain things in combat (Blind Fighting, Two Weapons).  Generally, an Attribute’s level adds to dice rolls for things associated with it, while having an appropriate Foci means that you get an Edge.  After every session characters get a few points to increase their Stats and Attributes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rulebook is only 32 pages long and has a thicker card stock cover.  It is accompanied by six one page adventures with related art on the back and by six pre-generated characters with an image of the character on the back, all on card stock.  There are also four six-sided dice.  The box everything comes in seems sturdy.  In general the production values are quite good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People who are confident with their improvisation skills can probably run the adventures easily, but those who like more details will probably want to do a bit more preparation. The adventures appear designed to be easily linked into a six episode mini-campaign, or can form the backbone of a longer campaign if the GM writes their own adventures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like the inclusion of the pre-generated characters and the one page adventures.  They allow a gaming group to pick the game and start playing with little or no preparation.  And the simplified rules make it easy to learn the game, and to create characters if the gaming group doesn't want to use the pre-generated characters.  I think this makes it an excellent pick-up-and-play game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to have seen something like the adventure generators from various Savage Worlds setting books or Toon and its supplements.  They allow the GM who is stuck for ideas to come up with something quickly when inspiration is lacking. But it would have been difficult to fit in the constraints of the product.  Perhaps on another sheet of card stock, since I can’t see deleting anything from the rulebook?  BESM and Tri-Stat generally have very little procedural support for coming up with NPCs, scenes, adventures, etc., and I think an adventure generator would be a useful addition. Of course, having the example adventures to give an idea of what &lt;em&gt;Demonicity&lt;/em&gt; adventures would be like is very useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I quite like &lt;em&gt;Demonicity&lt;/em&gt; and hope to play it soon.  My only reservations are about the price of this game and the other two Tri-Stat boxed games, &lt;em&gt;Pixies&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Wyrms&lt;/em&gt;.  Forty-five retail dollars Canadian for the &lt;a href="http://dyskami.ca/tristat.html"&gt;physical product&lt;/a&gt; seems like a lot.  The &lt;a href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/369442/Demonicity-RolePlaying-Adventures-TriStat-System"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; seems more reasonable at 15 dollars.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>demonicity</category><category>dyskami</category><category>rpg</category><category>tri-stat</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2022/12/02/demonicity-a-tri-stat-boxed-game-by-dyskami/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 03:54:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Anime 5E: Fifth Edition Fantasy Role-Playing Adventures</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2022/06/14/anime-5e-fifth-edition-fantasy-role-playing-adventures/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Do you like D&amp;amp;D 5E, but would like to have it with with point-based
character generation, effects-based rules, and an Anime
flavour?  Well &lt;em&gt;Anime 5E: Fifth Edition Fantasy
Role-Playing Adventures&lt;/em&gt; is what you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My physical copies of &lt;em&gt;Anime 5E: Fifth Edition Fantasy Role-Playing
Adventures&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dyskami.ca/anime5e.html"&gt;home page&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/dyskami/anime-5e-fifth-edition-fantasy-role-playing-reimagined"&gt;Kickstarter&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/359098/Anime-5E-Fifth-Edition-Fantasy-RolePlaying-Adventures"&gt;DriveThruRPG page&lt;/a&gt;)
from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dyskami.ca/index.html"&gt;Dyskami Publishing Company&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_C._MacKinnon"&gt;Mark C. MacKinnon&lt;/a&gt; came
today, and I have only had a chance to briefly skim the pocket
edition, but I'm pleased at what they managed to fit into the small
package of 384 pages and a physical size of approximately 12.5cm wide
× 18.9cm tall × 2.25cm thick (4 15/16in wide × 7 13/32in tall ×
27/32in thick) and still have the text be large enough to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a picture of the Pocket Edition, with another picture with my
hand covering the book for size comparison:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/images/Anime-5E-pocket-edition.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Anime 5E pocket edition" src="https://tkurtbond.github.io/images/Anime-5E-pocket-edition.thumbnail.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/images/Anime-5E-pocket-edition-size-comparison.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Anime 5E pocket edition with hand for size comparison" src="https://tkurtbond.github.io/images/Anime-5E-pocket-edition-size-comparison.thumbnail.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I agree that adding the flexibility of Dynamic Powers attribute
as magic (p. 154) is very interesting I would like to have seen a
little guidance for using the rest of the attributes as spells using
the Deplete limiter (p. 237) and the optional Energy rules (p. 280);
I've seen the similar rules in BESM (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Eyes,_Small_Mouth"&gt;BESM1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.dyskami.ca/besm.html"&gt;BESM2&lt;/a&gt;) used very well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll have to wait until I get a chance to peruse the hardback version
to comment on the art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later: I just have to add: &lt;strong&gt;OMG! Battle Cabbits!&lt;/strong&gt; (On p. 367.) So
cute!  Now, if they only turned into spaceships as well...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also liked the Items chapter, especially the “Ring of Power”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last edited: 2022-06-15 02:36:59 EDT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Local Variables:
time-stamp-format: "%Y-%02m-%02d %02H:%02M:%02S %Z"
time-stamp-start: "\\*Last edited:[ \t]+\\\\?"
time-stamp-end: "\\*\\\\?\n"
time-stamp-line-limit: -20
End: --&gt;</description><category>5e</category><category>anime</category><category>anime 5e</category><category>besm</category><category>cabbit</category><category>dyskami</category><category>mark mackinnon</category><category>pocket edition</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2022/06/14/anime-5e-fifth-edition-fantasy-role-playing-adventures/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 03:34:40 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>