<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about electronics)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_electronics.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 07:47:18 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Apple Podcasts doesn't recognize my iPod Shuffle</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/09/apple-podcasts-doesnt-recognize-my-ipod-shuffle/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, after the most recent upgrade to macOS Catalina my &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPod_Shuffle"&gt;iPod
Shuffle&lt;/a&gt; is not recognized by Apple Podcasts, so I have no way of
loading more podcasts on it.  This is a pity, because it was the only
mp3 player that I actually liked, though I liked the second generation
one better than the fourth generation.  It had no screen, which is an
advantage since I mostly listen to podcasts in the car.  The controls
were very intuitive and were designed to be easy to operate without
looking at them.  They were also reasonably hard to press by
mistake. I shall miss it.  Oh, cruel modern world to have cast it out!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also had what appears to be an atypical workflow for the Shuffle.
In iTunes I would manually pick the episodes of the podcasts I was
interested and download them, then copy them manually to the Shuffle.
After I listened to them on the Shuffle I'd delete the download
manually in iTunes.  I never automatically synced the contents of my
Shuffle from iTunes.  With the second generation Shuffle I could copy
the files onto the Shuffle in the specific order I wanted.  The reason
I didn't like the fourth generation Shuffle was it organized the files
alphabetically by podcast name and then by episode date released, and
you had to hit a specific button and listen to it enumerate the
podcasts to move from one podcast to another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have another MP3 player, a SanDisk Clip Sport (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://downloads.sandisk.com/downloads/um/clipsport-um.pdf"&gt;manual&lt;/a&gt;) which I
tried some time ago and didn't like as much as the Shuffle.  My main
problem with it was that it was harder to operate without looking at
it: it has a screen, which you have to look at sometimes, and its
controls are not as easy to use without looking at them.  The controls
are also much more sensitive to pressure than the controls on the
Shuffle, so it is easier to activate them accidentally.  (I've
fast forwarded when my arm accidentally touched the controls while
carrying something near my chest.)  And, of course, the interface for
copying podcasts onto the Clip Sport is just copying files onto
external drive the Clip Sport shows up as, into the proper folder for
podcasts. So the “listened to” status and the time into each podcast
you've reached is not something the podcatcher application can help
you track.  And the Clip Sport itself doesn't keep track of where you
were in a particular podcast, though it does remember which one you
were listening to, and where in the podcast you had reached.  It's
really easy to mess up with the forward button and move on to the next
podcast and when you use the reverse button to move back the Clip
Sport has forgotten where in the podcast you were.  Sigh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh well.  I guess I'll have to give the Clip Sport another try.
Luckily I had exported my podcast feed from iTunes before I converted
to macOS Catalina — I had 122 podcast subscriptions.  I installed
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gpodder.github.io/"&gt;gpodder&lt;/a&gt; on my macOS laptop to manage the podcasts. (I was glad a
version of it as a macOS application was available.) It told me that
several of my subscriptions didn't have valid feeds any more, or
simpler weren't there, so now I have 105 podcast subscriptions.  To
download a podcast I can right click on the episode name in the
episode list and choose “Download”.  (It would be convenient if the
not downloaded/downloading/downloaded indication icon was an active
button to download it with one click.)  It has an option, when you
right click on a podcast, to open the download directory for that
podcast, which makes it easy to copy the files to the Clip Sport.  Of
course, they end up on the Clip Sport alphabetically by filename, and
some podcasts have really weird names — I'd swear some of them were
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universally_unique_identifier"&gt;UUID&lt;/a&gt;s.  There is a gpodder option to rename the files to the title
of the episode, which is good when episodes include the episode number
in the title.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>apple podcasts</category><category>clip sport</category><category>ipod</category><category>mp3 player</category><category>shuffle</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/09/apple-podcasts-doesnt-recognize-my-ipod-shuffle/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 00:00:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>ifrogz Plugz EarBuds</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/04/01/ifrogz-plugz-earbuds/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Wal-Mart carries the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ifrogz.com/"&gt;ifrogz&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20120124010324/http://ifrogz.com/product/EPPlugz"&gt;Plugz&lt;/a&gt; earbuds for 10$, and for cheap ear
buds I like these the best of the ones I've tried.  They are
comfortable, they stay in my ears, the soft plastic tips don't come
off (unlike the memory foam tips on many cheap ear buds, which I was
always loosing), and they do a reasonable job of cutting down outside
noise.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>earbuds</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/04/01/ifrogz-plugz-earbuds/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2011 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>