<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about dnd)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/dnd.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 18:49:35 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Fantastic Medieval Campaigns</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/fantastic-medieval-campaigns/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://traversefantasy.itch.io/fmc"&gt;Fantastic Medieval Campaigns&lt;/a&gt; (FMC) by Marcia B. is a great
retroclone and restatement of Original D&amp;amp;D: it's clearly written, well
organized, contains a table of contents for the book and then a table
of contents in each section, has a glossary and indices for monsters,
spells, and tables, and uses the color backgrounds of the pages well
to make finding the different sections easy.  The art is charming and
appropriate for a OD&amp;amp;D retroclone, and the layout is clean.  It
includes a retroclone of Chainmail, which is rare.  I like it very
much.  And the PDF is free!  I got the hardback color book and read it
and want to run at least two campaigns with it, the first using its
Chainmail retroclone, “Chain of Command”, and the next with the d20
based combat system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, but, but!  The back cover text says “problematize our
preconceptions of a text (or even a whole genre)” and mentions
“falsehood”.  And the contents of the last page of the text,
which is labeled “This Page Intentionally Left Blank.”, are certainly
not blank, and expresses opinions of D&amp;amp;D that must surely
offend many D&amp;amp;D players.  I'll quote it here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fantastic Medieval Campaigns is a recreation of what is at best a
deeply reactionary work of art—if not a fascist one altogether.
We recognize now that the authors, as well as some who were in
their circle, thought quite badly of women, indigenous people, and
others.  However, we should let the text speak for itself because
it speaks loudly.  The book is a guide to fantastic war game
campaigns, where the players take on the roles of
sword-and-sorcery adventurers seeking greatness.  They will begin
in the Underworld simply slaying monsters and retrieving treasure
in the form of gold, legal tender ready to be exchanged on the
open market.  As characters accumulate treasure, they acquire
superhuman abilities and political power to boot.  Heroes,
Thaumaturgists, and Bishops emerge from their colonial katabasis
conquering land by which to become Lords, Wizards, and Patriarchs.
They will establish sanctuaries and, with their vast armies, turn
the tide against the forces of evil chaos they have always
‘resisted' thus far.  The setting in general is one where might
makes right, where the violent extraction of resources is central
to the protagonists activity, and where participation in these
things is rewarded with not only political power bu the sort of
physiological and supernatural power which colonizers and fascists
imagined themselves to have.  It is a mirror to the desires and
fantasies of its original authors, a bunch of white, straight,
cissexual men in the Midwest, just as it is a reflection of boys'
pulp literature at the height of American culture about crushing
one's enemies and driving them before oneself and hearing the
lamentations of their women.  All in all, this work was not
written in a vacuum nor did it spring fully formed from the heads
of its creators.  You can use this book however you like or even
attempt to play it with the mindset of a midcentury American  man,
but do not delude yourself with regards to its content or to the
fantasy which it encodes.  That being said, as the author, I offer
up this work for analysis, critique, and reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, that certainly put the coyote in the chicken house!  It is
definitely controversial in OSR circles.  Honestly, though, I'm not
sure &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; furor was worth following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just want to point out that, whatever the author's opinions of D&amp;amp;D,
they wrote FMC so they could more easily understand the rules, so
they could better play D&amp;amp;D with their friends, and according to a
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.paperspencils.com/fantastic-medieval-campaigns/"&gt;friend of theirs&lt;/a&gt; they spent over a year working on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of whether I agree with their views or not, FMC is a well
written game and its author should be proud of it.  It can be used to
run some great games.  If you don't agree with the author's views, just
ignore them and &lt;strong&gt;play the game&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>controversy</category><category>dnd</category><category>fantastic medieval campaigns</category><category>fmc</category><category>odnd</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/fantastic-medieval-campaigns/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 04:13:27 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>