<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about dungeon tiles)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/dungeon-tiles.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Jul 2020 23:30:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Miniatures, battlemats, and terrain at my table</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/miniatures-and-battlemaps-at-my-table/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I started playing with &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; 1E (in 1979 or 1980) we didn't use
miniatures or battle maps, it was all theater of the mind.  Since all
the players I knew personally started with &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; none of us had seen
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chainmail_(game)"&gt;Chainmail&lt;/a&gt; or played miniatures games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I moved on to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DragonQuest"&gt;DragonQuest&lt;/a&gt;, 2nd edition, (in the mid 1980s) where
a hex grid and miniatures was required, I bought a Chessex hex grid
Megamat and wet erase markers.  One of my brothers had bought a box of
miniatures (though for the life of me I cannot remember what company
it was from or what figures it contained).  We used those for player
characters.  For monsters, I cut out a bunch of ¾ inch square blocks
of wood and numbered them on the top side, put a “D” for Dead on the
bottom side, put an “S” on another smooth side for Stunned, and a “U”
for Unconscious, leaving the rough sides (where the wood was cut
against the grain) blank.  I continued to use all these when I moved
over to using &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GURPS"&gt;GURPS&lt;/a&gt; 3rd edition, which also had specific Stunned and
and Unconscious conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much, much later I got the Steve Jackson Games Cardboard Heroes but
never could bear to cut them up, since I wasn't actively playing at
the time it came out (1999 or so?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started playing &lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; again with 3.5E (probably sometime
after 2004) I mostly played and didn't DM.  I was fortunate that the
DMs that I played with had good collections of pre-painted plastic
miniatures for both player characters and monsters from the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Miniatures_Game"&gt;Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons Miniatures Game&lt;/a&gt;.  I did collect some of the Dungeon Tiles
(see &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeon_Tiles"&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dmdavid.com/tag/a-complete-list-and-gallery-of-dungeon-tiles-sets/"&gt;dmdavid&lt;/a&gt;) that Wizards of the Coast published
during this time. (I actually used them playing Savage Worlds.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one campaign that I DMed with 3.5E I bought an Flip Chart/Easel
Pad printed with a 1 inch grid.  I would take several sheets to the
game in a tubular storage container and draw the rooms on the map with
black marker as the players explored.  If we ran off the the side of a
sheet or went to a new level I'd get out another sheet and draw on
that.  This worked surprisingly well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One GM had a fair bit of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dwarvenforge.com/"&gt;Dwarven Forge&lt;/a&gt; terrain and that was a lot
of fun to play on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started playing &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savage_Worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt; (around 2005) I did a lot of
GMing, and was thrilled by the Figure Flats and map tiles that that
Great White Games (now known again as Pinnacle Entertainment Group —
PEG) included in many of their Savage Tales PDF adventures.  I had a
printer that could print on card stock, so these were ideal for
me.  Later PEG products, such as their Plot Point campaigns, often had
Figure Flats as separate PDF accessories.  I found them all very
useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also found the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/51074/eAdventure-Tiles-Introductory-Set"&gt;e-Adventure Tiles&lt;/a&gt; series from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/80/SkeletonKey-Games"&gt;SkeletonKey Games&lt;/a&gt;
very useful.  These &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wiki.roll20.net/Geomorphic_Map_Tiles"&gt;geomorphic map tiles&lt;/a&gt; are 6×6 inch squares, marked
with a 1 inch square grid, and by printing them out and putting them
together you can produce an infinite variety of maps.  I found them
most useful when printed on cardstock and labeled on the back with
their id number.  I'd make up several maps and then sort out the
printed tiles for that map into a manila envelope for easy
retrieval. There used to be a program that you could use the small
preview images from the tiles (which were considerately set up for
easy Copy and Paste from the PDF) to lay out your map at the small
scale and then print it for reference when later putting together the
large tiles. &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/miniatures-and-battlemaps-at-my-table/#tiamat" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; I'd include those in the manila envelope with
the tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used paper miniatures from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/667/Arion-Games"&gt;Arion Games&lt;/a&gt; and Disposable Heroes
paper miniatures from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.pigames.net/store/default.php?cPath=27"&gt;Precis Intermedia&lt;/a&gt;.  I also had &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.nobleknight.com/P/2147348073/Paper-Wars---Dragon-Pass-at-War"&gt;Paper Wars -
Dragon Pass at War&lt;/a&gt;, a collection of Glorantha paper miniatures
published by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rpggeek.com/rpgpublisher/10024/unspoken-word"&gt;The Unspoken Word&lt;/a&gt;, which seem to have been drawn by
Simon Bray, Dario Corallo, and Sarah Evans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the early paper miniatures that I used were tri-fold and were
cut out, folded, and glued (or taped) together.  They usually had
front sides in color and a back side in black and white.
Unfortunately, these take up almost as much room as lead or plastic
miniatures, though were much lighter to carry.  I stored them in cheap
plastic food containers, which let me easily see what was inside them.
Carrying enough of them to games outside my home was a bulky problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually I moved to A-frame paper miniatures, where there are two
sides and they are attached at the top, with tabs that fold out or in
at the bottom for a base.  Instead of relying on the tabs to form the
base, I used plastic &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.pigames.net/store/default.php?cPath=27_96"&gt;stands&lt;/a&gt; from Precis Intermedia, where you'd just
fold the miniature once and stick it in the stand.  The stands add a bit
of weight to the miniatures and make them much more stable.  If you
cut out a front that is attached to a back, instead of all three
sides, you can just fold them once and stick them in a stand as well,
so I could use all my trifold paper miniatures as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://zenseeker.net/PaperMiniatures/DIY.htm"&gt;Zen DIY Paper Miniatures Page&lt;/a&gt; has some pictures of A-frame and
trifold paper miniatures.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since these paper miniatures are flat when not inserted into stands I
currently organize my paper miniatures into separate small manila
envelopes for each type of creature, labeled with the creature type on
the outside.  Occasionally I use small ziplock bags, especially for
the PCs' miniatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper miniatures described above are all drawn in such a way that
the figure is drawn within a rectangle and you can cut them out with
long straight cuts and cross cuts.  There is another style of paper
miniatures drawn in a manner so that you cut out the irregular outline
of the figure itself with many small or curving cuts.  These are much
harder to cut out, and are more difficult to store, but are &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt;
impressive to look at.  (You can see some examples in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://onemonk.com/monsters.html"&gt;Monsters&lt;/a&gt;
collection at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://onemonk.com/"&gt;One Monk Miniatures&lt;/a&gt;) That's too much work for me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also got a Steel Sqwire Flip Mat, which uses dry erase pens, and it
is 24×30 inches and folds up into an 8×10 inch package only a ¼ inch
thick or so.  Much easier to carry around, since it fits into the same
backpack or messenger bag I use to carry my RPG books and
accessories. &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/miniatures-and-battlemaps-at-my-table/#accessories" id="id4"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; More over, unlike the ones you can find
now published by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://paizo.com/products/btpy8oto?GameMastery-FlipMat-Basic"&gt;Paizo&lt;/a&gt;, it had both 1 inch squares and 1 inch hexes,
perfect for DragonQuest, GURPS, or The Fantasy Trip, though I've used
mostly the squared side, for Savage Worlds.  The dry erase pens are
much more satisfactory than the wet erase pens.  For some time I
haven't had extra time to lay out locations using paper map tiles, and
the Flip Mat lets me quickly draw out locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I usually use miniatures and a battle map for Savage Worlds
there have been several occasions where I've run games in theater of
the mind style, without any miniatures or battle map.  It takes a
little adapting, but isn't that difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current practice is to use paper miniatures in stands for player
characters and numbered blocks for opponents, with a Flip Mat as the
battle map.  Some times for opponents that take up more than one
square I'll fold over or cut up a 3×5 or 4×6 card and use that,
writing an arrow to indicate which way is the front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never used &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://thefantasytrip.game/products/core-games/melee/"&gt;Melee&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://thefantasytrip.game/products/core-games/wizard/"&gt;Wizard&lt;/a&gt; style counters, which lie flat on
the table, but I got in on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://thefantasytrip.game/products/core-games/the-fantasy-trip-legacy-edition/"&gt;The Fantasy Trip Legacy Edition&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/sjgames/the-fantasy-trip-old-school-roleplaying"&gt;kickstarter&lt;/a&gt; and am intending to try them out sometime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, when running &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Basic_Set#1981_revision"&gt;B/X D&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/pages/rpg-vocabulary/#retro-clone"&gt;retro-clones&lt;/a&gt; there of
(like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://goblinoidgames.com/"&gt;Goblinoid Games&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;cite&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/cite&gt; (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Labyrinth_Lord"&gt;L1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/760/Goblinoid-Games/subcategory/2033_6311/Labyrinth-Lord"&gt;L2&lt;/a&gt;), it's &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt;
inspired &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/78523/Advanced-Edition-Companion-Labyrinth-Lord?cPath=2033_6311"&gt;Advanced Edition Companion&lt;/a&gt;, or the book that squashes them
together: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/259983/Advanced-Labyrinth-Lord-Dragon-Cover?cPath=2033_6311"&gt;Advanced Labyrinth Lord&lt;/a&gt;, or like &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/"&gt;Necrotic Gnome&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/old-school-essentials"&gt;Old
School Essentials&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://froggodgames.com/product/swords-wizardry-complete-rulebook/"&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry&lt;/a&gt;) it's all theater of the
mind: no miniatures, no battle map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="tiamat"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/miniatures-and-battlemaps-at-my-table/#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;The program that I used was a desktop application rather
than a web-based application, but &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rpgobjects.com/index.php?c=tiamat"&gt;Tiamat the Tile Mapper&lt;/a&gt; is a
similar application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="accessories"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/miniatures-and-battlemaps-at-my-table/#id4"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dice of course; usually I carry a couple of extra
sets for when someone forgets their dice.  For Savage Worlds I
carry several differently colored sets of glass beads (stored in
small ziplock bags). I use blue beads for bennies, white beads for
GM bennies, red beads for wounds, yellow beads for shaken and white
beads again for fatigue.  I've found it helps the players (and
myself) to remember their status if they have physical objects
sitting on their character sheet to remind them.  When playing with
numbered blocks for opponents I put the shaken bead on top of the
block; this really helps when I've got 30 opponents on the table.
I carry a couple of decks of playing cards for Savage Worlds
initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ad&amp;d</category><category>arion games</category><category>battlemaps</category><category>cardboard heroes</category><category>chainmail</category><category>chessex</category><category>d&amp;d</category><category>d&amp;d 3.5e</category><category>dragonquest</category><category>dungeon tiles</category><category>dwarven forge</category><category>flip mat</category><category>goblinoid games</category><category>gurps</category><category>hex grid</category><category>labyrinth lord</category><category>melee</category><category>miniatures</category><category>necrotic gnome</category><category>old school essentials</category><category>paper miniatures</category><category>precis intermedia</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>skeletonkey games</category><category>swords &amp; wizardry</category><category>terrain</category><category>the fantasy trip</category><category>tiamat the tile mapper</category><category>wizard</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/miniatures-and-battlemaps-at-my-table/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 01:17:47 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>