<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about epiphany)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/epiphany.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 18:07:17 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Diceless Roleplaying Games</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/05/10/2003-05-10/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;These descriptions were part of or inspired by a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://groups.google.com/groups?hl=en&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;amp;threadm=a3db6b24.0305092050.2fc139b1%40posting.google.com&amp;amp;rnum=1&amp;amp;prev=/groups%3Fq%3Dgroup:rec.games.frp.advocacy%2Bauthor:Kurt%2Bauthor:Bond%26hl%3Den%26lr%3D%26ie%3DUTF-8%26oe%3DUTF-8%26selm%3Da3db6b24.0305092050.2fc139b1%2540posting.google.com%26rnum%3D1"&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class="reference external" href="news:rec.games.frp.advocacy"&gt;rec.games.frp.advocacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="epiphany"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Epiphany&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think Epiphany's ranged combat is equivalent to Rock-Paper-
Scissors, though.  In R/P/S each side chooses randomly between three
choices and there is no intrinsic reason to choose one or the other.
In Epiphany's ranged combat each side totals up their advantages and
all the attacker's advantages are used for offense and all the
defendor's advantages are used for defense.  This is non-random and it
depends on what applicable abilities are available to each side.  I
don't think these two are that similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.btrc.net/html/catalog/catmain.html#Epiphany"&gt;Epiphany&lt;/a&gt;'s
resolution mechanism is analogous to Rock-Paper-Scissors, nor do I
think that result is random.  In R/P/S you pick one of the three
choices, your opponent picks one of the choices, there is no reason to
pick one of the choices over the others, and the result is random.  In
Epiphany, each side counts up the number of Advantages they have that
apply to the situation and decides how many to apply to Offense and
how many to apply to Defense.  (The number of Advantages one side has
is the total of the Attributes and Abilities that they have that apply
in this situation, minus any Disadvantages.) That's not random at all,
and has the tactical issue of allocating Advantages to Offense and
Defense, which makes it even more like unlike R/P/S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I think Epiphany's resolution is often compared to R/P/S because they
both indicate the what each side is doing by holding out fingers, but
the choices behind and effects of those choices are very different, so
this apparent similarity of finger- pointing is actually misleading.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="nobilis"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nobilis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobilis is a bit more crunchy than most diceless games.  All Characters
have four Attributes--Aspect, Domain, Realm, and Spirit-- which are
rated from zero to five and describe the character's level of ability
in four broad areas of effect.  Each attribute also has a number of
associated Miracle Points.  Characters can also have other abilities,
called Gifts, which have a more focused or limited area of effect.  All
actions are rated in difficulty from zero to nine.  Actions in a
particular area of effect that have a difficulty less than that of the
attribute that governs that area are automatically successful.  Actions
that have a difficulty greater than the appropriate attribute require
spending miracle points to succeed.  There are tables that indicate the
level of power each level of difficulty provides, and there are lists
of example actions and their difficulty levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>epiphany</category><category>nobilis</category><category>old blog</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/05/10/2003-05-10/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2003 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>