<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about fighting fantasy)</title>
  <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/fighting-fantasy.atom</id>
  <updated>2021-08-14T05:57:49Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/fighting-fantasy.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/fighting-fantasy/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I like Advanced Fighting Fantasy</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/06/21/why-i-like-advanced-fighting-fantasy/</id>
    <updated>2021-06-21T12:48:21-04:00</updated>
    <published>2021-06-21T12:48:21-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2021/06/21/why-i-like-advanced-fighting-fantasy/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have a great fondness for the original &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced_Fighting_Fantasy"&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy&lt;/a&gt;
series, even though I didn’t get them until 2011 or so.  I think the
the Arion Games &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Advanced_Fighting_Fantasy#Advanced_Fighting_Fantasy_titles_published_by_Arion_Games_(2011-present)"&gt;2nd edition&lt;/a&gt; of Advanced Fighting Fantasy is
probably a slightly better game, especially for campaigns (it made a
few adjustments, so character creation is not as random, and a few
other things), but I like it’s layout and typography less.  Also,
there is something about the presentation of the game in &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;
as something for people new to RPGs that made it appealing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is it about the Advanced Fighting Fantasy series that makes
it so cool?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the original &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fighting_Fantasy"&gt;Fighting Fantasy&lt;/a&gt; gamebooks were neat.  The
series was started by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ian_Livingstone"&gt;Ian Livingstone&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Jackson_(British_game_designer)"&gt;Steve Jackson&lt;/a&gt;.
(That's the British Steve Jackson, not the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Jackson_(American_game_designer)"&gt;American&lt;/a&gt; one.)  They
included a really simple RPG and a choose your own adventure style
adventure.  That’s where the book is made up at numbered paragraphs,
and when you get to a decision point you can choose among two or more
choices, and those point you at different paragraphs depending on the
choice you make.  For instance, you might have a choice to attack,
retreat to an earlier location, or try something off the wall.  The
addition of the simple RPG added a lot, in my opinion, increasing
replayability.  Anyway, that addition made the Fighting Fantasy books
some of the most popular gamebooks.  Many of them are classics of the
genre.  Most of them are fantasy, and set in the world of Titan, which
was popular enough that there was a world book devoted to it,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Titan_(Fighting_Fantasy_book)"&gt;Titan&lt;/a&gt;, and a book of monsters from that word, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fightingfantasy.fandom.com/wiki/Out_of_the_Pit"&gt;Out of the Pit&lt;/a&gt;.
And the art used in illustrating the books was very evocative.  (I
particularly liked Russ Nicholson's art (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://russnicholson.blogspot.com/"&gt;R1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Russ_Nicholson"&gt;R2&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mini RPG used in the Fighting Fantasy books was really simple: the
reader’s character has three stats, SKILL, which measures their
general level of skill, STAMINA, which measures the character’s energy
and fitness and how much damage they can take, and LUCK, which
measures how lucky the character is.  SKILL is 1d6+6, STAMINA is
2d6+12, LUCK is 1d6+6.  NPCs and creatures just have SKILL and
STAMINA.  Generally, if the character is trying to do something
outside combat, they roll 2d6 &amp;lt;= their SKILL to succeed.  Combat is
simple, the player rolls 2d6 and adds their skill, their opponent
rolls 2d6 and adds their skill, and the one with the higher total
subtracts 2 from the other’s STAMINA total.  If they tie neither win.
LUCK is used to see how lucky the character is.  For instance, if a
cave is collapsing a character will “Test their LUCK” and roll 2d6 &amp;lt;=
their LUCK to succeed at escaping the collapse.  Every time a
character Tests their LUCK, they reduce their current luck by 1.
Luck can also be used in Combat to increase the wounds they deal or
decrease the wounds they take.  If a character has wounded an
opponent, they can Test their LUCK, and if they are Unlucky the
opponent takes only 1 damage instead of 2, but if they are Lucky the
opponent takes 4 damage instead of 2.  If the character has been
wounded, they can Test their Luck and if Lucky they take only 1
damage, but if they are unlucky they take 3 damage.  So it is a
tradeoff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, that system works well for a gamebook, but doesn’t have enough
detail for most RPG players.  (Although it was published as an intro
RPG, in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fightingfantasy.fandom.com/wiki/Fighting_Fantasy_-_The_Introductory_Role-playing_Game"&gt;Fighting Fantasy: The Introductory Role-playing Game&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy, written by Marc Gascoigne, takes that
framework and adds to it in a way that increases the interesting
detail of the system, without overcomplicating it too much.
Primarily, they add Special Skills, which allow characters to
specialize.  For instance, if a character wanted to be good with a bow
and able to follow people through the forest they’d pick up the
Special Skills Bow and Awareness.  Then, when shooting arrows at
opponents they’d add the rating for their Bow Special Skill to their
SKILL.  When tracking someone through the forest, they’d add their
Awareness Special Skill to their SKILL.  And so on.  A sneaky person
might have the Special Skills Locks, Sleigh of Hand, Sneaking, and
Trap Knowledge.  And so on.  Someone from a noble background might
have Etiquette, Law, and Leadership.  A merchant might have Bargan,
City Lore, and Evaluate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like that characters are competent in general, due to SKILL, but can
be more competent in their areas of interest, using Special Skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can build important NPCs just like characters if you want the
detail, but for run-of-the-mill opponents you can just use SKILL and
STAMINA, so stating out NPCs and opponents is very easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Advanced Fighting Fantasy added more detail to weapons and armor,
still keeping to the use of six sided dice only. So, instead of each
attack doing 2 STAMINA damage every time, you roll a die and depending
on the weapon, that tells you how much damage you do, by looking up
the weapon’s damage chart.  For instance, a dagger might do 1 damage
on a 1 or 2, 2 damage on a 3 through 6, and 3 damage on a 7+ (because
there are a few things that add one to the damage roll, but not
directly to the resulting damage), while a great sword does 2 damage
on 1, 3 damage on a 2 or 3, 4 damage on a 4 or 5, 5 damage on a 6, and
6 damage on a 7+.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, here's the damage for Dagger, Club, and Two-handed Sword:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 68%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 8%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Weapon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;7+&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Club&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dagger&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two-handed Sword&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's an interesting way to get variable damage when you are limited
to using just six sided dice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course there was a Magic Special Skill, and if you learned that
you could learn and cast spells, each spell costing an amount of
STAMINA to cast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Advanced Fighting Fantasy had a nice mass combat system, and lots
of setting detail from &lt;cite&gt;Titan&lt;/cite&gt; and opponents from &lt;cite&gt;Out of the Pit&lt;/cite&gt;
(both republished in trade paperback to go with the AFF trade
paperbacks), and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Advanced Fighting Fantasy (AFF1e) was published in three trade
paperback sized books, &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt; (1989), &lt;cite&gt;Blacksand&lt;/cite&gt; (1990), and
&lt;cite&gt;Allansia&lt;/cite&gt; (1994).  &lt;cite&gt;Titan&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Out of the Pit&lt;/cite&gt;, were republished in
1989 in trade paperback sized books to match.  &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt; had the
basic rules, &lt;cite&gt;Blacksand&lt;/cite&gt; added more options and described the city of
Blacksand (a fantasy hive of scum and villainy), and &lt;cite&gt;Allansia&lt;/cite&gt; added
more options and described the continent of Allansia in more detail.
The books were less available in the US than in Great Britain where
they originated, and I never saw them in either bookstores (where they
were sold alongside the Fighting Fantasy gamebooks, hence the trade
paperback size) or in gaming stores.  I got my copies in 2011, when
AFF 2nd Edition came out, for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2011 Graham Bottley of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://arion-games.com/"&gt;Arion Games&lt;/a&gt; got the license to publish a
2nd edition of Advanced Fighting Fantasy (AFF2e).  It was a more
familiar A4 sized book (the international paper size closest to the US
Letter paper size), and while I didn’t particularly care for its
layout choices, I did like the way it made the game better for running
campaigns (character creation was less random, and gave characters
more room for growth), its addition of a MAGIC stat and Magic Points
from which the costs for spells were deducted instead of STAMINA, and
its additions of multiple types of magic (one, Sorcery, was based on a
different gamebook series, the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Jackson%27s_Sorcery!"&gt;Sorcery!&lt;/a&gt; series, from Steve
Jackson), and talents, which were special things a character could do.
I wasn’t so thrilled that priests now used a completely separate magic
system not based on casting spells costing Magic Points; in 1st
Edition priests had different spell lists they could learn from, but
otherwise used the same mechanics as Mages.  AFF2e also added more
detailed armour, which works similarly to damage — roll a die, look up
how much damage is blocked on the armour chart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's Leather Cuirass and Plate Armour:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 67%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 4%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 8%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Armour&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;7+&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Leather Cuirass&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plate Armour&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AFF1e, by contrast, said that the Damage Table had been carefully
constructed to take into account armour (&lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, p. 163), and
assumed Heroes (the player characters) and their adversaries all wore
armor (&lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, p. 164), and if anyone took off their armour,
then any Damage Rolls (which was an index into a table, remember, not
the actual damage) had 2 added to them.  I expect this explains why
the damage values on the Weapon chart all changed in AFF2e.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I played some AFF 1st Edition games with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;the kids&lt;/a&gt;, which
was a lot of fun.  I also played some AFF 2nd Edition games with some
of them, which was also fun.  I played AFF1E with some of the folks
from work, and it was fun, but they wanted something with more
detailed combat.  I could see why, even AFF2e combat is fairly simple.
They rest of the game they liked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Arion Games has gone on to publish slightly more than a book a
year since 2011, covering the same ground as the original AFF’s three
books did, plus a lot more, including two more monster books (&lt;cite&gt;Beyond
the Pit&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Return to the Pit&lt;/cite&gt;), more options for heroes in the
&lt;cite&gt;Heroes Companion&lt;/cite&gt;, a new area of Titan (&lt;cite&gt;Travels in Arion&lt;/cite&gt;), a
herbal, and a smaller book on creatures from a particular area of
Titan (&lt;cite&gt;Creatures of Mishna&lt;/cite&gt;).  And just recently they published the
&lt;cite&gt;Combat Companion&lt;/cite&gt;, which adds extra options for combat that the
gamers from my work mentioned earlier would have liked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Titan, the world of Fighting Fantasy and Advanced Fighting Fantasy
is a very nice little bit of everything fantasy setting, anchored by
locations and characters from 59 Fighting Fantasy gamebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, Advanced Fighting Fantasy is a role-playing game with
simple mechanics that still provide ample detail, set in an
interesting fantasy world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arion Games also publishes &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/214183/Stellar-Adventures"&gt;Stellar Adventures&lt;/a&gt;, a science fiction
game that uses the same rules, customized for science fiction
adventures, which has several supplements as well.  The &lt;cite&gt;Stellar
Adventures&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt;, 2nd Edition lines are all
available in PDF on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/667/Arion-Games/subcategory/1684_25223/Advanced-Fighting-Fantasy"&gt;DriveThruRPG.com&lt;/a&gt;, with most available in
print-on-demand as well, very important in these days of online
gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last edited: 2021-08-09 12:10:07 EDT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Local Variables:
time-stamp-format: "%Y-%02m-%02d %02H:%02M:%02S %Z"
time-stamp-start: "\\*Last edited:[ \t]+\\\\?"
time-stamp-end: "\\*\\\\?\n"
time-stamp-line-limit: -20
End: --&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="out-of-the-pit" label="out of the pit"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
    <category term="stellar-adventures" label="stellar adventures"/>
    <category term="titan" label="titan"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>AFF1e: Dungeoneer Adventure II: Revenge of the Sorcerer, Part 2</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/01/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-ii-revenge-of-the-sorcerer-part-2/</id>
    <updated>2014-11-01T15:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2014-11-01T15:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/01/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-ii-revenge-of-the-sorcerer-part-2/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing “Dungeoneer Adventure II: Revenge of the Sorcerer”,
from &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to
skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwise, starting with the Director:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Director&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — Grimbold Tornhelm, Alexa Wolfrica (L.B. wasn't here)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. — Gordo Brondwyn, Aspen Darkfire (E.A. wasn't here)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They explored the tunnel the centipede came out of, and took the 5
tridents in the nest at the end, in want of some better loot.  Headed
back to the main tunnel and continued on.  They were soon captured by
the Fish People, who tied them up and marched them off toward a
wizard!  After a while they came to an open area, held up by pillars,
and the Fish Men seemed to get very nervous.  A white light appeared
in the open area, and the Fish Men all screamed and ran off, dropping
the characters' possessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The white light gradually resolved into a ghost, who seemed pleasant
enough, and introduced himself as Sargon.  Eventually the PCs made a
deal with Sargon to bring him a magic Crystal of Power that the Fish
Men were keeping in the Temple of Hydana, in return for which Sargon
would tell them how to defeat Xorton Throg.  They snuck into the
temple through a secret door Sargon told them about and killed the
Fish Men priest who was there before he could alert the guards.  They
took the Crystal and a magic sword that was also on the altar.  They
searched the room and found a secret door that lead to stairs that
lead up to a tavern. They found out it was the Mermaid Tavern, and
then escaped back down into the cellar followed by a bouncer, but
escaped down the hidden trap door before he reached the cellar, and he
didn't follow them.  They continued down the stairs to the temple.  They
returned to Sargon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Crystal returned Sargon to life and he told them how to find and
defeat Xorton Throg by getting him to throw a powerful spell at them and
reverse it onto him by bringing out the crystal.  He also restored the
magic sword to good condition.  They followed his advice and killed
Xorton Throg, after killing some skeletons and a skeletal
tyransaurous. They got 300 GP each loot and 4 swords each from the
remains of the skeleton army.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They returned to Nicodemus and gave the Crystal to him, then slipped
out of Port Blacksand and back to Salamonis, where the king rewarded
them with 500 GP each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They each got 3 XP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff1e" label="aff1e"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>AFF1e: Dungeoneer Adventure II: Revenge of the Sorcerer, Part 1</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/12/27/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-ii-revenge-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/</id>
    <updated>2012-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2012-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/12/27/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-ii-revenge-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing “Dungeoneer Adventure II: Revenge of the Sorcerer”,
from &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to
skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwise, starting with the Director:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Director&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — Grimbold Tornhelm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. — Gordo Brondwyn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;L.B. — Alexa Wolfrica&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. — Aspen Darkfire&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCs attended court, where their part in rescuing Princess Sarissa
was explained, along with the fact that Xortan Throg was still at
large.  The PCs are assigned the task of killing Xortan Throg, and
told to get assistance from Nicodemus in Port Blacksand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCs got 500 GP as a reward for thwarting Xortan Throg's
earlier efforts and for rescuing Princess Sarissa.  They were also
given 60 GP each as an advance for their next efforts, and
a healing potion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help them slip into Port Blacksand in disguise, they were given a
wagon of goods and Merchant Passes for each of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They entered the city and found their way to the Dragon's Tooth Inn,
where they turn over the wagon to their contact, Halim Thrumbar.  He
gave them directions to where Nicodemus lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gordo wanted to gamble in the inn, but Grimbold tried to drag him
away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They went to Nicodemus's and after a little discussion were admitted.
Nicodemus told them that Xortan Throg lives in Port Blacksand, where
he can study the ruins of Carsepolis, in the sewers of Port Blacksand,
and has some dealings with the Fish People. He suggests that they
start by looking near the old sluice-gates down by the docks at dusk.
They do, and see pirates entered the sewers guided by Fish Men, and
decide to follow them at a distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the way they fight a giant centipede that attacks them.  Gordo
strikes the blow that kills the centipede.  Aspen is knocked into the
sewer and starts to drown.  Alexa pulls her out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff1e" label="aff1e"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lessons from Titan and Advanced Fighting Fantasy</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/16/lessons-from-titan-and-advanced-fighting-fantasy/</id>
    <updated>2012-10-16T10:07:04-05:00</updated>
    <published>2012-10-16T10:07:04-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/16/lessons-from-titan-and-advanced-fighting-fantasy/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back at the beginning of October I started a thread on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rpg.net/"&gt;rpg.net&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://forum.rpg.net/showthread.php?656478-Advanced-Fighting-Fantasy-Distinctive-elements-of-Titan-and-FF-for-an-adventure"&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy: Distinctive elements of Titan and FF for
an adventure?&lt;/a&gt; to collect ideas for what should go in a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.arion-games.com/aff.html"&gt;AFF&lt;/a&gt;
adventure I want to write for my gaming group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I ran across a blog post, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://drbargle.blogspot.co.uk/2012/07/titanic-bullet-points.html"&gt;Known World, Old World: Titanic
Lesson Plan&lt;/a&gt;, which also talks about distinctive elements of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Titan_-_The_Fighting_Fantasy_World"&gt;Titan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff" label="aff"/>
    <category term="ff" label="ff"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="gamebooks" label="gamebooks"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
    <category term="titan" label="titan"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>AFF1e: Dungeoneer Adventure I: Tower of the Sorcerer, Part 2</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/13/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-2/</id>
    <updated>2012-10-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2012-10-13T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/13/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-2/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing “Dungeoneer Adventure I: Tower of the Sorcerer”, from
&lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to skip
this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/06/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/"&gt;Previously&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scheduling didn't work out again, so L.B. couldn't join us via Google
Hangouts, alas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwise, starting with the Director:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Director&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — Grimbold Tornhelm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. — Gordo Brondwyn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. — Aspen Darkfire; she also played Alexa Wolfrica, L.B.'s
character, since L.B. couldn't attend&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Griffin's door, they unlocked the door, they unbarred the door,
and then Aspen (at Alexa's suggestion) listens at the door and hears
very interesting things.  They decided to rebar the door and go on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They opened the Giant Lizard's door, saw the saddle, saw the lizard,
and pulled the door shut and barred it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Guardroom, there was a lot of throwing chairs, by both sides.
Alexa was reduced to –1 STAMINA by an opponent's &lt;span class="mech"&gt;Mighty Blow&lt;/span&gt;.
Aspen cast &lt;span class="spell"&gt;Stamina&lt;/span&gt;, bringing Alexa back to 5 STAMINA, and
then Gordo was taken to –1 STAMINA by another opponent's &lt;span class="mech"&gt;Mighty
Blow&lt;/span&gt;, and was brought back to 5 STAMINA by another &lt;span class="spell"&gt;Stamina&lt;/span&gt;
from Aspen.  All through the fight the Ogre had been laughing at the
Heroes and throwing stuff at them that knocked them down, but Aspen
had been steadily sniping at them, and despite one impressive
&lt;span class="skill"&gt;Dodge&lt;/span&gt;, where the Ogre interposed a Goblin haunch from his supper
and blocked an arrow she had steadily brought his STAMINA down.  When
the Orcs were finally disposed of and he threw the table on the Heros,
Aspen was far enough back to escape the spill, and switched from
arrows to &lt;span class="spell"&gt;Fire Bolt&lt;/span&gt;, rolled a 6 for damage, and the Ogre fell
down dead!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the battle Alexa cast &lt;span class="spell"&gt;Stamina&lt;/span&gt; (which for her is
just a natural ability, a “second wind”, not a spell), and got an
&lt;span class="mech"&gt;Oops!&lt;/span&gt;, and E.A. rolled a 13 on the “Oops! Table”, and Alexa
ended up with a pair of small goat horns!  Eventually everybody was
back up to full STAMINA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the sorcerer's chambers they killed Xortan Throg and tried &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt;
to kill evil Prince Barinjhar by pulling their blows, hoping to return
him to his father for rehabilitation.  However, he died while they
were searching Xortan Throg's study and freeing Princess Sarissa.
They found him dead when the returned to the main chamber.  The real
Xortan Throg clued them in, via a vision in the fire in the fireplace,
that they had killed a fake, and that he was still alive and looking
forward to destroying them and Salamonis.  Since they'd killed the
Prince, they decided traveling to Salamonis with Princess Sarissa was
a good idea, and headed back out through the Goblin cave to avoid
Prince Barinjhar's soldiers, outside, and set off in direction of the
fabled city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All characters got &lt;strong&gt;+3 XP&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kids picked up on throwing things pretty quickly; I'll have to see
what other sorts of tactical twists we use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed running this, and the kids had fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff1e" label="aff1e"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>AFF1e: Dungeoneer Adventure I: Tower of the Sorcerer, Part 1</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/06/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/</id>
    <updated>2012-10-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2012-10-06T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/10/06/aff1e-dungeoneer-adventure-i-tower-of-the-sorcerer-part-1/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing “Dungeoneer Adventure I: Tower of the Sorcerer”, from
&lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to skip
this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I've mentioned &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#at-my-table"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt; I've been trying to use the RPGs derived
from the &lt;cite&gt;Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt; gamebooks for pickup games with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;.
This time around I switched from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#fighting-fantasy-the-introductory-role-playing-game"&gt;Fighting Fantasy — The Introductory
Role-playing Game&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;cite&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/cite&gt;) to Dungeoneer, the first book of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#advanced-fighting-fantasy-aff"&gt;Advanced
Fighting Fantasy&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;cite&gt;AFF1e&lt;/cite&gt;), and started “Dungeoneer Adventure I: Tower of the
Sorcerer”, the first introductory scenario in the book, using the
pre-generated characters from the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to get L.B. in the game through Google Hangouts, but
unfortunately the scheduling didn't work out.  She did pick a
character, Alex Wolfric, and I turned modified the character sheet
turning the character in Alexa Wolfrica.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwise, starting with the Director:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Director&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — Grimbold Tornhelm&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. — Gordo Brondwyn&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. — Aspen Darkfire; she also played Alexa Wolfrica, L.B.'s
character, since L.B. couldn't attend&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="previously"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Previously&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the occasion that the kids picked out their characters from the
pre-gens I ran a combat between Gordo Brondwyn and Grimbold Tornhelm
so they could see how combat and skills worked.  Gordo threw daggers
at Grimbold and kept out of his reach, but didn't have much recourse
once he'd thrown all his daggers.  I stopped the combat there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="more-rules-familiarization"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;More Rules Familiarization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started out with some combat with Aspen Darkfire and Alexa Wolfrica
versus Gordo Brondwyn, so E.A. could see how combat and surprise
rounds worked, and how spells worked, since she was the only player
who would be running spellcasters this episode, and everybody could
see how combat between one character on one side and multiple
characters on the other side worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I had them do some tunnel exploring under an abandoned temple to
show them how some of the other Special Skills worked, including
&lt;span class="skill"&gt;Trap Sense&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="skill"&gt;Underground Lore&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="skill"&gt;Dark Sense&lt;/span&gt;, and
&lt;span class="skill"&gt;Awareness&lt;/span&gt;.  There were pressure plates, a rolling boulder (ala
Indiana Jones), and a chasm across the tunnel that the boulder herded
them toward.  Aspen and Alexa both noticed the chasm, but Gordo and
Grimbold, behind them, did not, and right out into midair, luckily
crashing into and grabbing hold of the other side of the chasm, and
narrowly missed by the boulder.  Alexa and Aspen helped them up
afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-adventure"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Adventure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kids' characters talked with Prince Barinjhar and Morval for a
while, then headed off down the indicated path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They entered the tunnel, and found the main cave full of Goblins, who
they handily defeated, each killing three.  Alexa managed to pick up
the portcullis blocking the tunnel to the tower all by herself, an
impressive deed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later she broke open both doors to the prisoner cells, freeing Xortan
Throg's experimental subjects, the peasants Rufus (hunchback, one arm
6 inches longer than the other) and Sam (triangular head and deformed
legs).  The characters escorted them back through the portcullis and
provided them with torches and directions out of the tunnel, then
returned to the stairs leading upwards beyond the cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kids seemed to enjoy the game: E.A. and M.A. said so explicitly,
and T.A. liked that the characters started out as super competent
Heroes rather than 1&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt;-level nobodies.  They all liked how they
mowed down the Goblins.  T.A. liked the fact that it added detail to
&lt;cite&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/cite&gt;, since he likes game systems with more detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think next time I'll add some examples of improvised tactical SKILL
use, to show how combat can be something besides just opposed SKILL
rolls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff1e" label="aff1e"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>FF:TIRpG: Shaggradd's Hives of Peril: the Missing Session?</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/09/17/ff-tirpg-shaggradds-hives-of-peril-play-session-missing/</id>
    <updated>2012-09-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2012-09-17T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/09/17/ff-tirpg-shaggradds-hives-of-peril-play-session-missing/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;!-- area has CSS on the blog. --&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing the adventure &lt;cite&gt;Shaggradd's Hives of Peril&lt;/cite&gt; from
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#fighting-fantasy-the-introductory-role-playing-game"&gt;Fighting Fantasy — The Introductory Role-playing Game&lt;/a&gt;
(FF:TIRpG), so if you haven't played that you might want to skip
this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I've mentioned &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, I've been trying to use the RPGs derived
from the &lt;cite&gt;Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt; gamebooks for pickup games with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;,
starting with the second adventure from &lt;cite&gt;Fighting Fantasy —
The Introductory Role-playing Game&lt;/cite&gt; (FF:TIRpG), &lt;cite&gt;Shaggradd's Hives of
Peril&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="i-m-confused"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I'm Confused&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reason, I think we played another short session of
&lt;cite&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/cite&gt;, but if so I've lost my notes.  Did &lt;span class="player"&gt;D.B.&lt;/span&gt; play?
Did he play &lt;span class="pc"&gt;Oswald&lt;/span&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="actual-play" label="actual-play"/>
    <category term="ff" label="ff"/>
    <category term="fftirpg" label="ff:tirpg"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="gaming" label="gaming"/>
    <category term="missing" label="missing"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
    <category term="spoilers" label="spoilers"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>FF:TIRpG: Shaggradd's Hives of Peril: Play Session #2</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/10/30/ff-tirpg-shaggradds-hives-of-peril-play-session-2/</id>
    <updated>2011-10-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2011-10-30T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/10/30/ff-tirpg-shaggradds-hives-of-peril-play-session-2/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;!-- area has CSS on the blog. --&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing the adventure &lt;cite&gt;Shaggradd's Hives of Peril&lt;/cite&gt; from
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#fighting-fantasy-the-introductory-role-playing-game"&gt;Fighting Fantasy — The Introductory Role-playing Game&lt;/a&gt;
(FF:TIRpG), so if you haven't played that you might want to skip
this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I've mentioned &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, I've been planning to use the RPGs derived
from the &lt;cite&gt;Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt; gamebooks for pickup games with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/08/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;,
today we continued with the second adventure from &lt;cite&gt;Fighting Fantasy —
The Introductory Role-playing Game&lt;/cite&gt; (FF:TIRpG), &lt;cite&gt;Shaggradd's Hives of
Peril&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — GamesMaster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. played&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ezarik (e-ZAR-ik) — SKILL 8, STAMINA 17, LUCK 10.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oswald — SKILL 10, STAMINA 21, LUCK 12, who was already lost in
the treasure vaults in the dark.  (This was C.A.'s character from
the earlier game, but he wasn't available today.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. played Letty Letitia — SKILL 10, STAMINA 19, LUCK 10.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. played Toth — SKILL 8, STAMINA 17, LUCK 9.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;L.B. played Amber — SKILL 12 STAMINA 21 LUCK 8.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amber introduced herself as &lt;strong&gt;Judy&lt;/strong&gt; for some reason.  (The player did
this deliberately.  I have no idea why.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Started in &lt;span class="area"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;, went to &lt;span class="area"&gt;19&lt;/span&gt;, then &lt;span class="area"&gt;22&lt;/span&gt;.  They
skinned the weretiger.  On to &lt;span class="area"&gt;23&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="area"&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="area"&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;.
Finally Lettie looked in &lt;span class="area"&gt;18&lt;/span&gt; and then the door shut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The kids were giddy, and the game didn't last very long, alas.  No
doubt the chaos contributed to my inability to take good notes this
session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="actual-play" label="actual-play"/>
    <category term="ff" label="ff"/>
    <category term="fftirpg" label="ff:tirpg"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="gaming" label="gaming"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
    <category term="spoilers" label="spoilers"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>FF:TIRpG: Shaggradd's Hives of Peril: Play Session #1</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/24/ff-tirpg-shaggradds-hives-of-peril-play-session-1/</id>
    <updated>2011-09-24T22:28:12-05:00</updated>
    <published>2011-09-24T22:28:12-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/24/ff-tirpg-shaggradds-hives-of-peril-play-session-1/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;!-- area has CSS on the blog. --&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing the adventure &lt;cite&gt;Shaggradd's Hives of Peril&lt;/cite&gt; from
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#fighting-fantasy-the-introductory-role-playing-game"&gt;Fighting Fantasy — The Introductory Role-playing Game&lt;/a&gt;
(FF:TIRpG), so if you haven't played that you might want to skip
this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I've mentioned &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, I've been planning to use the RPGs derived
from the &lt;cite&gt;Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt; gamebooks for pickup games with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/08/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;,
and today I was able to put that plan into action, starting as planned
with &lt;cite&gt;Fighting Fantasy — The Introductory Role-playing Game&lt;/cite&gt;
(FF:TIRpG), using the second adventure from the the book, &lt;cite&gt;Shaggradd's
Hives of Peril&lt;/cite&gt;. &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/24/ff-tirpg-shaggradds-hives-of-peril-play-session-1/#well" id="id2"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;M.A. and E.A. were watching a movie, but T.A. (as always) was eager to
play, and as we were getting started C.A., who had heard us talking
about gaming earlier and said he wanted to play, wandered in and
wanted to join in, so I had him roll up a character too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — GamesMaster.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. played Ezarik (e-ZAR-ik) — SKILL 8, STAMINA 17, LUCK 10.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;C.A. played Oswald — SKILL 10, STAMINA 21, LUCK 12, who was already
lost in the treasure vaults in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T.A. had rolled up his character and was speaking with
&lt;span class="npc"&gt;Shaggradd&lt;/span&gt; when C.A. showed up.  I decided that Ezarik would
meet C.A.'s character, Oswald, down in the treasure vaults, where he'd
been sitting in the dark after his candle burned out after he‘d run
from a monster.  So we rolled up a character, who turned out to be
skilled, strong, and lucky, named him Oswald, and went back to Ezarik.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="npc"&gt;Shaggradd&lt;/span&gt; blindfolded Ezarik, lead him around by hand, spun him
around in a circle, told him to hunker down, and pushed him into a low
tunnel.  After he refused the 2% extra on the 10% entrance fee for her
to cast a &lt;em&gt;Reverse Teleport&lt;/em&gt; on him, she pulled off the blindfold and
pushed him further in, and slammed a door on him.  After he lit his
lantern, he could see that he was in small tunnel with rotting wood
sides, that opened out into a taller and slightly larger roughly
circular room.  The floor of the tunnel and the room were both dirt,
and in the cent of the room was a pit trailing down into blackness,
with a rope tied to a black spike hammered into the rotting wall of
the chamber, covered with spider webs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Descending the rope he ended up in a &lt;span class="area"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;, small chamber dug into
the earth, with four exits at right angles.  He took the exit to the
west, leading to &lt;span class="area"&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;, a large cavern with a skull carved into
the east all, with three tunnels leading out through missing teeth in
the skull.  He headed out the middle passage, and after a little while
heard the sound of a stream, but couldn't see it. &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/24/ff-tirpg-shaggradds-hives-of-peril-play-session-1/#no-bridge" id="id3"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; A
little further on he found a little man, about a metre tall and
dressed in what appeared to be the entire skin of a small dragon&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/24/ff-tirpg-shaggradds-hives-of-peril-play-session-1/#dragonhide" id="id4"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;, wings and tail included, cleverly formed so that the
rear feet were boots, the fore feet were gauntlets, and the head was a
helmet, with the face appearing through the mouth of the beast,
sitting next to a puddle of wax that was all that left of his candle.
This was Oswald, a hobbit, and as it turned out he was very hungry.
He had lost his way while being chased by a monster, and then his
candled had burned out, leaving him waiting in the dark, as he hand
not taken advantage of &lt;span class="npc"&gt;Shaggradd&lt;/span&gt;'s offer of a &lt;span class="spell"&gt;Reverse
Teleport&lt;/span&gt; either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continued on to &lt;span class="area"&gt;35&lt;/span&gt;.  Pulled lever.  Could see just a &lt;em&gt;bit&lt;/em&gt; by
the light of a phosphorescent plant growing on the surface of the
cavern.  Not knowing where they were they headed out the only entrance
they say, and back to &lt;span class="area"&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;, where they recognized the skill.
This time they took the right (north) passage to &lt;span class="area"&gt;31&lt;/span&gt;, and
started to enter the middle passage there, but a &lt;span class="creature"&gt;troll&lt;/span&gt;
popped out of the passage and attacked them.  After exchanging a few
blows with the troll and getting a small cut on one cheek, Oswald
fled, leaving behind his companion and his companion's lantern!
Ezarik stayed behind and fought the troll for another round, and then
pursued his companion, and luckily the troll did not follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Oswald ran back down the passage to &lt;span class="area"&gt;30&lt;/span&gt;, bounced off
the wall and ran through the passage to &lt;span class="area"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; and straight across
and out the passage that lead to the collapsing stairs, slide down the
stairs, stumbled across the gravel beach, through the water, and
finally sat down on the ground beyond the stream in &lt;span class="area"&gt;19&lt;/span&gt;, in the
dark again.  He could smell some delicious fruit nearby….&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ezarik, fleeing the troll, guessed at the likely route Oswald had
taken and quickly found him, sliding down the collapsing stairs into
&lt;span class="area"&gt;19&lt;/span&gt; and wrenching his arm in his fall.  Glad to be reunited,
Oswald drinks some water from the stream while Ezarik eats some of his
provisions.  The smell of delicious fruit was coming from some large
green fruits on a strange underground tree.  After they rested a few
minutes they continue exploring, taking the passage east until it
forked and then taking the north-east slanting passage until it ended
in a dead end, &lt;span class="area"&gt;20&lt;/span&gt;.  Returning to the fork in the passage, they
entered a very hot room half filled with burning coals, &lt;span class="area"&gt;21&lt;/span&gt;,
where a fiery lizard squeaked at them.  Oswald squeaked back, but the
lizard was puzzled.  They left that room through another door, where
they discovered a tall red-headed man sleeping (&lt;span class="area"&gt;22&lt;/span&gt;).
Unfortunately, he woke up and was very angry, demanding that they
leave immediately.  They went back through the door to &lt;span class="area"&gt;21&lt;/span&gt;,
Oswald apologizing to the man for waking him up, and the man calming
down and going back to bed.  Then they returned to the cavern with the
stream, where Oswald climbed up into the tree and started to pick a
fruit, noticing a key in the tree as he did so.  Unfortunately, just
at that moment, five of the fruit hatched into large angry goose-like
red birds, and began attacking.  Oswald fled east into the passageway,
as did Ezarik, though he tried and failed to grab the key as he fled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is where we ended for the evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the evening we learned that Oswald's dragon armor
and dragon tooth sword were not family heirlooms, that he could play
both the piano and the flute, and that he had lost a wand and a map
earlier in the these caverns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplicity of &lt;cite&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/cite&gt; makes it a great pickup game. There are
only three stats, SKILL, STAMINA, an LUCK, so rolling up a character
is trivial, which is great for when somebody unexpected shows up in
the middle of things and wants to play — say, for example, a
three-year-old, C.A.  And the rules are so simple that after you have
played a few times you can easily remember them, so you don't even
need to have your rule book handy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Playing with a three year old has a few pitfalls.   C.A. has a great
vocabulary, and uses pretty complicated sentences, but his
pronunciation is somewhat unclear, adding to our communication
difficulties.   He's not familiar with the fantasy genre, so doesn't
know that there are no flashlights or cars or technology.  And he
hasn't quit figured out that once his character is in a situation, he
has to deal with the situation using only the resources he has at hand
already and what's available in the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, he's also a lot of fun to play with.  He comes up
with lots of interesting details about his character, he tries
interesting things, he has fun seeing what's going to happen next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T.A. liked the game, though it was not his favorite.  (I think he's
used to more detailed systems, and prefers them to something this
simple.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="well"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/24/ff-tirpg-shaggradds-hives-of-peril-play-session-1/#id2"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first adventure from &lt;cite&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/cite&gt;, &lt;cite&gt;The Wishing Well&lt;/cite&gt;, is
shorter.   It is also redone in Arion Games' &lt;cite&gt;Advanced Fighting
Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt;, 2e, with example characters, so I'll probably start our
&lt;cite&gt;AFF2e&lt;/cite&gt; game off with that adventure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="no-bridge"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/24/ff-tirpg-shaggradds-hives-of-peril-play-session-1/#id3"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's not immediately obvious from the map, but later
area description text makes it clear that the corridor from
&lt;span class="area"&gt;30&lt;/span&gt; to &lt;span class="area"&gt;35&lt;/span&gt; crosses the stream on a bridge.  Since I
hadn't read that area description yet, I went with an unseen but
not unheard stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="dragonhide"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/24/ff-tirpg-shaggradds-hives-of-peril-play-session-1/#id4"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;C.A. was dressed in a dragon suit, making him look
much like an Anne Geddes picture, so I carried that element into
the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="actual-play" label="actual-play"/>
    <category term="ff" label="ff"/>
    <category term="fftirpg" label="ff:tirpg"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="gaming" label="gaming"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
    <category term="spoilers" label="spoilers"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Fighting Fantasy and Advanced Fighting Fantasy RPGs</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/</id>
    <updated>2011-09-22T19:45:22-05:00</updated>
    <published>2011-09-22T19:45:22-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;section id="i-missed-out"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I missed out…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somehow I completely missed out on the &lt;cite&gt;Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt;:series (&lt;cite class="abbrevtitle"&gt;FF&lt;/cite&gt;)
gamebooks during their initial run.  Probably, since I was already
playing &lt;cite class="abbrevtitle"&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt;, &lt;cite class="abbrevtitle"&gt;T&amp;amp;T&lt;/cite&gt;, and &lt;cite class="abbrevtitle"&gt;DQ&lt;/cite&gt;, the solitary fun of the gamebooks was
not as appealing as the social fun of tabletop RPGs, and what little
desire I had for something like gamebooks was was more than adequately
served by &lt;cite class="abbrevtitle"&gt;T&amp;amp;T&lt;/cite&gt; solo adventures.  In any case, I never owned any &lt;cite class="abbrevtitle"&gt;FF&lt;/cite&gt;
gamebooks until I picked up the 2003 iBooks reprints of &lt;cite&gt;The Warlock
of Firetop Mountain&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;The Citadel of Chaos&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also means that I missed out on the &lt;cite class="abbrevtitle"&gt;FF&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#aff"&gt;AFF&lt;/a&gt; RPGs, as
well.  Thank &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Hamaskis"&gt;Hamaskis&lt;/a&gt; for Internet bookstores!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="but-internet-rpg-forums-are-amazing"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;…but Internet RPG Forums are amazing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had run across a mention of a &lt;cite&gt;Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt; RPG, somewhere
(probably on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://forum.rpg.net/"&gt;rpg.net&lt;/a&gt;), and eventually figured out it was &lt;cite&gt;Fighting
Fantasy — The Introductory Role-playing Game&lt;/cite&gt; (&lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#ff-tirpg"&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/a&gt;) and
purchased a copy from a used bookstore online.  It was easy to find,
as I recall. &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#many" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mechanically it is the system from the &lt;cite class="abbrevtitle"&gt;FF&lt;/cite&gt; gamebooks, but with
explanations for new tabletop gamers of how to use it for tabletop
gaming.  It is actually a nice introductory RPG, but it was a little
too simple for the game I wanted, and my interested stopped there for
a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I only got &lt;cite&gt;The Riddling Reaver&lt;/cite&gt;, a collection of adventures for
&lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#ff-tirpg"&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/a&gt;, in 2011, after I got &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#aff2e"&gt;AFF2e&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#aff"&gt;AFF&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point I figured out (again, probably by reading on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://forum.rpg.net/"&gt;rpg.net&lt;/a&gt;)
that the &lt;cite&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt; RPG was a different set of books
from the &lt;cite class="abbrevtitle"&gt;FF&lt;/cite&gt; RPG, with a more detailed system, and it was probably
what I should have been looking for instead of &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#ff-tirpg"&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/a&gt;, but my
interest had fallen asleep; no doubt in part because the third book of the
set, &lt;cite&gt;Allansia&lt;/cite&gt;, was reputedly difficult and expensive to get. &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#few" id="id2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.arion-games.com/"&gt;Arion Games&lt;/a&gt; edition (&lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#aff2e"&gt;AFF2e&lt;/a&gt;) published in 2011
reawakened my interest.  I got that edition, and liked the system and
setting, but wondered how different it was to the original &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#aff"&gt;AFF&lt;/a&gt;.
Eventually I decided I wanted to compare &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#aff2e"&gt;AFF2e&lt;/a&gt; to the original
&lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#aff"&gt;AFF&lt;/a&gt;, so it was back to the Internet bookstores.  &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt; and
&lt;cite&gt;Blacksand!&lt;/cite&gt; were relatively easy to find (&lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt; in
particular), but an relatively affordable copy of &lt;cite&gt;Allansia&lt;/cite&gt; was more
difficult.  Eventually I was successful. Yesterday &lt;cite&gt;Allansia&lt;/cite&gt; arrived,
and today &lt;cite&gt;Blacksand!&lt;/cite&gt; arrived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="at-my-table"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;At My Table&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm planning to use &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#aff"&gt;AFF&lt;/a&gt; as my pickup game with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/08/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;, the game
we play when something else has to be canceled, too few players are
available, or I'm just too tired to play anything more complicated.
I'm looking to make use of the &lt;cite&gt;Titan&lt;/cite&gt; setting, with all its
over-the-top fantasy elements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to start with the original &lt;cite class="abbrevtitle"&gt;FF&lt;/cite&gt; RPG, play that for a few
sessions, add in the stuff from &lt;cite&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/cite&gt;, then &lt;cite&gt;Blacksand!&lt;/cite&gt;, then
&lt;cite&gt;Allansia&lt;/cite&gt;, maybe all in the same episodic campaign.  Eventually I'll
transition to another campaign, using the &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#aff"&gt;AFF&lt;/a&gt; 2e rules.  At the end
of it all I should be able to do a good comparison of all three rules
sets.  Maybe then I'll do an actual review, but don't hold your
breath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="fighting-fantasy-and-advanced-fighting-fantasy-rpg-bibliography"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fighting Fantasy and Advanced Fighting Fantasy RPG Bibliography&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="fighting-fantasy-the-introductory-role-playing-game-ff-tirpg"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Fighting Fantasy — The Introductory Role-playing Game (FF:TIRpG)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p id="ff-tirpg"&gt;The system in &lt;cite&gt;Fighting Fantasy - The Introductory Role-playing Game&lt;/cite&gt;
is pretty much the same as in the &lt;cite class="series"&gt;Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt; game
books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game calls the person who ‘controls’ the game the GameMaster or
GM (p. 11).  The player characters are called “adventureres” (p. 9, 10).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Fighting_Fantasy_-_The_Introductory_Role-Playing_Game"&gt;Fighting Fantasy&lt;/a&gt; — &lt;cite class="subtitle"&gt;The Introductory Role-playing Game&lt;/cite&gt;
(copyright 1984 by Steve Jackson; ISBN 0-14-031709-0), and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/The_Riddling_Reaver_(book)"&gt;The Riddling Reaver&lt;/a&gt; (copyright 1986 by Steve Jackson, Paul
Mason, and Steve Williams; ISBN 0-14-032156-X), a collection of
four adventures for &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#ff-tirpg"&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are standard mass-market paperbacks, 11×17.6 cm, 4¼×6⅞ in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were also the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Fighting_Fantasy_Manual"&gt;Fighting Fantasy Manuals&lt;/a&gt;, a couple of books
detailing the monsters and world of the &lt;cite class="abbrevtitle"&gt;FF&lt;/cite&gt; gamebooks: &lt;cite&gt;Out of the
Pit&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Titan&lt;/cite&gt;.  These are large format paperbacks, A4 sized (around
US Letter sized).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Out_of_the_Pit"&gt;Out of the Pit&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;cite class="subtitle"&gt;Fighting Fantasy Monsters&lt;/cite&gt; (copyright
1985 by Marc Gascoigne, Steve Jackson, and Ian Livingstone;
ISBN ISBN 0-14-031999-9), and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Titan_-_The_Fighting_Fantasy_World"&gt;Titan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;cite class="subtitle"&gt;The Fighting Fantasy World&lt;/cite&gt; (copyright 1986 by Marc
Gascoigne, Steve Jackson, and Ian Livingstone; ISBN 0-14-032127-6)
detailing the Fighting Fantasy world).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="advanced-fighting-fantasy-aff"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy (AFF)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p id="aff"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Advanced_Fighting_Fantasy"&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy&lt;/a&gt; took the role-playing system from the
gamebooks and &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#ff-tirpg"&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/a&gt; and developed them in more detail, adding
‘Special Skills', which allow characters to more skilled in specific
areas than just their general SKILL, a magic system, a couple of mass
battle systems, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game uses the metaphor of making a fantasy movie, so the person
running the game is called the &lt;em&gt;Director&lt;/em&gt; (p. 11) and the player
characters are called &lt;em&gt;Heroes&lt;/em&gt; (p. 9).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Dungeoneer_(book)"&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/a&gt; (text copyright 1989 by Marc Gascoigne and Pete Tamlyn;
ISBN 0-14-032936-6),&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Blacksand!"&gt;Blacksand!&lt;/a&gt; (text copyright 1990 by Marc Gascoigne and Pete Tamlyn;
ISBN 0-14-034396-2), and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Allansia_(book)"&gt;Allansia&lt;/a&gt; (text copyright 1994 by Marc Gascoigne and Pete Tamlyn;
ISBN 0-14-036051-4),&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were published as paperbacks approximately 13×20 cm, about
5×7¾ in.  There were matching releases of &lt;cite&gt;Out of the Pit&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Titan&lt;/cite&gt;
to go along with the new game, in the same size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Out_of_the_Pit"&gt;Out of the Pit&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;cite class="subtitle"&gt;Fighting Fantasy Monsters&lt;/cite&gt; (copyright
1985 by Marc Gascoigne, Steve Jackson, and Ian Livingstone;
ISBN 0-14-034131-5), and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://fightingfantasy.wikia.com/wiki/Titan_-_The_Fighting_Fantasy_World"&gt;Titan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;cite class="subtitle"&gt;The Fighting Fantasy World&lt;/cite&gt; (copyright 1986 by Marc
Gascoigne, Steve Jackson, and Ian Livingstone; ISBN 0-14-034132-3)
detailing the Fighting Fantasy world).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="advanced-fighting-fantasy-2nd-edition-aff2e"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy, 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; edition (AFF2e)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p id="aff2e"&gt;In 2011 &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.arion-games.com/"&gt;Arion Games&lt;/a&gt; published a 2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; edition, distributed
by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.cubicle7.co.uk/"&gt;Cubicle 7&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Advanced Fighting Fantasy&lt;/cite&gt;, &lt;cite class="subtitle"&gt;The Roleplaying Game&lt;/cite&gt;,
2&lt;sup&gt;nd&lt;/sup&gt; edition (copyright 2011 by Graham Bottley, Steve
Jackson, and Ian Livingston; ISBN 978-0-85744-067-9),&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Out of the Pit&lt;/cite&gt; (copyright 1985; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.arion-games.com/"&gt;Arion Games&lt;/a&gt; edition 2011,
ISBN 978-0-85744-068-6), and&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Titan&lt;/cite&gt;, (copyright 1986; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.arion-games.com/"&gt;Arion Games&lt;/a&gt; edition 2011,
ISBN 978-9-85744-069-3).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These paperbacks are approximately 21.5×28 cm, pretty much exactly
8.5×11 in.  These editions of &lt;cite&gt;Out of the Pit&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Titan&lt;/cite&gt; are
essentially straight reprints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the license &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.arion-games.com/"&gt;Arion Games&lt;/a&gt; has to publish &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#aff2e"&gt;AFF2e&lt;/a&gt;
precludes PDF versions of the books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="many"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don't know if &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#ff-tirpg"&gt;FF:TIRpG&lt;/a&gt; was easy to find because they
printed so many of it, or if it was just part of the large print
runs they used to use in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="few"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#id2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I suspect that &lt;cite&gt;Allansia&lt;/cite&gt; was published late enough that
print runs in general had shrunk in size considerably, even if the
print run for &lt;cite&gt;Allansia&lt;/cite&gt; in particular was small simply because it
was the third book in the &lt;a class="reference internal" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/09/22/fighting-fantasy-rpgs/#aff"&gt;AFF&lt;/a&gt; RPG series, which was bound to make
it less  popular than the gamebooks in any case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="advanced-fighting-fantasy" label="advanced fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="aff" label="aff"/>
    <category term="aff2e" label="aff2e"/>
    <category term="ff" label="ff"/>
    <category term="fftirpg" label="ff:tirpg"/>
    <category term="fighting-fantasy" label="fighting fantasy"/>
    <category term="gamebooks" label="gamebooks"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
