<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about free software)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/free-software.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 07:47:20 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Recent Reading; Where free software is failing</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/08/25/2003-08-25/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;section id="recent-reading"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recent Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Transit to Scorpio&lt;/cite&gt;, as by Alan Burt Akers; actually written by Ken
Bulmer.  The earlier books in this series have Alan Burt Akers listed as
their author while the later books are listed under Dray Prescot, but
they were actually written by Henry Kenneth Bulmer, a prolific writer
of science fiction and other things.  The Dray Prescot Saga is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.kregen.com/booklist.html"&gt;long&lt;/a&gt; series in the planetary
romance genre.  The first 37 of the books were published in English
(starting in 1972 and continuing into the early 1990s) and the rest of
the 52 books were published in German.  They are the story of Dray
Prescot, a 18th century sailor who is transported to the distant
planet of Kregen and his adventures there as nomad, slave, warrior,
pirate, and reluctant troubleshooter for two opposing superhuman
forces.  Like most classic planetary romance, these are rousing tales
of adventure, straightforward wholesome escapist fantasy.  The length
of the series, however, allows this to be something more than than a
mere escape, as we watch Dray Prescot develop from a typical warrior
stereotype into something more interesting and see how the many themes
of the series (friendship, identity, fair play, prejudice, religion,
and trust among them) develop through a much longer period than most
authors are able to devote.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="where-free-software-is-failing"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where free software is failing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Barlow's blog for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ww.telent.net/diary/2003/8/#25.67406"&gt;Monday, 25 Aug 2003&lt;/a&gt; talks about Tom
Lord's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20030607173459/http://lists.fifthvision.net/pipermail/arch-users/2003-May/027591.html"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; that talks about where Free Software is
failing to think ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>free software</category><category>old blog</category><category>recent reading</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/08/25/2003-08-25/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 25 Aug 2003 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>