<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about gdw)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/gdw.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2022 15:17:48 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Recent Reading: Marc W. Miller</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/05/02/marc-w-miller-gdw/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Double Adventure 1: Shadows &amp;amp; Annic Nova&lt;/cite&gt;, by Marc W. Miller;
copyright © 1980 by Game Designers' Workshop; 7th printing;
Product #312.  Art on page 19 by Liz Danforth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to see how these adventures differ from current
adventure design.  Both of these adventures present a location with
details about its contents, and give a way that a group of player
characters might get involved.  One of the adventures gives a page
of historical background of the location for the GM, although the
background doesn't directly affect play.  The other gives no history
at all, other than what can be gleaned from observing the location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trend in commercial RPG adventure design has been to deliver
more and more detail for the GM, culminating in the current D&amp;amp;D
adventure format that attempts to provide, on a two-page spread,
absolutely everything that a DM has to have to run a tactical
encounter, from the tactical map to the exact details of each and
every NPC involved, so that the DM doesn't have to look anything up.
Moreover, in many modules, perhaps starting with the &lt;cite&gt;Dragonlance&lt;/cite&gt;
modules in the 1980s, there is a story supplied, which the player
characters are expected, more or less, to follow and figure out, and
some more-or-less obvious goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Shadows&lt;/cite&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;cite&gt;Annic Nova&lt;/cite&gt; certainly don't supply a pre-built story —
any story will be generated by the referee and players at the gaming
table, with possibly some pre-game activity by the referee while
reading the adventure beforehand.  And there are no obvious goals,
just situations to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually find this rather liberating, compared to the more
detailed adventures that are more common today.  There is something
about the things that aren't there in &lt;cite&gt;Shadows&lt;/cite&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;cite&gt;Annic Nova&lt;/cite&gt; that
fires up my imagination and draws me into the situation.  It's
probably the same sort of thing that makes me see the original
&lt;cite&gt;Greyhawk&lt;/cite&gt; folio as more interesting that the later &lt;cite&gt;Living Greyhawk
Gazetteer&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mention Liz Danforth in the info about the book above because ever
since I ran across her art in 5th edition &lt;cite&gt;Tunnels &amp;amp; Trolls&lt;/cite&gt; I've
enjoyed it immensely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>adventure design</category><category>classic traveller</category><category>d&amp;d</category><category>gaming</category><category>gdw</category><category>liz danforth</category><category>recent reading</category><category>rpg</category><category>traveller</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/05/02/marc-w-miller-gdw/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2009 20:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>