<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about heinlein)</title>
  <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/heinlein.atom</id>
  <updated>2023-02-19T19:01:25Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/heinlein.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/heinlein/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Recent Reading: Heinlein</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/05/recent-reading-heinlein/</id>
    <updated>2008-07-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2008-07-05T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/05/recent-reading-heinlein/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently decided that I need to read Heinlein's juvenile novels.
I'd read some of them in my youth (thanks to the Weston and Clarksburg
public libraries), but not all, and I wondered how they would stand up
in the 21st century to my middle-aged eyes, and how interesting they
might be to younger eyes as well.   (I'll have to wait a bit to see
the later, though.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, inexpensive compilations published by the Science Fiction
Bookclub are easily available from online sellers, and I got four
volumes that include all the juveniles, as well as &lt;cite&gt;Starship
Troopers&lt;/cite&gt;.  &lt;cite&gt;Four Frontiers&lt;/cite&gt; is the first of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Four Frontiers&lt;/cite&gt;, by Robert A. Heinlein; First Science Fiction Book
Club printing: June 2005.  Published by arrangement with “The
Robert A. &amp;amp; Virginia Heinlein Prize Trust” and “The Robert A. &amp;amp;
Virginia Heinlein Library Foundation”, and Tor Books, and The
Berkley Publishing Group, a division of Penguin Group (USA) Inc.
ISBN 0-7394-5345-9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Rocket Ship Galileo&lt;/cite&gt;, copyright 1947 by Robert A. Heinlein,
copyright renewed 1974 by Robert A. Heinlein, Copyright 1988 by
the Robert A. &amp;amp; Virginia Heinlein Library Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had never read this one.  As you might expect, the earliest is
the roughest, and probably the least interesting to current crop
of juveniles.  It's still a fun adventure story, though current
social mores would have made it impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Space Cadet&lt;/cite&gt;, copyright 1948 by Robert A. Heinlein,
copyright renewed 1975 by Robert A. Heinlein, Copyright 1988 by
the Robert A. &amp;amp; Virginia Heinlein Library Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't remember reading this one, but may have.  It's interesting
how much of this is about learning to deal with others, which
moves from dealing with other cadets to, eventually, dealing with
aliens.  Knowledge, brains, and morals win out over brains, money,
and greed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Red Planet&lt;/cite&gt;, copyright 1949 by Robert A. Heinlein,
copyright renewed 1976 by Robert A. Heinlein, Copyright 2003 by
the Robert A. &amp;amp; Virginia Heinlein Library Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm almost positive that I'd read this one, but if so I'd
forgotten how subversive it was.  And I love the skating, for some
reason.  (I don't skate myself.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Farmer in the Sky&lt;/cite&gt;, copyright 1950 by Robert A. Heinlein,
copyright renewed 1977 by Robert A. Heinlein, Copyright 2003 by
the Robert A. &amp;amp; Virginia Heinlein Library Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This situation on earth in this one, sadly, looks more and more
likely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a fair amount of discussion of the actual technology of space
travel and related planetary science in these first four books, and
that's probably what has aged the worst.  The adventures are still
fun, and I think an open-minded juvenile could still enjoy them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/07/new-blog-first-post/"&gt;timewarp&lt;/a&gt; post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</summary>
    <category term="heinlein" label="heinlein"/>
    <category term="recent-reading" label="recent reading"/>
    <category term="science-fiction" label="science fiction"/>
    <category term="timewarp" label="timewarp"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
