<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about hero system)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/hero-system.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 18:49:40 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Playing Classic Traveller in 2020</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/16/playing-classic-traveller-in-2020/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;section id="finally-playing-classic-traveller"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Finally playing Classic Traveller&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine who was in my gaming group back in the 1980s read the
article &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tor.com/2020/01/10/traveller-a-classic-science-fiction-simulator/"&gt;Traveller: A Classic Science Fiction Simulator&lt;/a&gt; at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.tor.com"&gt;Tor.com&lt;/a&gt; and found it interesting.  We discussed it, and he
downloaded &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/80190/CTSTStarter-Traveller"&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/"&gt;Drivethrurpg.com&lt;/a&gt; (it is free)
and started reading it.  I had the PDF already, and I printed it out
and started reading it as well.  I also found a physical copy for sale
on the Internet, so I ordered that as well, and it was much more
convenient to use than my printout in binders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-my-gaming-history"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;My Gaming History&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience with Traveller back in the 1980s was minimal: another
friend had the little black box with the three little black books
(LBBs), and we rolled up characters (which at the time seemed way
more complicated than &lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt;, which we were used to).  Then we tried
to figure out what to do, which was not immediately obvious to us.
&lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; has the obvious core activity of going down in a dungeon and
killing monsters, but Traveller was a lot more wide-open.  My
friend hadn't bought an adventure (which I find very useful for
getting an idea of core activity of a game) and he'd bought the
&lt;cite&gt;Basic Set&lt;/cite&gt;, so there wasn't an adventure in the box.  We didn't
realize that we could use the various checklists and procedures to
improvise an adventure on the spot.  So we didn't get far, alas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I bought several new editions of Traveller over the years
(&lt;cite&gt;Megatraveller&lt;/cite&gt;, &lt;cite&gt;Traveller: The New Era&lt;/cite&gt;, &lt;cite&gt;Traveller 4, Traveller
5&lt;/cite&gt;) but never found the chance to play them.  But my interest in
Classic Traveller grew once I found it being talked about in
Internet forums and blogs.  I bought a copy of the original rules
and many other LBBs, and some of the farfuture.net reprints and
CD-ROMs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, yesterday afternoon I went over to my friend's house with my
&lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; box and some other Classic Traveller materials for
show and tell, and then we rolled up three characters each, 2D6 for
attributes in order.  I had two survive character generation (because
we were using the hardcore “you can die in character generation” rule
that was the default in Classic Traveller), both had been in the Army,
both having miserable strengths (one of them couldn't carry his rifle
&lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; a clip of ammo; don't know how he made it through the Army),
and the weakest only had one term and the other only had two terms,
though he made Lieutenant.  My friend had one character survive
character generation, also from the Army, and he had more terms that
either of my characters, though I don't remember how many, and ended
up a Lt. Colonel if I remember correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we ran a practice combat between my friend's character and my
better character: Submachine Guns at short range (1–5 meters) in a
forest!  Classic Traveller doesn't have initiative, so everything
happens simultaneously, and we both shot the other and each had an
attribute reduced to zero, so we both fell unconscious.  After ten
minutes we both woke up, and decided to &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; try to kill each other
again.  Since he had Medical-1 he used his medical kit and healed us
both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we tried our hand at what some think is &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;‘s core
activity: shipping cargo to another planet (once we finally figured
out that standard shipping of non-speculative cargo is covered in the
“REVENUE” subsection of “STARSHIP ECONOMICS”, and not near “TRADE AND
COMMERCE” section that we mistakenly thought it would be near).  So,
we rolled up some cargoes and High, Middle, and Low passages for our
arbitrarily chosen world.  Then we worked out all the expenses for our
ship, the standard Type-A Free Trader, to see if we could keep up with
them.  And we could, though there seemed to be little slack.  Success!
This lead us back to the “REQUIRED STARSHIP COMPONENTS” subsection of
the “STARSHIPS” section to figure out how much fuel was available for
maneuvering in-system after a jump.  (10 tons out of 30 tons of fuel
was available for the maneuver drive and the power plant, if I
remember correctly.)  We looked at speculative cargoes a bit, but
didn't actually try them.  We weren't sure how you found the selling
price once you were at your destination.  (A second roll on the
“Actual Value” table?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point we looked at experience and character development in
Classic Traveller.  As far as we can tell, that section is missing
from &lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;, though it is in the 1981 LBBs and &lt;cite&gt;The
Traveller Book&lt;/cite&gt;.  (Is it in the 1977 LBBs?  I'll have to
check. &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/16/playing-classic-traveller-in-2020/#megatraveller" id="footnote-reference-1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;1&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) Anyway, basically you do a 4 year
self-improvement program, and if you succeed in staying the program
(Roll your Determination, and you need an 8+ on 2D6), the program
improves a couple of skills temporarily by 1 level of expertise.  You
can then do another 4 year program to make those gains permanent.
(There are similar but slightly different procedures for improving
physical attributes, weapons skills, and education.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we had a lot of fun.  Next time we get together we're going to
design a starship or two and try space combat!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reflections-afterward"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections Afterward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The version of &lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; available at DrivethruRPG.com seems
to be a better scan than the one off the Classic Traveller CD-Rom at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.farfuture.net/"&gt;farfuture.net&lt;/a&gt;, and is arranged in three separate PDF files, one for
each of the three books in the set, which is much more convenient for
printing and for viewing more than one at once on a screen.  Alas,
neither of them had select-able text, each page being a scanned image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had brought my copy of the 1977 edition of Classic Traveller, 3
digest sized (5½×8½ inches) booklets in the classic box, along with
some of the other books/supplements/adventures in that format, the
Quick Link Interactive reprint of the 1981 LBBs in one volume, and the
hardcover edition of &lt;cite&gt;The Traveller Book&lt;/cite&gt;.  I find the pamphlet format
of the original Classic Traveller books charming: they're an easy size
for reading away from the table, they seem to have lasted pretty well
over the years, and it is relatively easy to refer to two of them at
once.  On the other hand, &lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;'s division into a book
of the &lt;cite&gt;Core Rules&lt;/cite&gt;, another book of &lt;cite&gt;Charts and Tables&lt;/cite&gt;, and a final
book with adventures, is very handy at the table where you have room
enough to have both &lt;cite&gt;Core Rules&lt;/cite&gt; open and &lt;cite&gt;Charts and Tables&lt;/cite&gt; open to
the the specific pages for the tables matching what you're reading in
&lt;cite&gt;Core Rules&lt;/cite&gt;.  Also &lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; has a “TYPICAL ACTIVITIES”
checklist on p. 9 of &lt;cite&gt;Charts and Tables&lt;/cite&gt; (that I can't find in the
3LBBs) that basically outlines how you could improvise a Free
Trader-based adventure at the table.  The hardback &lt;cite&gt;The Traveller
Book&lt;/cite&gt; is sturdy and easy to use at the table, but not as convenient as
&lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;‘s split into &lt;cite&gt;Core Rules&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;Charts and
Tables&lt;/cite&gt;.  The &lt;cite&gt;Core Rules&lt;/cite&gt; booklet had helpful page references to
&lt;cite&gt;Charts and Tables&lt;/cite&gt; for each of the major sections, and these were
usually a 2-page spread with all (or nearly all) of the tables for the
subject being discussed.  Despite the charming nature of the LBBs, I
think having the separate &lt;cite&gt;Charts and Tables&lt;/cite&gt; book from &lt;cite&gt;Starter
Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; is so convenient that we'll continue using it at the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found it useful to have multiple versions of Traveller available
while reading &lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; to cross-check things: I found an
erratum in &lt;cite&gt;Starter Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="footnote-list brackets"&gt;
&lt;aside class="footnote brackets" id="megatraveller" role="doc-footnote"&gt;
&lt;span class="label"&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a role="doc-backlink" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/16/playing-classic-traveller-in-2020/#footnote-reference-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remembered that &lt;cite&gt;Megatraveller&lt;/cite&gt; had a different
method for character advancement/experience, so I looked that up
when I got home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can learn a new skill by experience, observing and trying that
skill and gaining 1 Adventure Tally (AT) per session if the referee
it played a significant part in the session.  Once you've acquired
enough ATs, you need to roll a 15 or more on 2D6 with a Dice
Modifier (DM) from Intelligence (if it is high enough) and the
number of ATs you've accumulated.  Use the same procedure to
improve a skill.  There is a similar procedure for improving
characteristics.  (This is similar to getting skill “Ticks” in
RuneQuest or other &lt;cite&gt;Basic Roleplaying&lt;/cite&gt;-based systems.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could also learn a skill by formal training. &lt;strong&gt;(1)&lt;/strong&gt; You have
to roll 7+ on 2D6 (having an applicable skill gives you a DM; the
skill depends on what kind of training you're seeking) to find the
training.  &lt;strong&gt;(2)&lt;/strong&gt; You have to roll 7+ on 2D6 (with a DM from your
Determination characteristic) to stay determined to complete the
training.  Finally, &lt;strong&gt;(3)&lt;/strong&gt; You have to roll to see if you were
successful by rolling 11+ on 2D6 (with DMs from the skill you are
training if you already have it, or other related skills you
already know, and your instructors Instruction skill).  The
training takes on average 200 hours, and costs approximately Cr10
per hour.  There is a similar procedure for improving
characteristics, except for Social Standing, which can only be
improved by actually acquiring money and spending it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amusingly &lt;cite&gt;Megatraveller&lt;/cite&gt;, in contrast to Classic Traveller's
relative lack of character improvement, points out that increasing
skills and characteristics by accumulating ATs encourages
characters' participation, keeps them interested in the game, and
makes them aware of the benefits they can achieve in a session.
I'll note that this is just like leveling in &lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; or getting
experience points in skill based games like &lt;cite&gt;Hero System&lt;/cite&gt; or
&lt;cite&gt;GURPS&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, my quick look through the &lt;cite&gt;Megatraveller&lt;/cite&gt; &lt;cite&gt;Players'
Manual&lt;/cite&gt; gave me the impression that &lt;cite&gt;Megatraveller&lt;/cite&gt; is just much
more complicated that Classic Traveller in every way, a typical
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second-system_effect"&gt;second-system effect&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>classic traveller</category><category>d&amp;d</category><category>gurps</category><category>hero system</category><category>my gaming history</category><category>rpg</category><category>starter traveller</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/03/16/playing-classic-traveller-in-2020/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 14:11:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Slings in RPGs: Often Nerfed</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/07/slings-in-rpgs-often-nerfed/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;In response to reading &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-4541318/Roman-sling-bullets-deadly-44-Magnum.html?fbclid=IwAR2IZhVYW4-4_BcuQDOq2yGXwwurzBd3HNSo1BzN7XUwZLKHF4XZ54yy0VU"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; article, headlined “Roman sling bullets
used against Scottish tribes 2,000 years ago were as deadly as a .44
Magnum”, I was thinking about slings in RPGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've often thought that sling bullets are woefully nerfed in many
RPGs, especially D&amp;amp;D.  In D&amp;amp;D 5E, for instance, they're only 1d4,
while a short bow is 1d6 and a long bow is 1d8. For comparison,
daggers are 1d4 and longswords are 1d8.  In OD&amp;amp;D using Greyhawk's
“Damage Done by Weapon Type” table sling &lt;em&gt;stones&lt;/em&gt; are 1d4, and the
same in B/X D&amp;amp;D's optional “Variable Weapon Damage” table.  However,
in 3-book OD&amp;amp;D and B/X D&amp;amp;D without the “Variable Weapon Damage” table
all weapons did 1d6 damage, so slings weren't nerfed there.  AD&amp;amp;D 1E
has sling &lt;em&gt;bullets&lt;/em&gt; as 1d4+1 vs. Size Small or Medium and 1d6+1
vs. Size Large.  Sling &lt;em&gt;stones&lt;/em&gt; are 1d4 vs. Size Small, Medium or
Large.  Compare that to arrows at 1d6 vs. Size Small, Medium, or
Large.  But all bows fire twice per round, so they can be doing up to
2d6 per round.  Interestingly, heavy quarrels are 1d4+1 vs. Size Small
or Medium, and 1d6+1 vs. Size Large with the heavy crossbow firing
once in two rounds, while light quarrels are 1d4 vs. all three sizes
and fire every round.  So, nerfed once you take into rates of fire.
D&amp;amp;D 3.5E has sling bullets as 1d4, while longbows are 1d8 and heavy
repeating crossbows are 1d10 and light repeating crossbows are 1d8.
Definitely nerfed.  In D&amp;amp;D 4E slings are 1d6, while longbows are 1d10,
shortbows are 1d8, and a crossbow is 1d8.  There is even more
variability among editions of D&amp;amp;D than I remembered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savage_Worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt; slings are Str+d4, while a bow is 2d6.  For
comparison, a dagger is Str+d4 and a long sword is Str+d8.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RuneQuest"&gt;RuneQuest&lt;/a&gt; 2E they are 1d8, similar to a Composite bow at 1d8+1
and broadsword at 1d8.  In Elric! (a member of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stormbringer_(role-playing_game)"&gt;Stormbringer&lt;/a&gt; line
of games, appearing between 4th Edition and 5th Edition, but the rules
were substantially equivalent to Stormbringer 5E; It is relative of
RuneQuest mechanically, part of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Role-Playing"&gt;Basic Roleplaying (BRP)&lt;/a&gt; family
of games) a sling is 1d8+1, similar to a Desert Recurve Bow at 1d8+2,
and a broadsword at 1d8+1.  So in the BRP games they are not nerfed.
In DragonQuest their Damage Modifier is +1, while a dagger is +0, a
long bow is +4 and a broadsword is +4.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talislanta"&gt;Talislanta&lt;/a&gt; 4E a sling's Damage Rating is 4, as is a dagger, while a
long bow and broadsword are 8.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hero_System"&gt;Hero&lt;/a&gt; 5E, sling damage is 1d6+1, same as a medium bow or a light
long bow, while a medium long bow is 1½ d6 (that's 1 and ½ d6)
and a heavy long bow is 2d6.  A dagger is 1d6-1 and a broadsword is
1d6+1.  Note that strong enough characters add damage to this based on
how strong they are. Not nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GURPS#Prior_RPG_history"&gt;GURPS&lt;/a&gt; 4E, damage is based on your strength, and the only dice used is
d6.  We'll use an average Strength 10 character as an example.  Their
Thrust damage is 1d-2 and their Swing damage is 1d. An opponent's
Damage Resistance (DR) is subtracted from the rolled damage and any
damage left is multiplied by a modifier for each type of damage.
Piercing damage has a ×1 modifier, cutting has a ×1.5 modifier, and
impaling has a ×2 modifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, sling damage is swing piercing, and the damage for that for our
average character is 1d.  A longbow is thrust+2 impaling. and the
damage for that is 1d, and whatever makes it past DR is doubled.  A
regular bow is thrust+1 impaling, and the damage for that is 1d+1
(minus DR) ×2.  A dagger is thrust-1 impaling, so that is 1d-3 (minus
DR) ×2.  A thrusting broadsword is swing+1 cutting (1d+1 (minus DR)
×1.5) or thrust+2 impaling (1d+2 (minus DR) ×2).  I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; that's
nerfed a little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I'd like to note that when actually playing GURPS I think this is
simpler to do at the table than it sounds like. The damage values for
each attack is figured out at character creation :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fantasy_Trip"&gt;The Fantasy Trip&lt;/a&gt;, which like GURPS only uses d6, slings do
1d-2, small bows do 1d-1, longbows do 1d+2, daggers do 1d-1, and
broadswords do 2d.  A little bit nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Eyes,_Small_Mouth"&gt;Big Eyes Small Mouth (BESM)&lt;/a&gt; 2nd Edition Revised, slings are not
listed, but a long bow does 5 damage, a longsword does 10 damage, and
a dagger does 5 damage.  In BESM 3rd Edition, an average person has an
Attack Combat Value (ACV) of 4 and a Damage Multiplier of 5.  Each weapon has
a Level, which is multiplied by the Damage Multiplier and added to the
ACV for the final damage.  Slings are Level 1 (1 × 5 + 4 = 9), as are
daggers.  Longbows are Level 3 (3 × 5 + 1 = 16), as are longswords.
Definitely nerfed.  (It is the same in &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H%C3%A2rnMaster"&gt;HarnMaster&lt;/a&gt;, weapon impact (damage) for Melee weapons has three
Aspects, Blunt (B), Edge (E), and Point (P).  A dagger's impact is B
1, E 2, P 5, while a broadsword is B 3, E 5, and P 3.  A Missile
weapon's impact depends on the type of missile weapon and the range:
short, medium, long, and extreme.  Slings are Short 4, Medium 3, Long
2, and Extreme 2.  Shortbows are Short 6, Medium 5, Long 4, Extreme 3.
Longbows are Short 8, Medium 8, Long 6, Extreme 5.  Nerfed.  I'll note
that these weapon or missile impacts are added to a Strike Impact is
decided by a table indexed by how well the attacker did on opposed
rolls of attack skill against the defender's skill in Block,
Counterstrike, Dodge, or if the defender ignored the attack. For Melee
attacks this can result in the defender having blocked the attack,
either the attacker or the defender fumbling or stumbling, the
defender gaining a Tactical Advantage (a free action), or either or
both having made a Strike, which generates from 1 to 4 d6s.  For
Missle attacks this can result in a Miss (with a chance to hit an
adjacent combatant, a Wild (a fumble roll), a Block, or a Strike,
which generates from 1 to 3 d6s.  The Armor Protection value is
subtracked and the result is the total Effective Impact, which is then
referenced on the Injury Table to determine where the on the body the
injury is and how serious it is.  There are no Hit Points like D&amp;amp;D or
Wounds like Savage Worlds.  Instead the character accumulates injuries
like “1 Minor Slash Left Upper Arm, 1 injury level”.  The total injury
level determines the difficulty of the character staying conscious and
penalty to any skill roll.  Some of the injuries may immediately kill
the injured character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a good thread by Robert S. Conley (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://batintheattic.blogspot.com/"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.batintheattic.com/index.php"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rpggeek.com/rpgdesigner/22847/robert-conley"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;) on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.rpgpub.com/threads/the-one-where-i-sing-the-praises-of-harnmaster.2363/"&gt;RPG PUB&lt;/a&gt;
that talks some more about HarnMaster combat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In West End Games' &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D6_Fantasy"&gt;D6 Fantasy&lt;/a&gt;, attributes are measured in d6s and 2D
is an average human.  Bow and sling damage and melee damage as d6s
added to a number of d6s determined by your Strength Damage, which is
determined by your Physique attribute or Lifting skill (both measured
in d6s), drop any adds, divided by 2.  So our average human's Strength
Damage is 2D.  Then longbows add +2D+2, shortbows add +1D+2, and
slings add +1D.  For comparison, daggers add +1D and broad/long swords
ad +2D+2.  So, nerfed, although it is hard to make precise
distinctions at this level of resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tunnels_%26_Trolls"&gt;Tunnels &amp;amp; Trolls&lt;/a&gt; only uses d6s and weapons are measured in “Dice +
Adds”, that is the number of d6s to roll and the number of points to
add to the dice total.  The common sling is 2d.  A very light self bow
is 2d, a light self bow is 3d, a medium self bow is 4d, a heavy self
bow is 5d, and a extra-heavy self bow is 6d.  These all have
increasing Strength Required to use the weapon.  For comparison, a
Dirk is 2D+1 and a broadsword is 3d+4.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dragon_Warriors"&gt;Dragon Warriors&lt;/a&gt; weapon damage has two parts: an armor
penetration die (measured in dice: d4, d6, d8, etc.) and damage
points.  The armor penetration die is rolled against the Armour Factor
of the defender's armour: a Gambeson has an Armour Factor of 2 while
Plate has an Armor Factor of 5, and the attacker has to roll &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt;
than the Armour Factor to inflict damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sling has Damage (d6, 3 points) while a Bow has Damage (d6, 4
points).  For comparison, a dagger has Damage (d4, 3 points) and a
sword has Damage (d8, 4 points).  Slightly nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I GM games that I think nerf slings, like D&amp;amp;D, I often use a
house rule that sling bullets are higher damage than sling stones, and
more similar to the damage of a short bow, 1d6, for example.  I may
have been underestimating them and should consider them closer to a
long bow, 1d8, as Chaosium's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Role-Playing"&gt;Basic Roleplaying (BRP)&lt;/a&gt; variants
(RuneQuest, Elric, Stormbringer) do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="addendum-classic-traveller-cepheus-engine"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2020-03-14 Addendum — Classic Traveller &amp;amp; Cepheus Engine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wiki.travellerrpg.com/Classic_Traveller"&gt;Classic Traveller&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;cite&gt;Supplement 04 Citizens of the
Imperium&lt;/cite&gt; (1979) has a section on bow weapons, on p. 16!  A sling does
2D wounds and a long bow does 2D wounds also.  For comparison, from
&lt;cite&gt;Book 01 Characters &amp;amp; Combat&lt;/cite&gt; (1981) on p. 47 on the “Range Table” (?)
dagger, blade, cutlass, and sword all do 2D wounds.  Not nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Cepheus Engine&lt;/cite&gt; (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/237247/Cepheus-Engine-RPG"&gt;C1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.paulelliottbooks.com/what-is-cepheus-engine.html"&gt;C2&lt;/a&gt;) doesn't have slings, but a bow is 2D6.
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/304840/The-Sword-of-Cepheus"&gt;Sword of Cepheus&lt;/a&gt;, the fantasy variant, has sling as 2D, short bow
as 2D, long bow as 3D, dagger as 2D, and sword as 3D.  Maybe a little
nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="addendum-advanced-fighting-fantasy-1e-2e"&gt;
&lt;span id="aff"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;h2&gt;2021-07-19 Addendum — Advanced Fighting Fantasy 1E &amp;amp; 2E&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AFF 1E (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fightingfantasy.fandom.com/wiki/Dungeoneer_(book)"&gt;Dungeoneer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fightingfantasy.fandom.com/wiki/Blacksand_(AFF)"&gt;Blacksand&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fightingfantasy.fandom.com/wiki/Allansia_(book)"&gt;Allansia&lt;/a&gt;) does not, as far as I can tell,
mention slings at all.  Boo, hiss!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/667/Arion-Games/subcategory/1684_25223/Advanced-Fighting-Fantasy"&gt;AFF 2E&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; have slings.  Yay!  In AFF you roll a d6 (the Damage
roll) and look up the result on a table for your weapon.  You can have
bonuses to the d6 Damage roll that can give a result of 7 or above.
Here is the entry for sling, along with longbow, shortbow and sword
for comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weapon&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7+&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sling&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arrow - Longbow&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arrow - Shortbow&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sword&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, slings are a little nerfed.  I think I'll use a house rule that
says the sling damage in the book is for sling stones, and sling
bullets do the same damage as an arrow fired from a shortbow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last edited: 2021-08-09 12:15:25 EDT&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Local Variables:
time-stamp-format: "%Y-%02m-%02d %02H:%02M:%02S %Z"
time-stamp-start: "\\*Last edited:[ \t]+\\\\?"
time-stamp-end: "\\*\\\\?\n"
time-stamp-line-limit: -20
End: --&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>ad&amp;d 1e</category><category>advanced fighting fantasy</category><category>aff 1e</category><category>aff 2e</category><category>b/x d&amp;d</category><category>basic roleplaying</category><category>besm</category><category>big eyes small mouth</category><category>brp</category><category>cepheus engine</category><category>classic traveller</category><category>d6 fantasy</category><category>d&amp;d</category><category>d&amp;d 3.5e</category><category>d&amp;d 4e</category><category>dragon warriors</category><category>dragonquest</category><category>elric!</category><category>gurps</category><category>harnmaster</category><category>hero system</category><category>nerfed</category><category>od&amp;d</category><category>opend6</category><category>rpg</category><category>runequest</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>slings</category><category>stormbringer</category><category>sword of cepheus</category><category>t&amp;t</category><category>talislanta</category><category>tft</category><category>the fantasy trip</category><category>traveller</category><category>tunnels &amp; trolls</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/07/slings-in-rpgs-often-nerfed/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 19:40:23 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>