<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about ken hite)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/ken-hite.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 20:55:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Why D&amp;D is so successful?</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/08/19/why-dd-is-so-successful/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I once quoted Ken Hite's description of D&amp;amp;D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original D&amp;amp;D seems, quite obviously, to be a pastiche of Fritz
Leiber and Robert E. Howard adventure stories, set in a Tolkeinian
world of Moorcockian morality, using Jack Vance's magic system,
redacted for multiple protagonists. No wonder things are confused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to a friend, and they were a little offended, considering it a
criticism of D&amp;amp;D.  I guess it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a criticism, but I think it is a
valid description of D&amp;amp;D.  However, I advance the theory that this
“confused” nature of D&amp;amp;D is what makes it successful, because it
provides so many different (and sometimes conflicting) elements that
you can come up with about anything in D&amp;amp;D, and it will be fun.  Each
gaming group selects those things from D&amp;amp;D that they find interesting,
customizing their play to their taste.  This is something that is
sometimes much harder in more focused games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>d&amp;d</category><category>ken hite</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/08/19/why-dd-is-so-successful/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 14:43:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ken Hite at Origins on Steampunk via Lewis Pulsipher</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/06/13/ken-hite-at-origins-on-steampunk/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pulsiphergamedesign.blogspot.com/"&gt;Lewis Pulsipher&lt;/a&gt; said in his post &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pulsiphergamedesign.blogspot.com/2012/06/origins-2012-diminished.html"&gt;Origins 2012 — “Diminished”&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I asked if Hite was familiar enough with Steampunk to say what the
story is in that (to me) obscure genre.  He pointed out that it’s
now more an aesthetic than a genre, the goggles and leather and
glass and so forth (and corsets for women?).  Yet he then made an
erudite comparison, saying that just as fairy stories helped
Victorians reconcile with what was a pretty ugly past (and where
the real fairy stories were “don’t go out on the moor at night or
they’ll eat you”), steampunk helps people reconcile with
technology.  Modern technology is a “black box” to most people,
but most people can understand that hot steam expands and can move
things, and feel comfortable with the steam engines and
“clockwork” of Steampunk.  Steampunk helps people come to terms
with technology.  A remarkable answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ken hite</category><category>origins</category><category>steampunk</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/06/13/ken-hite-at-origins-on-steampunk/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 Jun 2012 17:55:46 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>