<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about lily)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/lily.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 19:01:12 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Playing an RPG with Lily</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/09/21/2003-09-21/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Lily (my daughter; she'll be five next month) was in my office today
and asked about a miniature &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/09/21/2003-09-21/#footnote-1" id="footnote-reference-1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;1&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that was in a little box on one of my
bookshelves.  I told her it was used for playing a game, and showed her
some more of them.  She was fascinated, and wanted to know if we could
play the game.  I said ok, and got out my battlemat.  Without thinking
too much about it, and influenced by the miniatures (typical &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt;
miniatures) I drew out the entrance to a cave in the side of a cliff,
and we played out exploring a typical mindless dungeon with several of
the miniatures and drawing the dungeon on the battle mat.  Lily really
got into it, having her PCs go back to their house for supplies once
and exploring and scaring away monsters and looking for treasure.  She
also really liked rolling dice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospective, she'd probably have had more fun if I'd run a
&lt;cite&gt;Bunnies &amp;amp; Burrows&lt;/cite&gt; game; I don't have any &lt;cite&gt;B&amp;amp;B&lt;/cite&gt; miniatures,
though.  She's seen me play &lt;cite&gt;B&amp;amp;B&lt;/cite&gt; (using the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.fudgerpg.com/"&gt;Fudge&lt;/a&gt; rules) with her cousins a couple of
times, and has been a little bit interested, but given her greater
interest in the miniatures this time I think she might really enjoy a
&lt;cite&gt;B&amp;amp;B&lt;/cite&gt; game now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watching Lily have fun moving the miniatures around and rolling dice
reminds me of how much shear &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt; this was when I first starting
gaming (playing &lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt;).  Part of the fascination was indeed just
the miniatures and dice, and that's something that I've not really
thought about in a long time.  I've maintained in the past that part of
the fun of games like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.chaosium.com/catalog/product_info.php?cPath=39&amp;amp;products_id=62"&gt;Stormbringer&lt;/a&gt; is actually rolling all
those funny shaped dice, and certainly there is something neat about a
well-painted minature figure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="footnote-list brackets"&gt;
&lt;aside class="footnote brackets" id="footnote-1" role="note"&gt;
&lt;span class="label"&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a role="doc-backlink" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/09/21/2003-09-21/#footnote-reference-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not much of a miniatures person myself (I don't play any
miniature games, for instance), and these miniatures were actually my
brother Alan's from many years ago when we actually played &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt;, and
some of them are actually official &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; miniatures.  I like being able
to look at a fight scene on a battle map and see where the characters
their opponents, however, and often use dice or 0.75 inch numbered
wooden cube to represent characters during complicated fight scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;</description><category>kids</category><category>lily</category><category>old blog</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/09/21/2003-09-21/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Sep 2003 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>