<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about lord of the rings adventure game)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/lord-of-the-rings-adventure-game.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2022 16:26:35 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Lord of the Rings Adventure Game from Iron Crown Enterprises</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2022/12/10/the-lord-of-the-rings-adventure-game-from-iron-crown-enterprises/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Last edited: 2022-12-14 11:19:06 EST&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got an interesting game yesterday, and finished reading it today:
the 1991 &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings Adventure Game&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iron_Crown_Enterprises"&gt;Iron Crown
Enterprises&lt;/a&gt;, which was the first holder of the Tolkien franchise
for RPGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICE got its start with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rolemaster"&gt;Rolemaster&lt;/a&gt;, which started as a detailed
add-on combat system for D&amp;amp;D and developed into a very detailed RPG of
its own, based on open-ended d100 rolls: high is good and on very
high or low rolls you roll again and add the new roll for high or
subtracted for low, continuing infinitely in either direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ICE then got the Tolkien franchise and developed &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Middle-earth_Role_Playing"&gt;Middle-Earth Role
Playing&lt;/a&gt; (MERP) as a slightly simplified RPG for those who wanted to
play in Middle Earth, but did not want all the complexities of the
full Rolemaster system.  The adventures were written in such a way that
you could play them either with Rolemaster or MERP, and had some short
guidelines to help the GM adapt them for other games.  They had a lot
of success and their Middle Earth products were extensive and highly
regarded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of folk used them with other RPG systems.  (I bought several for
the ideas.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in their run, ICE wanted to tap the larger Tolkien readership and
so wrote the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_the_Rings_Adventure_Game"&gt;Lord of the Ring Adventure Game&lt;/a&gt; as a much simpler
game that they hoped would draw interested readers and the viewers of
the animated Hobbit and Lord of the Rings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I have fond memories of the animated Hobbit, though I knew it only
through reading the graphic novel adaptation that used art from the
movie when I was at my uncle and aunt's place in New York one summer.
I finally saw it, probably on TV some years later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the Lord of the Rings Adventure Game (LOR hereafter, as seems
to be customary) comes in a box with a 32 page rulebook, a 64 page
adventure with 6 pre-generated characters, a 32 pamphlet of 4 pages of
backstory for the 6 pregens and area maps for the adventure, several
poster sized maps, including a nice color one of Middle Earth, and
(missing in my copy, as the seller had noted in the description) 2
six-sided dice and a sheet of standup cardboard figures of people and
creatures and the pregens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characters have 12 stats: 6 capabilities (Strength, Agility,
Intelligence, Movement, and Endurance) and 6 skills (Defense, Melee
Offensive Bonus, Ranged Offensive Bonus, General, Subterfuge,
Perception, and Magical).  The value of each of these is called a
bonus, and can be less than zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You pick one of 9 character types (Hobbit Scout, Elf Scout, Human
Warrior, Dwarf Warrior, Elf Warrior, Human Ranger, Half-elf Ranger,
Human Bard, and Elf Bard), which sets your equipment and capability
values and starting skill values, and then you have six +1 bonuses to
add to your skills as you choose, no more than +3 to any one skill.
If you have +1 or more in magic you get two spells per +1 bonus.  Some
of your equipment gives bonuses to your stats.  You roll 2d6 plus a
stat bonus versus a target number or an opponent’s roll.  Meet or
exceed an unopposed roll to succeed, while you can tie on opposed
rolls.  In combat take the attacker’s Offensive Bonus minus the
defenders Defensive Bonus and roll 2d6 and look the result up in a
chart to see how much damage is done and whether the defender is
knocked unconscious or killed outright.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your character type sets your Endurance (basically your hit points),
with the dwarf warrior having the most at 60 points and the elf bard
the least at 30 points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 15 spells, all very in keeping with the magic seen in the
novels, which is to say not tremendously powerful (Strength, Shield,
Speed, Balance, Camouflage, Concentration, Item Analysis,
Clairvoyance, Healing, Luck, Protection from Magic, Sustenance, Calm,
Charm Animal, and Fire Bolt).  Magic items typically add a plus to a
stat, or let you do something you couldn’t before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maneuvers are how you use your stats.  Some, like climbing a tree have
a set difficulty.  Others the GM sets the difficulty, from Routine (4)
to Absurd (18).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Activities are things that are normally automatically successful if
you have the equipment and time (tying up a captive, setting up camp,
digging a ditch), but turn into GM moderated maneuvers if you don’t
have the time or equipment (digging a ditch to hide in before the
opponents you want to ambush show up).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 14 action sequences.  These things like combat (one of the
action sequences) where there is a general sequence you follow to do
something, from sneaking through a town at night to tracking through a
wilderness or ambushing an enemy.  I like how these are written up as
a standard sequence of things to do and consider, just like how combat
is done in most system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These action sequences can be adjusted by the GM for circumstances and
they encourage you to make up your own.  You might make one up for
when someone is wanting to convince a crowd of something.  They are
multi-step procedures for doing something.  I think they would be
quite useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get Experience Points (EP) for successful maneuvers depending on
how hard the target number was, for every point of damage inflicted,
with unconsciousness and killed results worth more, and for every
point of damage the caster of a spell takes to cast the spell.  (Every
spell costs the caster Damage to cast!). You also get EP for good
ideas and for the group accomplishing significant goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The included adventure is a mix of programmed sequences to help the
new GM and players learn the system, where the choices the players
make determines what section you turn to next, and the sections are
broken up into action sequences and the results determine which
section the players go to next, GM notes on how to run or adjust
things, and descriptions of what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do notice that each of the pregens has a special ability: finding
lost items or people, eidetic memory, knowing if any creature within a
20 foot radius is aligned with forces of darkness, healing wounds
faster, being unusually skilled at bargaining and negotiation, and
always knowing which way is north and can follow known routes
perfectly.  But there is no rule for assigning these to characters.  I
imagine that if the GM wanted to have special abilities for other
characters the GM and the players should come up with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules encourage you to use figures or counters to represent
characters in combat, and movement is given in inches, to be measured
on the map, if you draw one, or on the table if you just set out the
figures at the right distances.  You could easily use a battle map
with a grid, if you have one.  Movement at a walk is 50 feet plus 10
feet multiplied by the characters Movement bonus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I like it.  I hope to run it this year for Christmas, if all
goes well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a Wikipedia &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lord_of_the_Rings_Adventure_Game"&gt;page&lt;/a&gt; about it, but it is even
briefer than this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a compatible game, The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://sites.google.com/site/ambarquenta/home/the-offical-games/meag"&gt;Middle-Earth Adventure Game&lt;/a&gt;
(MEAG), that was designed by Brian Gross and J.R. Gracen.  I knew of
it before I got the LotRAG, it seems to be a generalization and
expansion, and thus a little more complicated, but it doesn't look
&lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; complicated.  I'll read it and report what I think of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Local Variables:
time-stamp-format: "%Y-%02m-%02d %02H:%02M:%02S %Z"
time-stamp-start: "\\*Last edited:[ \t]+\\\\?"
time-stamp-end: "\\*\\\\?\n"
End: --&gt;</description><category>ice</category><category>iron crown enterprises</category><category>lor</category><category>lord of the rings adventure game</category><category>lotrag</category><category>merp</category><category>rolemaster</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2022/12/10/the-lord-of-the-rings-adventure-game-from-iron-crown-enterprises/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2022 23:30:01 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>