<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about melee)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/melee.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 04:21:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Fantasy Trip</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;[I should have posted this a long time ago.  Oh well.  At least it's
being posted now.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="back-in-the-day"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Back in the Day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really wish I'd gotten a copy of Steve Jackson's Melee in 1977 and
Wizard in 1978 when they were published by Metagaming, and Advanced
Melee, Advanced Wizard, and In the Labyrinth when those came out in
1980. Together those make up the game The Fantasy Trip (TFT). Melee and
Wizard are the basic combat and magic rules, published as board games.
Advanced Melee and Advanced Wizard are the full combat rules. And In the
Labyrinth adds all the other stuff necessary for a complete roleplaying
game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metagaming_Concepts"&gt;Metagaming at
Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Melee_board_game_1977.png"&gt;Melee, 1977&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Wizard_Metagaming_1978.png"&gt;Wizard, 1978&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I never saw them in any store in my area. I did meet one person who
played The Fantasy Trip, probably in 1981 or so, but never got to talk
to him about it; we were both quite busy with other things at the summer
camp from hell. Wish he'd brought his rulebooks…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melee_(game)"&gt;Melee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wizard_(board_game)"&gt;Wizard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fantasy_Trip"&gt;The Fantasy Trip at
Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="modern-times"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Modern Times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I picked up my copies of the original Advanced Melee, Advanced Wizard,
and In the Labyrinth much more recently. Probably in 2018 or so. Thank
goodness for Internet game stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Advanced_Melee_1980.jpg"&gt;Advanced Melee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Advanced_Wizard_1980.jpg"&gt;Advanced Wizard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_In_the_Labyrinth_1980.jpg"&gt;In the Labyrinth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="legacy-edition"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Legacy Edition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018 Steve Jackson Games kickstarted The Fantasy Trip Legacy Edition,
with new versions of Melee and Wizard and a new version of In the
Labyrinth that contained everything from the original as well as the
rules from Advanced Melee and Advanced Wizard, and I backed it, and got
a LOT of stuff. I liked the new edition of The Fantasy Trip a lot. But I
didn't have a good chance to play it for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were some interesting changes from the Metagaming version of The
Fantasy Trip to the Legacy edition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Melee_Legacy_Edition.jpg"&gt;Melee, Legacy Edition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Wizard_Legacy_Edition.jpg"&gt;Wizard, Legacy Edition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_In_the_Labyrinth_Legacy_Edition.jpg"&gt;In the Labyrinth, Legacy
Edition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/Cover_of_Pocket_Box_Melee_and_Wizard.png"&gt;Pocket Box edition of Melee &amp;amp;
Wizard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sjgames.com/"&gt;Steve Jackson Games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fantasy_Trip#The_Fantasy_Trip_Legacy_Edition_2"&gt;The Fantasy Trip Legacy
Edition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://thefantasytrip.game/"&gt;The Fantasy Trip at Steve Jackson
Games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.hcobb.com/tft/legacy_first.html"&gt;The Fantasy Trip, Legacy vs First edition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the PDF of Melee is available from Steve Jackson Games for free!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://warehouse23.com/products/the-fantasy-trip-melee"&gt;Melee for
Free!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="playing-melee-online"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Playing Melee Online&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got to play Melee online in 2023 and had fun. It took a while for
everybody to get used to the way combat works — it's a hex-based
tactical combat system that strives for verisimilitude, and is quite
different from anything that the others were used to. This group has
been playing Mini Six from Antipaladin Games mostly before this, with some
of Deep7's 1PGs thrown in; previously we've played a lot of Labyrinth
Lord from Goblinoid Games and Savage Worlds from Pinnacle Entertainment
Group, and while Savage Worlds is played on a square grid battle map,
it's still not tactical in the same way as TFT, DragonQuest from SPI, or
GURPS from Steve Jackson Games. I played a lot of DragonQuest and GURPS
(TFT's younger relative) in the 80s and 90s, which both have hex-grid
based tactical combat, and enjoyed them a lot, so TFT's system wasn't
such a shock to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/144558/Mini-Six-Bare-Bones-Edition"&gt;Mini
Six&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.antipaladingames.com/"&gt;AntiPaladin Games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/tkurtbond/Minimal-OpenD6"&gt;Minimal OpenD6 SRD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://deep7.com/"&gt;Deep7 Press&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://deep7.com/?page_id=664"&gt;1PG - 1 Page Games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/78524/Advanced-Edition-Companion-Labyrinth-Lord-noart-version"&gt;Labyrinth Lord (free no-art
version)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/64331/Labyrinth-Lord-Revised-Edition-noart-version"&gt;Advanced Edition Companion for Labyrinth Lord (free no-art
version)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/259983/Advanced-Labyrinth-Lord-Dragon-Cover"&gt;Advanced Labyrinth
Lord&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.goblinoidgames.com/"&gt;Goblinoid Games&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://peginc.com/"&gt;Pinnacle Entertainment Group&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savage_Worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds at
Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DragonQuest"&gt;DragonQuest at
Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sjgames.com/gurps/"&gt;GURPS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I backed Steve Jackson Games' TFT kickstarters as well as Gaming
Ballistic's kickstarters, so I've got a lot of the stuff published for
The Fantasy Trip Legacy Edition. It's a pity I'm not playing face to
face these days, because most of those kickstarters were loaded with
neat stuff for face to face play — megahex tiles, cards of all kinds,
neoprene battle maps, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gamingballistic.com/"&gt;Gaming Ballistic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gaming-ballistic.myshopify.com/collections/all?filter.v.price.gte=&amp;amp;filter.v.price.lte=&amp;amp;filter.p.m.my_fields.collection=The+Fantasy+Trip"&gt;Gaming Ballistic's TFT
products&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continued playing Melee online, and added in Wizard.  Eventually I
plan to start running a TFT campaign using the many adventures
released by Steve Jackson Games and Gaming Ballistic. And they've
released a number of solo adventures, so I plan on playing those as
well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now I'm working on a hexcrawl using TFT, to be played somewhat
in the West Marches style, with a long past apocalypse that destroyed
a huge empire.  The idea is the people are moving back into the areas
left abandoned for centuries after the apocalypse due to inimical
magic that has recently retreated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="description-of-melee"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description of Melee&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Melee is a person-to-person combat board game. A Melee character has two
stats, Strength (ST) and Dexterity (DX), and a secondary stat, Movement
Allowance (MA). ST determines what weapons you can use. DX determines
how hard it is for you to hit your opponents: you roll 3d6 equal to or
under your (adjusted) DX to hit (noted as a 3/DX roll). MA determines
how fast you can move on the hex grid battlemap. Human characters start
with 8 in ST and DX and have 8 more points to allocate however you want
between the two, for a total of 24 points. There are NO dump stats, and
every combination of stats, weapons, and armor results in quite
differently performing characters, which interact with the combat system
in interesting ways. Unarmored humans start with MA 10, but most armor
reduces a characters MA. Armor also lowers your DX. When you are
familiar with the system you and one or more friends can create
characters and fight a battle in an hour or so, but when you are first
starting out it will take a while to internalize the system so it runs
quickly. Melee also has various nonhuman opponents: bears, wolves, giant
snakes, giants, and gargoyles. It also has fantasy fighters: elves,
dwarves, halflings, orcs, goblins, and hobgoblins, who start with
different minimum ST and DX, sometimes with different maximum total
points. Characters gain experience and when they have 100 they can trade
it in for a point to increase ST or DX. Up to 8 points can be gained
this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="description-of-wizard"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description of Wizard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wizard adds a third stat, Intelligence (IQ), and a lot of
spells. You've still only got 8 points to spend between the three
stats, so characters can have 32 points total.  Wizards can know as
many spells as they have IQ points. Spells are rated by the IQ
necessary to learn them.  Wizards roll 3/DX to see if they've cast
their spells correctly.  Each spell has a ST cost to cast; some spells
can be continued with a different ST cost.  Typically if a wizard
fails the roll to cast the spell it still costs 1 ST.  Wizard also adds
a couple more monsters, Myrmidons, and two sizes of dragon: 4 hex and 7
hex. Wizard is scaled well to work beside Melee as a person to person
combat board game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="description-of-in-the-labyrinth"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description of In the Labyrinth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Labyrinth (ITL) adds some elaborations to combat and magic, as
well as all the things necessary to make The Fantasy Trip a complete
roleplaying game. In particular, they add talents, non-magical
abilities. Talents allow a character to try to do something, or makes
something anybody can do easier. Talents are rated by the IQ necessary
to learn them, and by how many points IQ points they cost to get at
character creation. Talents cost twice as much (in IQ points at
character creation and in XP after character creation) for wizards as
they do regular “hero” characters. Regular heroes can learn spells, but
they cost triple (in IQ points at character creation and in XP after
character creation) what they cost wizards. ITL adds lots of spells,
many of which have non-combat uses, as you'd expect from an RPG.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding out if your character succeeds is a matter of rolling dice
equal to or lower than your stats. For easy things you roll 2 dice or
even 1 die, normal things take 3 dice, while difficult things take 4,
5, even or &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; dice! Look at the chance to roll a 14 or less on
6d6! Yikes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="/d6-dice-odds.png" src="https://tkurtbond.github.io/d6-dice-odds.png"&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="random-things-i-like-about-tft"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Random things I like about TFT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Melee and Wizard are relatively simple person to person combat board
games that serve as an introduction to the full system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Uses only six sided dice.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tactical hex grid based combat with verisimilitude.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The RPG is a complete fantasy roleplaying game in one 176 page book.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;ITL's one page Quick Character Generation lets you quickly roll up a
new character with interesting features and personality.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Table of Jobs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creating Magic Items.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;ITL's mini setting of the Village of Bendwyn and Southern Elyntia.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Characters, even complicated ones, fit on a 3×5 card.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It's got a free app, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://thefantasytrip.game/products/accessories/tft-helper/"&gt;TFT Helper&lt;/a&gt;,
for iOS and Android!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>android</category><category>ios</category><category>melee</category><category>metagaming</category><category>sjg</category><category>steve jackson games</category><category>tft</category><category>tft helper</category><category>the fantasy trip</category><category>wizard</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2024/01/21/the-fantasy-trip/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 22:31:57 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>