<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about minimizing)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/minimizing.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 23:07:24 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Simplifying</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/08/10/simplifying/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the things I need to do before I'm ready to build a house is
simplify.  I've got a lot of accumulated junk — physical and
mental, real and virtual — that I need to sort through, decide what is
important, and get rid of the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as the virtual goes, I need to simplify the tools I use: the
software I use to maintain my web site and blog, the tools I use to
process e-mail, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as real goes, I need to get rid of actual physical objects:
things I don't use, things I don't need to need to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mental is much harder, but probably more necessary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>minimizing</category><category>simplifying</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/08/10/simplifying/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2008 03:59:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Minimizing Gaming Baggage</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/07/minimizing-gaming-baggage/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I generally carry &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; too much stuff around to games.  I'm trying to
minimize it all, and here are some ways I've found or will be trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are running a system that doesn't focus on battlemat-oriented
tactical play, or the evening's adventure doesn't require that style
of play, you don't probably don't have much to carry to the nights
game: maybe just a single rulebook, your notes, and your dice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are using a battlemat and miniatures, you can cut down on what
you have to carry around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Just the core rulebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just needing to carry one small rulebook makes things much easier.
&lt;em&gt;Savage Worlds: Explorer's Editon&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Big Eyes, Small Mouth&lt;/em&gt; score
high here, as does &lt;em&gt;Rules Cyclopedia&lt;/em&gt; D&amp;amp;D and, given the pamphlet
size and low page count of the three core books, Original D&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Use flat paper figures and separate bases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never been one for painting miniatures, unfortunately, but I
have found that part of the fun of many roleplaying games is moving
miniatures around on a battlemat.  (The kids like them too.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that color printers that print on cardstock are cheap, paper
miniatures are practical &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; good looking.  But how do you
transport them?  It's great that they're way lighter than metal or
plastic miniatures, but if you actually cut out and glue up the
common triangle-from-the-top and triangle-from-the-side they still
take up a good bit of space, too much to take on a business trip,
for instance, and they're easily crushed.  The “T”-from-the-side
paper miniatures can sometimes be folded at the crossbar of the “T”,
but they tend to get bent when carried together. If you don't glue
the paper minatures you can carry them flat, but using paper clips
to hold them in their triangular or “T” shapes it is just too fiddly
and time consuming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what I recently started doing was cutting out and gluing
together just the front and backs.  This gives me flat, stiff
standups that can be easily stored in an envelope, but that together
with separate plastic bases provide nice good looking 3d
miniatures.  The plastic bases themselves are sturdy and can be
transported in a small bag; even a hundred of them can fit in my
computer bag without taking much space.  And the flat standups in an
envelope travel easily without being crushed or bent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;At some point I should try counters, like Fiery Dragon's Counter
Collections, which have the complete D&amp;amp;D 3.5E SRD monsters
covered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Put all needed opponents/monsters on index cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently got a printer that can print directly on cardstock and
3×5" cards, and I love being able to carry around the opponents and
deal out just the ones I need for the current encounter.  It greatly
reduces papershuffling in the middle of encounters, too, and cuts
down on the amount of junk on the table between you and the
players.  And you can carry them on in a shirt pocket on a pinch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don't forget stock opponents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a collection of stock opponents to fall back on really
helps.  Sometimes just shuffling the 3×5" cards gives me ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Flip Mats and dry-erase markers for battlemats&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got two of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.steelsqwire.com/"&gt;Steel Sqwire&lt;/a&gt;'s original Flip-Mat™ battlemats.
They've got 1 inch squares on one side and 1 inch hexes on the other
side, and they fold up flat to 8×10 inches and unfolded are 24×30
inches.  Two of these fit in my computer bag without bulking it up
noticably, and work wonderfully with dry-erase pens.  (No more
stains from wet-erase remains!)  The only problems is that since
they fold, they have creases, and don't lay pefectly flat.  However,
I've used these with paper miniatures and unless someone slaps
something down in the middle of mat or really jars the table things
are pretty stable and the miniatures don't fall down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Printed Cardstock Tile Terrain instead of battlemats&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently bought a bunch of PDF printable terrain tiles from
Skeleton Key Games.  They make nice looking terrain and they are all
standardized shapes that I can print on cardstock on an inexpensive
inkjet printer and cut out.  Since they're all the same size and
shape they stack flat and since they're cardstock you can easily
carry them in a standard 6½x9½ manilla envelope, and two or three
envelopes easily carry enough for an evening's play.  The
disadvantages are that tiles sometimes curve, which tends to lead to
the tiles moving around more as they're laid and played on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a side node, the various tile sets published by Wizards of the
Coast for use with D&amp;amp;D, Star Wars, and the associated miniatures
battle games have a great graphical appears and are very heavy,
sturdy solid cardboard (not corragated), so they make a great
battlemat.  Unfortunately, they're all different sizes which makes
it difficult to pack them compactly, and the thick cardboard which
makes them so stable in play also makes them surprisingly bulky.
(And I can never figure out easily if I've actually collected up all
the pieces after the game.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2008-08-20 01:29:26: I'm still undecided as to whether these are
slower and less convenient than the Flip-Mats.  They do look neat,
though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!--  --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stones/bennies/chips/status chips, playing cards, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>minimizing</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/07/minimizing-gaming-baggage/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2008 01:15:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>