<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about oberon-2)</title>
  <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/oberon-2.atom</id>
  <updated>2022-06-05T16:35:28Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/oberon-2.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/oberon-2/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>The criticisms of Pascal in “Why Pascal is Not My Favorite Programming Language” applied to Oberon</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2022/06/05/the-criticisms-of-pascal-in-why-pascal-is-not-my-favorite-programming-language-applied-to-oberon/</id>
    <updated>2022-06-05T12:29:05-04:00</updated>
    <published>2022-06-05T12:29:05-04:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2022/06/05/the-criticisms-of-pascal-in-why-pascal-is-not-my-favorite-programming-language-applied-to-oberon/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I reread Brian W. Kernighan’s famous paper “Why Pascal is Not My
Favorite Programming Language”
(&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.cs.virginia.edu/~evans/cs655/readings/bwk-on-pascal.html"&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://doc.cat-v.org/bell_labs/why_pascal/"&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;) to see if those or
similar criticisms can still be applied to the Oberon family of
languages,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oberon_(programming_language)"&gt;Oberon&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oberon-2"&gt;Oberon-2&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://people.inf.ethz.ch/wirth/Oberon/index.html"&gt;Revised
Oberon&lt;/a&gt;. I found
Oberon-2 to be particularly inspiring, but feel that both Oberon and
Oberon-2 lack some of the practical aspects that made C such a
revelation to me back in the 1980s when I first encountered it, after
having programmed mostly in various BASICs, 6502 machine code, VAX
MACRO, and Pascal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here are Kernighan’s summary, nine criticisms, along with my
comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the size of an array is part of its type, it is not possible to
write general-purpose routines, that is, to deal with arrays of
different sizes. In particular, string handling is very difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is still a problem in the original Oberon, but Oberon-2
introduced open arrays, which allows any size of array to be passed
to a procedure. While you can’t return arrays of arbitrary sizes from
a procedure, you can dynamically allocate any size array using
&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;POINTER TO ARRAY&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;NEW&lt;/code&gt;, and return the pointer. Revised
Oberon adopted open arrays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lack of static variables, initialization and a way to communicate
non-hierarchically combine to destroy the “locality” of a program -
variables require much more scope than they ought to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This criticism still applies. None of the Oberon languages include
static variables or initialization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lack of static variables is somewhat mitigated by the ability to
divide things up using modules, since the tendency is to create a
module for the shared variable and the procedures that depend on it,
but is still clumsy if the only thing you need is a static variable
in one procedure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The one-pass nature of the language forces procedures and functions
to be presented in an unnatural order; the enforced separation of
various declarations scatters program components that logically
belong together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oberon and Oberon-2 allow mixing &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;CONST&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;TYPE&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;VAR&lt;/code&gt;
declarations in any order and to appear multiple times, but still
requires procedure and forward procedure declarations to come after
all other declarations. In Revised Oberon &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;CONST&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;TYPE&lt;/code&gt;, and
&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;VAR&lt;/code&gt; declarations must occur and in that order, followed by
procedure declarations, so the original criticism applies entirely
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lack of separate compilation impedes the development of large
programs and makes the use of libraries impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not a problem any more. All the Oberon languages use modules,
introduced in Modula. Arguably, this is much superior to C’s model of
separate compilation and using header files to ensure consistent
function declarations are consistent across files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The order of logical expression evaluation cannot be controlled,
which leads to convoluted code and extraneous variables.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This appears to not apply to the Oberon languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ‘case’ statement is emasculated because there is no default
clause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Original Oberon and Oberon-2 both have &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;ELSE&lt;/code&gt; clauses for &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;CASE&lt;/code&gt;
statements. Revised Oberon does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The standard I/O is defective. There is no sensible provision for
dealing with files or program arguments as part of the standard
language, and no extension mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IO in the Oberon family of languages is mostly defined by the
procedures provided in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oberon_(operating_system)"&gt;Oberon
System&lt;/a&gt;,
the operating system written in Oberon (and later in Oberon-2). It
has good facilities for dealing with files, considered by some to be
a better API than the familiar Unix/C API, for the functionality it
provides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of the Oberon languages provide a standard method for access
to program arguments in the Unix/C style, as the Oberon System used
entirely different mechanisms.  Those Oberon[-2] implementations
I've used outside of the Oberon System all provided some access to
the program arguments, usually as a procedure returns the number of
program arguments and another that returns a specific argument, but
none of them used the same API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The language lacks most of the tools needed for assembling large
programs, most notably file inclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The addition of separately compiled modules that provide a defined
interface mostly obviates this criticism and is superior to the
kludge of separate complication and include files provided by C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is no escape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the Oberon languages include the module &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;SYSTEM&lt;/code&gt;, which
provides low level access to addresses of variables and to individual
bits of memory, along with bit manipulation of integers. Revised
Oberon adds access to sizes of types. Oberon and Oberon-2 provide a
&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;VAL&lt;/code&gt; function that allows interpreting a variable of one type as a
variable of another type. Revised Oberon does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the Oberon languages still have semicolon as separator instead of
semicolon as terminator.   I much prefer semicolon as terminator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All-in-all, I'm disappointed in Revised Oberon.  While I approve of a
few of its changes, most of them seem to be a definite step backward.
I think Wirth's minimalism does him a disservice here.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <category term="c" label="c"/>
    <category term="oberon" label="oberon"/>
    <category term="oberon-system" label="oberon system"/>
    <category term="oberon-2" label="oberon-2"/>
    <category term="pascal" label="pascal"/>
    <category term="revised-oberon" label="revised oberon"/>
    <category term="unix" label="unix"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
