<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about ova galactic rangers)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/ova-galactic-rangers.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 18:49:37 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>OVA: Galactic Rangers — Session 1</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2023/03/24/ova-galactic-rangers-session-1/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;aside class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text in &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;{&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;}&lt;/code&gt; are out of game explanations.  Text in
&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;[&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;]&lt;/code&gt; are out of character comments from the players and
GM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Player Characters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strazin Kostra, tigerman Galactic Ranger!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yin, a shapechanging Galactic Ranger!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strazin fights Gary from Accounting (who looks like a humanoid
dragon), his boss, on his first day at work!  {This was just a
training exercise.} He defeats him in one blow!  But Gary says “You
may have beaten me, but Cheryl from HR is the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; challenge…” (Dun
dun dun!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gary sends us out after four criminal bosses: the Turtle does
protection, the Tiger does gambling, the Bird does illegal information
gathering and trading, and the Dragon does drugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decide to go after the Bird later.  We'd have go off planet to the
satellite controlling space station around the planet of the bird
people.  On paper it is a telecommunication booster, but he uses it to
steal data.  Anyway, he's the hardest to approach, and we need
somebody smart, which is not playing to either of our strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to gather hard evidence of crimes, so they can be put away
for ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decide to go after the Tiger.  We are going to a casino with
associated brothel, Alpha Blue, under cover.  We are offered a hit of
a mild (and legal) drug at registration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{Drugs are not illegal unless really special: moon sugar, super
cocaine, etc. Crimes: illegal pit fighting where people die, contests
where people are expected to die, etc.}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yin goes straight to the tables, and breaks even, then gets the
feeling there is a disturbance in the force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strazin gets a mental image of a guy going back and to the left
through a secret passage to one of the arenas.  Strazin tells Yin
telepathically and they follow the guy to a death match.  They've got
five guys going over beams over a death drop, and they're betting on
who survives.  We end up in a lower box with the betters.  We've got a
martial arts guy, Fister, and Loud Strike, a wanted gun runner, who is
also wanted. {We are wired with audio and video.}  Fister and Loud
Strike are talking about going to the private suite of the Tiger to
get the winnings after the match.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Contestants are: Red &amp;amp; Blue tied for first, then Green &amp;amp; Black
tied, and trailing Yellow.  Yin and then Strazin bets on Yellow; none
of the betters can believe it.  Then Strazin uses Psychic to assist
Yellow, pushing twice then Green pushed black off in frustration and
lost his balance and fell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We win the jackpot, and Fister and the other guy take us up to the
Tigers office, where we see &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; tiger (not &lt;strong&gt;The Tiger&lt;/strong&gt;), who is
very rotund, not at all fit, Fat Tony, who asks if we want blue bucks
(the casino money) or to cash it out now.  We keep the blue bucks, for
later, and when he goes to pays recognizes Yin as infamous across the
Galaxy, and a fight breaks out.  It turns against us and we flee, Yin
uses &lt;em class="ability"&gt;Shape-Shifter&lt;/em&gt; to go down through the vents in the
floor and Strazin uses &lt;em class="ability"&gt;Psychic&lt;/em&gt; to read their weapon
patterns and to jump out the window and time it to catch the elevator
on the way down.  Yin says “We will never talk about this!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got &lt;strong class="xp"&gt;2 XP&lt;/strong&gt; each, and each get a bonus &lt;strong class="xp"&gt;1 XP&lt;/strong&gt;, for meta
reasons.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ova</category><category>ova galactic rangers</category><category>rpg</category><category>session logs</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2023/03/24/ova-galactic-rangers-session-1/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 25 Mar 2023 01:08:07 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>