<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about pirates)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/pirates.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2022 22:45:45 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Actual Play: Dead Men Tell No Tales, Part 2</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/11/25/dead-men-tell-no-tales-part-2/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I ran another session using the the &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Spanish Main&lt;/em&gt;
one-sheet “Dead Men Tell No Tales” with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/Downloads/POTSM/DeadMen.pdf"&gt;“Dead Men Tell No Tales”&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/"&gt;PEG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E.A. couldn't attend, but L.B. could, so she played Phillipe Gujon and
Alice Pettigrew, and out of deference to her dislike of playing
“boys”, it was revealed that “Phillipe” was actually “Phelicity”!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the roster was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. playing Isaiah Kestrel, Captain of the Lady Faire&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. playing Scarred Jack&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;L.B. playing (as her main character) Phelicity Gujon and (as her
secondary character) Alice Pettigrew&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We picked up a couple of days from the island on the map.  Not liking
the look of the decayed dock, they anchored offshore and left the crew
to guard the sloop.  On shore they found everybody 50 years dead.
They easily found the mine, ignored the skeletons wrapped in pirate
flags, and were shocked to find the lady hanging above the treasure in
the depths of the mines.  And of course, they were then attacked by
the six skeletons wrapped in pirate flags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T.A. was plagued by poor initiative card draws and low rolls, and
earned the unhappy nickname “Captain Slowpants”, and eventually ended
up “Captain Slow-anything”, much to his dismay.  Eventually, however,
they managed to kill the skeletons, and that's where the game ended.
(We only had a short time to play.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We played in my living room around a low, 2 foot diameter table,
keeping dice, tokens, and cards on the table and character sheets
off.  We didn't bother to user miniatures.  I used gaming stones to
represent wound and shaken statuses, and check track of the skeletons
just by removing the d6 that I rolled for their fighting attacks, so
there was no book keeping.  I thought that all worked well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(My bones and joints, on the other hand, did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; work well when
getting up off the floor after a couple of hours of play.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>kids</category><category>one-sheet</category><category>pirates</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>spoilers</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/11/25/dead-men-tell-no-tales-part-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2008 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Actual Play: Dead Men Tell No Tales, Part 1</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/11/15/dead-men-tell-no-tales-part-1/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Some of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt; and I played through about half of the &lt;em&gt;Pirates of
the Spanish Main&lt;/em&gt; Savage Worlds one-sheet “Dead Men Tell No Tales”
this afternoon and evening, before and after supper.  This is one of
the free downloads &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/"&gt;Pinnacle Entertainment Group&lt;/a&gt; did for the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roster was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. playing Isaiah Kestrel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. playing Alice Pettigrew and Phillipe Gujon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. played Scarred Jack&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/Downloads/POTSM/DeadMen.pdf"&gt;“Dead Men Tell No Tales”&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/"&gt;PEG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They found the dying pirate with the chest manacled to his foot, and
after he died opened the chest and found the treasure map, and decided
to head for the island.  Along the way they found and boarded the
decaying pirate ship, from which they deduced had come the dying
pirate.  They had a hard time with the zombie pirate captain wildcard,
who had the luck of the initiative most of the time, ending up with
the Joker &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; times, and the high card of the draw most of the
rest of the time.  The zombie wildcard incapacitated Alice with one
blow that ended up doing five wounds at a whack, and things were
looking dire.  However, the zombie pirate captain's luck with the
iniative cards finally left him However, E.A., rolling for the crew
extras who showed up after hearing Alice scream as she went down, aced
an attack roll, then aced all three of the damage dice, and then aced
at least one of the rerolls, putting the wildcard down decisively.
After that M.A. had Scarred Jack try an untrained Healing roll and
aced it big time, so most of Alice's wounds got healed and M.A. wants
Jack to learn Healing for real now, which is neat.  After they
returned to their ship the other ship collapsed and sank.  They
decided to continue to follow the treasure map, even though a storm
came up.  Alice was unconscious for four days.  After couple of days
it was obvious that they and their ship were suffering from the curse,
and that's were we had to leave the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should have looked up all the details of the edges and hindrances
and wrote them on the kids character sheets, and on my copies, before
the kids came over for the game.  I had to do it while they were
there, and of course they wanted to get on to the gaming.  However, I
knew we'd be looking them up in the middle of game if I didn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also need to play more often so I can keep the details in mind
better.  Maybe next weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>kids</category><category>one-sheet</category><category>peg</category><category>pirates</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>spoilers</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/11/15/dead-men-tell-no-tales-part-1/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2008 04:29:42 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>