<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about pirates of the spanish main)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/pirates-of-the-spanish-main.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Aug 2021 05:57:54 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Pirates! Session #5: Revenge is Sweet (and so are pies!)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/03/29/pirates-session-5-revenge-is-sweet-and-so-are-pies/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I guess I've got a &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Spanish Main&lt;/em&gt; campaign on my hands…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew the A. kids wanted to play a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/pages/roleplaying-games-played-with-the-kids/#savage-worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt; Pirates! game
when L.B. came to visit next, but I still hadn't anything the Thursday
before I was to pick L.B. up.  Luckily I had lunch that day with a
coworker who plays RPGs, and together we brainstormed an adventure
outline.  (Thanks, M.A.H.!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. playing Isaiah Kestrel, former captain of the &lt;em&gt;Lady Faire&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. playing Alice Pettigrew&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. playing Captain (Scarred) Jack&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;L.B. playing Phelicity Phillipe Gujon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew that losing the &lt;em&gt;Lady Faire&lt;/em&gt; still rankled, so I made the
villans of the damsel in distress plot suggested by M.A.H. the
mutinous crew of the &lt;em&gt;Lady Faire&lt;/em&gt; and the evil pirate who had taken
over the ship after the mutiny.  So, while the kids' struggling
pirates were looking for their next smuggling job (all their current
tiny boat would let them manage) they heard a rumor that their former
crew had kidnapped the daughter of a wealthy merchant.  They tracked
down the fisherman who had witnessed the attack on the yacht and
confirmed it had been their mutineers.  After this they set sail for
Tortuga, looking for information about where those mutinous dogs were
now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first time I'd bothered to use the sailing rules from the
rulebook, and they very quickly learned why somebody needs Knowledge
(Navigation)!  Eventually they reached Tortuga, and as soon as they
landed they started looking for information.  They very quickly
learned why somebody needs Streetwise!  Luckily for them, many people
had gone to a yearly pie-eating contest held by a local eatery.  They
entered, and Phelicity should have won, but another pirate was
initially declared the winner; however, the resulting pie-fight
conclusively proved he was cheating (and Phelicity got the prize
money!), and in the end he turned out to be Deadeye Dave, one of their
former crew.  He'd been dropped there to arrange ransom, while the
rest of the crew had gone off to a safe haven in the Virgin Islands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So off they went to the Virgin Islands.  After some excellent
navigating by former captain Isaiah they arrived, snuck up the side of
the former &lt;em&gt;Lady Faire&lt;/em&gt;, now named the &lt;em&gt;Saucy Wench&lt;/em&gt; (which the kids
universally agreed was a &lt;strong&gt;terrible&lt;/strong&gt; name), nailed their erstwhile
crew under hatches, and disposed of the interloping pirate captain and
his chief henchman just in time to intimidate their former crew as
they burst the hatches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually they left Deadeye Dave on one deserted island, the other
pirates on another, and sailed back to collect the reward for from the
damsel's relived father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They decided that since they had the &lt;em&gt;Lady Faire&lt;/em&gt; back that Isaiah
was captain of her again, while Captain Jack remained captain of the
smaller boat.  M.A. was charmingly nervous that the girls would
abandon Captain Jack's boat for Isaiah Kestrel's, since it was bigger,
but I think the fact that they now had a small fleet, rather than just
a single boat made everybody happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I have to figure out if this has affected their Fame, and how much
money the reward came to!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>kids</category><category>pirates of the spanish main</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/03/29/pirates-session-5-revenge-is-sweet-and-so-are-pies/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2009 20:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Pirates! Session #4: Smuggler's Song</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/12/20/pirates-session-4-smugglers-song/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/Downloads/POTSM/Smuggler%27s_Song.pdf"&gt;“Smuggler'S Song”&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/"&gt;PEG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. playing Isaiah Kestrel, former captain of the Lady Faire&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. playing Alice Pettigrew&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. playing Captain (Scarred) Jack&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;L.B. playing Phelicity Gujon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="recap"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last time out the kids had lost their ship, lost the treasure, and
deposed their captain.  They'd had to build themselves a new boat to
escape the once-cursed island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time out I decided that they'd forced by their dismal economic
situation into working for another pirate delivering smuggled goods,
and ran them through the &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Spanish Main&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/onesheets.html"&gt;one-sheet&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/Downloads/POTSM/Smuggler%27s_Song.pdf"&gt;Smuggler's Song&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They did pretty well, though they did end up running from the watch
several times.  And they mostly got paid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amusingly, my sister was not happy when they told her they'd been
fighting in a bar, so I've promised to steer closer to a “G” rating
next time…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>kids</category><category>one-sheet</category><category>peg</category><category>pirates of the spanish main</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>spoilers</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/12/20/pirates-session-4-smugglers-song/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2008 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>