<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about rpg)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/rpg.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 03:42:25 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Powers &amp; Perils is Oddly Fascinating</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/14/powers-perils-is-oddly-fascinating/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I bought &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://powersandperils.org/"&gt;Powers &amp;amp; Perils&lt;/a&gt; when it first came out.  While I was
never able to complete building a character, I did have fun reading
the rules and the setting details.  It was oddly fascinating.  So
complicated.  Every so often, I circle back to look at it again,
usually starting at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://powersandperils.org/"&gt;Powers &amp;amp; Perils&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I noticed this time is that a second edition is available on the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://powersandperils.org/books.htm"&gt;rules&lt;/a&gt; page, which includes both a PDF of the complete rules and a
PDF of the &lt;cite&gt;Perilous Lands&lt;/cite&gt; setting information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules are extensively hyperlinked, both in the table on contents
and in cross-references, which should make using such a complicated
system easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now I can't imaging finding a group that would be interested in
playing &lt;cite&gt;Powers &amp;amp; Perils&lt;/cite&gt;, but there is always a lingering impulse to
do something with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>powers &amp; perils</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/14/powers-perils-is-oddly-fascinating/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 03:15:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>BESM 4E - Initial Look</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/12/besm-4e-initial-look/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I took advantage of the Late Pledges option on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/370924922/besm-fourth-edition-big-eyes-small-mouth-rpg"&gt;BESM 4th
Edition&lt;/a&gt; kickstarter and have access to the PDFs they've released so
far.  It is a further refinement of &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt; with some point costs
re-balanced.  Interestingly, the combat system in the BESM 4E core
book is very, very simple, with only an Attack roll versus a Defence
roll.  And the detailed list of skills from &lt;cite&gt;BESM 2ER&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;
have been replaced with 12 “Skill Groups”, separated into three types
based on how expensive the skill group is, rated by utility.  I'm
hoping that the planned &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/370924922/besm-fourth-edition-big-eyes-small-mouth-rpg/posts/2569713"&gt;BESM Extras&lt;/a&gt; book will include more combat
options and the more detailed skill rules.  (The &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E Character
Folio&lt;/cite&gt; seems to indicate the detailed skills will be in &lt;cite&gt;BESM
Extras&lt;/cite&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;'s switch to roll over, which is continued in &lt;cite&gt;BESM
4E&lt;/cite&gt;. There are 25 race templates and 25 class templates, up from &lt;cite&gt;BESM
3E&lt;/cite&gt;'s 20 each, and 20 Humanoid Companions templates that can easily be
converted into race or class templates. &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt; introduces &lt;em&gt;edges&lt;/em&gt;
and &lt;em&gt;obstacles&lt;/em&gt;, which add 1 (for minor) or 2 (for major) dice to a
roll, keeping the 2 best (for edges) or 2 worst (for obstacles),
similar to &lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D 5E&lt;/cite&gt;'s advantage and disadvantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way Standard and Custom Variables and Restrictions in &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;
worked has changed and been renamed.  They are now Enhancements and
Limiters, and instead of having a character point cost they reduce or
increase the Effective Level of an attribute.  For instance, If you
have bought the Weapon Attribute up to 10 Levels and add the Accurate
Weapon Enhancement (1 assignment) and the Area standard Enhancement
for 10 metres radius (2 assignments) and the Range standard
Enhancement for 100 metres (3 assignments) and Ammo Weapon Limiter for
2-3 shots available (2 assignments) makes the Effective Level 6 (10 -
1 - 2 - 3 + 2).  This makes the cost of Enhancements and Limiters
proportional to the base cost of an Attribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like the point costs for things are one-third to one-quarter
those of &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;, which keeps things a little simpler.  Here are the
suggested power levels:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 47%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 53%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Power Level&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Character Points&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sub-Human&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;25-49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adventurer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;50-74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heroic&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;75-99&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mythical&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;100-149&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Superhuman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;150-199&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Superpowered&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;200-249&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Godlike&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;250+&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a 10 page index, which I was happy to see, but alas the
entries are not hyperlinked.  There are copious cross references by
page number, which is very useful, but again not hyperlinked.  The
table of contents is reasonably detailed, though again not
hyperlinked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt; is firmly in the “GMs should fudge dice rolls if it will
make the game better.”  I'm ambivalent about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an 8-page section on Shojo roleplaying that seems
interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “Anime Multiverse” chapter seems identical between 3E and 4E and
presents an interesting short take on a multiverse cosmology, if you
need one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;, &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt; has lots of colors.  Lots and lots of
colors.  (I can see no reason for one column of text on each page to
have a background color.)  I recognize most of the art from earlier
editions.  I liked it then and still like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a simple character sheet, in color and black-and-white
versions in the PDF of the core rulebook, or for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dyskami.ca/downloads/BESM4_character_sheets.pdf"&gt;download&lt;/a&gt; from the
Dyskami &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dyskami.ca/besm.html"&gt;BESM RPG&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the &lt;cite&gt;Dramatis Personae&lt;/cite&gt; PDFs give 15 example characters, with
backgrounds, personalities, discussion of their Attributes and
Defects, three Adventure Hooks, and a personal quote.  These are
useful in seeing how the various Attributes work.  The backgrounds are
tied into the Anime Multiverse from the core book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I think it looks good.  If the things are in &lt;cite&gt;BESM Extras&lt;/cite&gt;
that I hope are there, I can definitely see switching from &lt;cite&gt;BESM 2ER&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>besm</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/12/besm-4e-initial-look/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 18:13:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Slings in RPGs: Often Nerfed</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/07/slings-in-rpgs-often-nerfed/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to reading &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-4541318/Roman-sling-bullets-deadly-44-Magnum.html?fbclid=IwAR2IZhVYW4-4_BcuQDOq2yGXwwurzBd3HNSo1BzN7XUwZLKHF4XZ54yy0VU"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; article, headlined “Roman sling bullets
used against Scottish tribes 2,000 years ago were as deadly as a .44
Magnum”, I was thinking about slings in RPGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've often thought that sling bullets are woefully nerfed in many
RPGs, especially D&amp;amp;D.  In D&amp;amp;D 5E, for instance, they're only 1d4,
while a short bow is 1d6 and a long bow is 1d8. For comparison,
daggers are 1d4 and longswords are 1d8.  In OD&amp;amp;D using Greyhawk's
“Damage Done by Weapon Type” table sling &lt;em&gt;stones&lt;/em&gt; are 1d4, and the
same in B/X D&amp;amp;D's optional “Variable Weapon Damage” table.  AD&amp;amp;D has
sling &lt;em&gt;bullets&lt;/em&gt; as 1d4+1 and sling &lt;em&gt;stones&lt;/em&gt; as 1d4.  D&amp;amp;D 3.5E has them
as 1d4.  So the D&amp;amp;D editions pretty consistently have it as
1d4. Definitely nerfed.  Except in 3-book OD&amp;amp;D and B/X D&amp;amp;D without the
“Variable Weapon Damage” table, where all weapons did 1d6 damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savage_Worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt; slings are Str+d4, while a bow is 2d6.  For
comparison, a dagger is Str+d4 and a long sword is Str+d8.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RuneQuest"&gt;RuneQuest&lt;/a&gt; 2E they are 1d8, similar to a Composite bow at 1d8+1
and broadsword at 1d8.  In Elric! (a member of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stormbringer_(role-playing_game)"&gt;Stormbringer&lt;/a&gt; line
of games, appearing between 4th Edition and 5th Edition, but the rules
were substantially equivalent to Stormbringer 5E; It is relative of
RuneQuest mechanically, part of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Role-Playing"&gt;Basic Roleplaying (BRP)&lt;/a&gt; family
of games) a sling is 1d8+1, similar to a Desert Recurve Bow at 1d8+2,
and a broadsword at 1d8+1.  So in the BRP games they are not nerfed.
In DragonQuest their Damage Modifier is +1, while a dagger is +0, a
long bow is +4 and a broadsword is +4.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talislanta"&gt;Talislanta&lt;/a&gt; 4E a sling's Damage Rating is 4, as is a dagger, while a
long bow and broadsword are 8.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hero_System"&gt;Hero&lt;/a&gt; 5E, sling damage is 1d6+1, same as a medium bow or a light
long bow, while a medium long bow is 1 ½ d6 (that's 1 and ½ d6)
and a heavy long bow is 2d6.  A dagger is 1d6-1 and a broadsword is
1d6+1.  Note that strong enough characters add damage to this based on
how strong they are. Not nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GURPS#Prior_RPG_history"&gt;GURPS&lt;/a&gt; 4E, damage is based on your strength, and the only dice used is
d6.  We'll use an average Strength 10 character as an example.  Their
Thrust damage is 1d-2 and their Swing damage is 1d. An opponent's
Damage Resistance (DR) is subtracted from the rolled damage and any
damage left is multiplied by a modifier for each type of damage.
Piercing damage has a ×1 modifier, cutting has a ×1.5 modifier, and
impaling has a ×2 modifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, sling damage is swing piercing, and the damage for that for our
average character is 1d.  A longbow is thrust+2 impaling. and the
damage for that is 1d, and whatever makes it past DR is doubled.  A
regular bow is thrust+1 impaling, and the damage for that is 1d+1
(minus DR) ×2.  A dagger is thrust-1 impaling, so that is 1d-3 (minus
DR) ×2.  A thrusting broadsword is swing+1 cutting (1d+1 (minus DR)
×1.5) or thrust+2 impaling (1d+2 (minus DR) ×2).  I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; that's
nerfed a little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I'd like to note that when actually playing GURPS I think this is
simpler to do at the table than it sounds like. The damage values for
each attack is figured out at character creation :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fantasy_Trip"&gt;The Fantasy Trip&lt;/a&gt;, which like GURPS only uses d6, slings do
1d-2, small bows do 1d-1, longbows do 1d+2, daggers do 1d-1, and
broadswords do 2d.  A little bit nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Eyes,_Small_Mouth"&gt;Big Eyes Small Mouth (BESM)&lt;/a&gt; 2nd Edition Revised, slings are not
listed, but a long bow does 5 damage, a longsword does 10 damage, and
a dagger does 5 damage.  In BESM 3rd Edition, an average person has an
Attack Combat Value (ACV) of 4 and a Damage Multiplier of 5.  Each weapon has
a Level, which is multiplied by the Damage Multiplier and added to the
ACV for the final damage.  Slings are Level 1 (1 × 5 + 4 = 9), as are
daggers.  Longbows are Level 3 (3 × 5 + 1 = 16), as are longswords.
Definitely nerfed.  (It is the same in &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H%C3%A2rnMaster"&gt;HarnMaster&lt;/a&gt;, weapon impact (damage) for Melee weapons has three
Aspects, Blunt (B), Edge (E), and Point (P).  A dagger's impact is B
1, E 2, P 5, while a broadsword is B 3, E 5, and P 3.  A Missile
weapon's impact depends on the type of missile weapon and the range:
short, medium, long, and extreme.  Slings are Short 4, Medium 3, Long
2, and Extreme 2.  Shortbows are Short 6, Medium 5, Long 4, Extreme 3.
Longbows are Short 8, Medium 8, Long 6, Extreme 5.  Nerfed.  I'll note
that these weapon or missile impacts are added to a Strike Impact is
decided by a table indexed by how well the attacker did on opposed
rolls of attack skill against the defender's skill in Block,
Counterstrike, Dodge, or if the defender ignored the attack. For Melee
attacks this can result in the defender having blocked the attack,
either the attacker or the defender fumbling or stumbling, the
defender gaining a Tactical Advantage (a free action), or either or
both having made a Strike, which generates from 1 to 4 d6s.  For
Missle attacks this can result in a Miss (with a chance to hit an
adjacent combatant, a Wild (a fumble roll), a Block, or a Strike,
which generates from 1 to 3 d6s.  The Armor Protection value is
subtracked and the result is the total Effective Impact, which is then
referenced on the Injury Table to determine where the on the body the
injury is and how serious it is.  There are no Hit Points like D&amp;amp;D or
Wounds like Savage Worlds.  Instead the character accumulates injuries
like “1 Minor Slash Left Upper Arm, 1 injury level”.  The total injury
level determines the difficulty of the character staying conscious and
penalty to any skill roll.  Some of the injuries may immediately kill
the injured character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a good thread by Robert S. Conley (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://batintheattic.blogspot.com/"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.batintheattic.com/index.php"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rpggeek.com/rpgdesigner/22847/robert-conley"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;) on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.rpgpub.com/threads/the-one-where-i-sing-the-praises-of-harnmaster.2363/"&gt;RPG PUB&lt;/a&gt;
that talks some more about HarnMaster combat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In West End Games' &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D6_Fantasy"&gt;D6 Fantasy&lt;/a&gt;, attributes are measured in d6s and 2D
is an average human.  Bow and sling damage and melee damage as d6s
added to a number of d6s determined by your Strength Damage, which is
determined by your Physique attribute or Lifting skill (both measured
in d6s), drop any adds, divided by 2.  So our average human's Strength
Damage is 1D.  Then longbows add +2D+2, shortbows add +1D+2, and
slings add +1D.  For comparison, daggers add +1D and broad/long swords
ad +2D+2.  So, nerfed, although it is hard to make precise
distinctions at this level of resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tunnels_%26_Trolls"&gt;Tunnels &amp;amp; Trolls&lt;/a&gt; only uses d6s and weapons are measured in “Dice +
Adds”, that is the number of d6s to roll and the number of points to
add to the dice total.  The common sling is 2d.  A very light self bow
is 2d, a light self bow is 3d, a medium self bow is 4d, a heavy self
bow is 5d, and a extra-heavy self bow is 6d.  These all have
increasing Strength Required to use the weapon.  For comparison, a
Dirk is 2D+1 and a broadsword is 3d+4.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dragon_Warriors"&gt;Dragon Warriors&lt;/a&gt; weapon damage has two parts: an armor
penetration die (measured in dice: d4, d6, d8, etc.) and damage
points.  The armor penetration die is rolled against the Armour Factor
of the defender's armour: a Gambeson has an Armour Factor of 2 while
Plate has an Armor Factor of 5, and the attacker has to roll &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt;
than the Armour Factor to inflict damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sling has Damage (d6, 3 points) while a Bow has Damage (d6, 4
points).  For comparison, a dagger has Damage (d4, 3 points) and a
sword has Damage (d8, 4 points).  Slightly nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I GM games that I think nerf slings, like D&amp;amp;D, I often use a
house rule that sling bullets are higher damage than sling stones, and
more similar to the damage of a short bow, 1d6, for example.  I may
have been underestimating them and should consider them closer to a
long bow, 1d8, as Chaosium's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Role-Playing"&gt;Basic Roleplaying (BRP)&lt;/a&gt; variants
(RuneQuest, Elric) do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>d&amp;d</category><category>dragonquest</category><category>rpg</category><category>runequest</category><category>slings</category><category>talislanta</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/07/slings-in-rpgs-often-nerfed/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 19:40:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ulisses Spiele updates Heliograph Space 1889 pdfs with bookmarks and document outlines</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/07/ulisses-spiele-updates-heliograph-space-1889-pdfs-with-bookmarks-and-document-outlines/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I got notices from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://ulisses-spiele.de/"&gt;Ulisses Spiele&lt;/a&gt; via &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/"&gt;DriveThruRPG&lt;/a&gt; that
each of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.heliograph.com/"&gt;Heliograph&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space:_1889"&gt;Space 1889&lt;/a&gt; PDFs had been updated, saying:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“An updated PDF with bookmarks and meta information is now available.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a little surprised to see this at this late date — is there that
much demand for these PDFs?  Still, I'm pleased to get the updates,
and glad there's still interest.  I've never tried the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rpggeek.com/rpgsystem/742/ubiquity-roleplaying-system"&gt;Ubiquity&lt;/a&gt; based
version, though I‘ve been thinking about buying the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savage_Worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt;
versions of those adventures, but the original system has charms of
its own.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>rpg</category><category>space 1889</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/07/ulisses-spiele-updates-heliograph-space-1889-pdfs-with-bookmarks-and-document-outlines/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 15:10:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Delving Deeper Revisited</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2015/12/14/delving-deeper-revisited/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ran across the current edition of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://forum.immersiveink.com/viewtopic.php?f=15&amp;amp;t=113"&gt;Delving Deeper&lt;/a&gt; on the web a
few weeks ago, and it prompted me to reread it in some depth.  (It had
been some time since I read my copy of the Delving Deeper &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2013/03/21/my-delving-deeper-boxset-came-today/"&gt;box
set&lt;/a&gt;.)  The current version of the Delving Deeper Reference Rules
(V4) is available &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ddo.immersiveink.com/dd.html"&gt;online&lt;/a&gt; in hypertext or for free download as three
digest-sized booklets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've decided I like this rule set very much.  It really seems to
reflect the rules of the original 3 Little Brown Books of Original D&amp;amp;D
very well, and I can see that there are enough differences from, say,
the Labyrinth Lord rules that I have been using, to make it a
different experience.  I'm looking forward to trying it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It prompted me to sit down and draw out a dungeon level and fill it
using the method in &lt;cite&gt;Delving Deeper&lt;/cite&gt;, which turned out to be good fun.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>0e</category><category>d&amp;d</category><category>delving deeper</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2015/12/14/delving-deeper-revisited/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2015 19:09:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Dwimmermount arrived</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/22/dwimmermount-arrived/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;My physical copy of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/autarch/dwimmermount"&gt;Dwimmermount&lt;/a&gt; arrived today.  It's huge.  It looks good.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>dwimmermount</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/22/dwimmermount-arrived/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 01:47:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>“Footsteps of the Fallen” comes to an end</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/11/footsteps-of-the-fallen-comes-to-an-end/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="section" id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A.H. — the DM&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;C.A.H. — Bulwark, a warforged&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Mord, an orc rogue&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;B.McC. — Vex, a changeling wizard/necromancer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We played the last session of M.A.H.'s “Footsteps of the Fallen”
campaign, and were successful in eliminating the Mourning!  In mass
battle we defeated the army of the Lord of the Blades.  Afterward we
killed the Lord of the Blades, but the psychic purple creature who
turned out to be behind it all escaped.  We're left with a bunch of
psychically active purple glass that can be mined and turned into
psychically active artifacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was probably the 33rd game session we'd played, and we'd been
playing since the first session on 2013-02-27.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got +5500 XP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>4e</category><category>d&amp;d</category><category>eberron</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/11/footsteps-of-the-fallen-comes-to-an-end/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2014 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>T.A.'s PotSM: The Scarlet Rose</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/08/t.a.s-potsm-the-scarlet-rose/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We played “The Scarlet Rose”, an adventure from off the net, so if
you haven't played that you might want to skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — GameMaster&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Capt. Jack Savage, Rowena Blackwood&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heard rumors of Cutthroat Henry Hobbs' treasure; key under Santa
Domingo's Lion's Gate (St. Leon's church).  Go there.  Try to climb
down well in church.  Rowena falls, but quietly.  Find box with sand
casting of key with the number 4 on the handle.  Took it to a
blacksmith, who recognizes it as a key from a gold collection site
from mines of Santa Domingo — he warns us that the spirits of natives
who died in the mines infest them to this day.  11$ to make the key.
Can't find any way to protect us from the spirits. Bought Lantern and
Bullseye Lantern and 6 pints of oil for 89$.  Went to mines.  5 main
passages.  Some men came out of one of the other passages.  Their
leader is Catfish Carlos Peña, and they say they can't let us get away
knowing about them.  We fire and kill Peña and others flee.  Number 4
area opens to our key.  Only thing of interest is the Shipping
Security Log.  The 13th shipment lists Robyn H Besh (an anagram for
Henry Hobbs) is in charge.  He must have changed the log and took
command of the ship to took it to Santiago (destination listed on the
log).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jack has a one-masted sloop with 4 crew.  On the 3rd day one of the
crew sees a ship; 2 days later another crew member sees it.  We've
also been having bad luck.  We reach Santiago.  Lots of taverns to
investigate.  We find an old man, Smiling Jack, who sells us for 5$
the information that William Wilks sailed with Besh, boasted of
Spanish treasure, but lost money and couldn't pay.  Smiling Jack leads
us to the gambling house wher Wilks, known as Whistling Willy, is
playing.  He's about to be shot.  Captain Jack Savage walks up to the
shooter and shoots him first, killing him.  His friends weren't
happy.  We kill 3 more, and 1 runs.  Question Whistling Willy.
Cutthroat double-crossed his crew.  Willy had a pine box Besh gave him
that turned out to have a false-bottomed, with a treasure map.  It
looks like Besh hid the treasure on the Isle of Pines.  We head
there.  A day's trek inland.  Come to the location where think
Hobbs/Besh buried the treasure.  Find large pine with H.H. and an
arrow pointing down carved on it, but it's surrounded by fire ants!
Drove the ants out with burning oil.  Takes 3 hours to dig down to 6
large chests with 5000$ each.  Took us several days to transfer the
chests to the ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;+5 XP.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>potsm</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/08/t.a.s-potsm-the-scarlet-rose/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2014 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Béthorm: The Plane of Tékumel</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/06/bthorm-the-plane-of-tkumel/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;My physical copy of &lt;cite&gt;Béthorm: The Plane of Tékumel&lt;/cite&gt; arrived in the
mail today.  It looks good to my quick scan.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>rpg</category><category>tekumel</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/06/bthorm-the-plane-of-tkumel/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2014 23:45:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>T.A.'s PotSM: The Lady's Favor</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/01/t.a.s-potsm-the-ladys-favor/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We played “The Lady's Favor”, the adventure from the back of the
&lt;cite&gt;Pirates of the Spanish Main&lt;/cite&gt; book, so if you haven't played that
you might want to skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — GameMaster&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Capt. Jack Savage, Rowena Blackwood&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCs rescued Virginia Cotton from rowdy pirates.  (+1 Fame) They
escorted her to the Royal Crown Tavern.  Her contact, Knox (???), told
her that her dad Jebidiah was a pirate, to her shock, and that he'd
buried a pirate treasure then got captured, and is being held captive
at the house of Baron Pettigrew.  When Virginia tells him that she
knows nothing of the treasure, he grabs her and tells his two thugs to
attack.  We manage to down Knox and one of the thugs and the other
flees.  We take their weapons and leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decide to sneak into Pettigrew's mansion.  Virginia suggests we
have our ship ready to go, so Capt. Jack gives the orders.  We went to
the mansion after dark and snuck up to the back door.  Sneak into the
kitchen, dining room, through the hall past a maid, and found a
sleeping guard.  We tried to knock the guard out and failed, but
intimidated him and tied him up, got the keys from him, opened the
door and found Jebidiah.  We untied Jebidiah and snuck out with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We agreed to split the treasure and headed off in the ship.  Jack
healed up.  We were trailed by another ship, but managed to give them
the slip.  We arrived at the island, but had to ride out a storm
offshore.  Then we took a longboat ashore, and dug up the treasure.
There were five chests, each containing 500$.  We distributed the
treasure, one chest each to Jebidiah, Virginia, our crew, Rowena, and
Capt. Jack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;+5 XP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>potsm</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/01/t.a.s-potsm-the-ladys-favor/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>