<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about rpg)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/rpg.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 04:19:35 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Traveller</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/22/traveller/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;An interesting &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.irosf.com/q/zine/article/10119"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Traveller_(role-playing_game)"&gt;Traveller&lt;/a&gt;, linked here for later reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christopher Kubasik's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://talestoastound.wordpress.com/tag/traveller-out-of-the-box/"&gt;Traveller Out of the Box&lt;/a&gt; and the rpg.net
thread (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://forum.rpg.net/index.php?threads/traveller-out-of-the-box-only-using-books-1-3.769219/"&gt;R1&lt;/a&gt;) that talks about it, and the &lt;cite&gt;Citizens of the Imperium&lt;/cite&gt;
thread (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.travellerrpg.com/CotI/Discuss/showthread.php?s=f6580820d04fdcca8d9f852002a83ea4&amp;amp;t=35235"&gt;C1&lt;/a&gt;), and a Classic Traveller thread (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.therpgsite.com/showthread.php?41450-Why-I-love-Classic-Traveller-old-school-in-general/page5&amp;amp;highlight=traveller+box"&gt;P1&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Robert Conley's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.batintheattic.com/traveller/"&gt;Classic Traveller Character Generator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>rpg</category><category>traveller</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/22/traveller/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 02:56:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Arduin Grimoire</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/22/arduin-grimoire/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just ran across some discussion of the &lt;cite&gt;Arduin Grimoire&lt;/cite&gt; and am
putting the links here for later reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dmdavid.com/tag/once-subversive-the-arduin-grimoire-reached-into-every-role-playing-game/"&gt;DMDavid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.jonathantweet.com/jotgamearduin.html"&gt;Jonathon Tweet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jrients.blogspot.com/search/label/cover%20to%20cover"&gt;J. Rrients&lt;/a&gt; (and the Arduin &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jrients.blogspot.com/2007/08/great-random-charts-from-rpg-history.html"&gt;Critical Hit Table&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://grandcentralarena.com/under-the-influence-the-arduin-grimoires/"&gt;Ryk E. Spoor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://empcho.bizhosting.com/index.html"&gt;Emperors Choice&lt;/a&gt; still sells some Arduin material.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>arduin</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/22/arduin-grimoire/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 23:07:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Miniatures, battlemats, and terrain at my table</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/miniatures-and-battlemaps-at-my-table/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I started playing with &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; 1E (in 1979 or 1980) we didn't use
miniatures or battle maps, it was all theater of the mind.  Since all
the players I knew personally started with &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; none of us had seen
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chainmail_(game)"&gt;Chainmail&lt;/a&gt; or played miniatures games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I moved on to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DragonQuest"&gt;DragonQuest&lt;/a&gt;, 2nd edition, (in the mid 1980s) where
a hex grid and miniatures was required, I bought a Chessex hex grid
Megamat and wet erase markers.  One of my brothers had bought a box of
miniatures (though for the life of me I cannot remember what company
it was from or what figures it contained).  We used those for player
characters.  For monsters, I cut out a bunch of ¾ inch square blocks
of wood and numbered them on the top side, put a “D” for Dead on the
bottom side, put an “S” on another smooth side for Stunned, and a “U”
for Unconscious, leaving the rough sides (where the wood was cut
against the grain) blank.  I continued to use all these when I moved
over to using &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GURPS"&gt;GURPS&lt;/a&gt; 3rd edition, which also had specific Stunned and
and Unconscious conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much, much later I got the Steve Jackson Games Cardboard Heroes but
never could bear to cut them up, since I wasn't actively playing at
the time it came out (1999 or so?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started playing &lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; again with 3.5E (probably sometime
after 2004) I mostly played and didn't DM.  I was fortunate that the
DMs that I played with had good collections of pre-painted plastic
miniatures for both player characters and monsters from the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Miniatures_Game"&gt;Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons Miniatures Game&lt;/a&gt;.  I did collect some of the Dungeon Tiles
(see &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeon_Tiles"&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dmdavid.com/tag/a-complete-list-and-gallery-of-dungeon-tiles-sets/"&gt;dmdavid&lt;/a&gt;) that Wizards of the Coast published
during this time. (I actually used them playing Savage Worlds.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one campaign that I DMed with 3.5E I bought an Flip Chart/Easel
Pad printed with a 1 inch grid.  I would take several sheets to the
game in a tubular storage container and draw the rooms on the map with
black marker as the players explored.  If we ran off the the side of a
sheet or went to a new level I'd get out another sheet and draw on
that.  This worked surprisingly well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One GM had a fair bit of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dwarvenforge.com/"&gt;Dwarven Forge&lt;/a&gt; terrain and that was a lot
of fun to play on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started playing &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savage_Worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt; (around 2005) I did a lot of
GMing, and was thrilled by the Figure Flats and map tiles that that
Great White Games (now known again as Pinnacle Entertainment Group —
PEG) included in many of their Savage Tales PDF adventures.  I had a
printer that could print on card stock, so these were ideal for
me.  Later PEG products, such as their Plot Point campaigns, often had
Figure Flats as separate PDF accessories.  I found them all very
useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also found the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/51074/eAdventure-Tiles-Introductory-Set"&gt;e-Adventure Tiles&lt;/a&gt; series from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/80/SkeletonKey-Games"&gt;SkeletonKey Games&lt;/a&gt;
very useful.  These &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wiki.roll20.net/Geomorphic_Map_Tiles"&gt;geomorphic map tiles&lt;/a&gt; are 6×6 inch squares, marked
with a 1 inch square grid, and by printing them out and putting them
together you can produce an infinite variety of maps.  I found them
most useful when printed on cardstock and labeled on the back with
their id number.  I'd make up several maps and then sort out the
printed tiles for that map into a manila envelope for easy
retrieval. There used to be a program that you could use the small
preview images from the tiles (which were considerately set up for
easy Copy and Paste from the PDF) to lay out your map at the small
scale and then print it for reference when later putting together the
large tiles. &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/miniatures-and-battlemaps-at-my-table/#tiamat" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; I'd include those in the manila envelope with
the tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used paper miniatures from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/667/Arion-Games"&gt;Arion Games&lt;/a&gt; and Disposable Heroes
paper miniatures from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.pigames.net/store/default.php?cPath=27"&gt;Precis Intermedia&lt;/a&gt;.  I also had &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.nobleknight.com/P/2147348073/Paper-Wars---Dragon-Pass-at-War"&gt;Paper Wars -
Dragon Pass at War&lt;/a&gt;, a collection of Glorantha paper miniatures
published by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rpggeek.com/rpgpublisher/10024/unspoken-word"&gt;The Unspoken Word&lt;/a&gt;, which seem to have been drawn by
Simon Bray, Dario Corallo, and Sarah Evans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the early paper miniatures that I used were tri-fold and were
cut out, folded, and glued (or taped) together.  They usually had
front sides in color and back sides in black and white.
Unfortunately, these take up almost as much room as lead or plastic
miniatures, though were much lighter to carry.  I stored them in cheap
plastic food containers, which let me easily see what was inside them.
Carrying enough of them to games outside my home was a bulky problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually I moved to A-frame paper miniatures, where there are two
sides and they are attached at the top, with tabs that fold out or in
at the bottom for a base.  Instead of relying on the tabs to form the
base, I used plastic &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.pigames.net/store/default.php?cPath=27_96"&gt;stands&lt;/a&gt; from Precis Intermedia, where you'd just
fold the miniature once and stick it in the stand.  The stands add a bit
of weight to the miniatures and make them much more stable.  If you
cut out a front that is attached to a back, instead of all three
sides, you can just fold them once and stick them in a stand as well,
so I could use all my trifold paper miniatures as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://zenseeker.net/PaperMiniatures/DIY.htm"&gt;Zen DIY Paper Miniatures Page&lt;/a&gt; has some pictures of A-frame and
trifold paper miniatures.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since these paper miniatures are flat when not inserted into a stand I
currently organize my paper miniatures into separate small manila
envelopes for each type of creature, labeled with the creature type on
the outside.  Occasionally I use small ziplock bags, especially for
the PCs' miniatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper miniatures described above are all drawn in such a way that
the figure is drawn within a rectangle and you can cut them out with
long straight cuts and cross cuts.  There is another style of paper
miniatures drawn in a manner so that you cut out the irregular outline
of the figure itself with many small or curving cuts.  These are much
harder, and are more difficult to store, but are very impressive to
look at.  (You can see some examples in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://onemonk.com/monsters.html"&gt;Monsters&lt;/a&gt; collection at
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://onemonk.com/"&gt;One Monk Miniatures&lt;/a&gt;)  That's too much work for me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also got a Steel Sqwire Flip Mat, which uses dry erase pens, and it
is 24×30 inches and folds up into an 8×10 inch package only a ¼ inch
thick or so.  Much easier to carry around, since it fits into the same
backpack or messenger bag I use to carry my RPG books and
accessories. &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/miniatures-and-battlemaps-at-my-table/#accessories" id="id4"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; More over, unlike the ones you can find
now published by &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://paizo.com/products/btpy8oto?GameMastery-FlipMat-Basic"&gt;Paizo&lt;/a&gt;, it had both 1 inch squares and 1 inch hexes,
perfect for DragonQuest, GURPS, or The Fantasy Trip, though I've used
mostly the squared side, for Savage Worlds.  The dry erase pens are
much more satisfactory than the wet erase pens.  For some time I
haven't had extra time to lay out locations using paper map tiles, and
the Flip Mat lets me quickly draw out locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I usually use miniatures and a battle map for Savage Worlds
there have been several occasions where I've run games in theater of
the mind style, without any miniatures or battle map.  It takes a
little adapting, but isn't that difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current practice is to use paper miniatures in stands for player
characters and numbered blocks for opponents, with a Flip Mat as the
battle map.  Some times for opponents that take up more than one
square I'll fold over or cut up a 3×5 or 4×6 card and use that,
writing an arrow to indicate which way is the front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, when running &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Basic_Set#1981_revision"&gt;B/X D&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt; or retroclones there of
(like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://goblinoidgames.com/"&gt;Goblinoid Games&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;cite&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/cite&gt; (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Labyrinth_Lord"&gt;L1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/browse/pub/760/Goblinoid-Games/subcategory/2033_6311/Labyrinth-Lord"&gt;L2&lt;/a&gt;), it's &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt;
inspired &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/78523/Advanced-Edition-Companion-Labyrinth-Lord?cPath=2033_6311"&gt;Advanced Edition Companion&lt;/a&gt;, or the book that squashes them
together: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/product/259983/Advanced-Labyrinth-Lord-Dragon-Cover?cPath=2033_6311"&gt;Advanced Labyrinth Lord&lt;/a&gt;, or like &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/"&gt;Necrotic Gnome&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://necroticgnome.com/collections/old-school-essentials"&gt;Old
School Essentials&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://froggodgames.com/product/swords-wizardry-complete-rulebook/"&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry&lt;/a&gt;) it's all theater of the
mind: no miniatures, no battle map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="tiamat"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/miniatures-and-battlemaps-at-my-table/#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;The program that I used was a desktop application rather
than a web-based application, but &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rpgobjects.com/index.php?c=tiamat"&gt;Tiamat the Tile Mapper&lt;/a&gt; is a
similar application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="accessories"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/miniatures-and-battlemaps-at-my-table/#id4"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dice of course; usually I carry a couple of extra
sets for when someone forgets their dice.  For Savage Worlds I
carry several differently colored sets of glass beads (stored in
small ziplock bags). I use blue beads for bennies, white beads for
GM bennies, red beads for wounds, yellow beads for shaken and white
beads again for fatigue.  I've found it helps the players (and
myself) to remember their status if they have physical objects
sitting on their character sheet to remind them.  When playing with
numbered blocks for opponents I put the shaken bead on top of the
block; this really helps when I've got 30 opponents on the table.
I carry a couple of decks of playing cards for Savage Worlds
initiative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>battlemaps</category><category>miniatures</category><category>rpg</category><category>terrain</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/miniatures-and-battlemaps-at-my-table/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 01:17:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Play a character that will work with the other characters!</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/play-a-character-that-will-work-with-the-other-characters/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the article &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dmdavid.com/tag/a-role-playing-game-players-obligation/"&gt;A role-playing game player’s obligation&lt;/a&gt; David
Hartlage of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dmdavid.com/"&gt;DM David&lt;/a&gt; says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a player, your first role-playing obligation is to imagine a
character who can cooperate with rest of the party to achieve the
common goals of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also quotes Gary Gygax:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Always seek to contribute the most to the team’s success. From
the players’ and the PCs’ standpoint any role-playing game is a
group endeavor. Individual success is secondary to the success of
the group, for only through group achievements can the quality of
the campaign be measured.” – Gary Gygax, Role-Playing Mastery&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that in general this is a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, if you are specifically intending to run a game to explore
infighting or where the player characters explicitly have goals that
seriously in conflict, I think that you should make this clear at the
beginning and make sure that everyone is on board.  Moreover, it may
make sense to use an RPG that is specifically designed for that, like
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bullypulpitgames.com/games/fiasco/"&gt;Fiasco&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.indiepressrevolution.com/xcart/Mountain-Witch-PDF.html"&gt;The Mountain Witch&lt;/a&gt; rather than introduce those elements
into a traditional RPG.  Even in a game built for that, make sure
everybody is on the same page.  It turns out badly if one person in
the group playing &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paranoia_(role-playing_game)#Paranoia_XP"&gt;Paranoia&lt;/a&gt; is playing in &lt;strong&gt;Zap&lt;/strong&gt; mode where
troubleshooters open fire on each other with little to no provocation
and another person in is playing in &lt;strong&gt;Straight&lt;/strong&gt; mode which
discourages random firefights and horseplay.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/play-a-character-that-will-work-with-the-other-characters/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 23:28:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Every edition of D&amp;D has specified some things in terms of miniatures</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/every-edition-of-dd-has-specified-some-things-in-terms-of-miniatures/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ran across an interesting article: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160107143330/http://www.advanceddungeonsandparenting.com:80/2012/02/d-next-zones-of-control-from-chainmail.html"&gt;D&amp;amp;D Next: "Zones of Control"
from Chainmail to 4e&lt;/a&gt; which argues, I think with good evidence, that
every version of &lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; has been based in miniatures as its default
mode of play.  (Alas the original site of this article, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.advanceddungeonsandparenting.com"&gt;Advanced
Dungeons &amp;amp; Parenting&lt;/a&gt; appears to having fallen to some annoying
entropy creating demons.  Some poking about seems to show the original
author being Christian Lindke of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.geekeratimedia.com/"&gt;Geekerati&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The split between abstract combat and miniatures combat was well
established by the time I started with &lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt;, reading the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Basic_Set#1977_version"&gt;Holmes&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/every-edition-of-dd-has-specified-some-things-in-terms-of-miniatures/#holmes" id="id4"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; edition and then playing first edition &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Editions_of_Dungeons_%26_Dragons#Advanced_Dungeons_&amp;amp;_Dragons"&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/a&gt;.  We never
played with miniatures.  Indeed, I think the hex grid and miniatures
based tactical combat rules were one of the things that drew me to
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DragonQuest"&gt;DragonQuest&lt;/a&gt; and later &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GURPS"&gt;GURPS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="holmes"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/every-edition-of-dd-has-specified-some-things-in-terms-of-miniatures/#id4"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I'm irritated that &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wizards_of_the_Coast"&gt;Wizards of the Coast&lt;/a&gt; has not yet
added the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons_Basic_Set#1977_version"&gt;Holmes&lt;/a&gt; edition, the 1977 blue box Basic Set,
to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.dmsguild.com/"&gt;DM's Guild&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>ad&amp;d</category><category>d&amp;d</category><category>holmes basic d&amp;d</category><category>miniatures</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/every-edition-of-dd-has-specified-some-things-in-terms-of-miniatures/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 20:27:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Gygax on Character Death</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/gygax-on-character-death/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the article &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dmdavid.com/tag/turning-dd-character-deaths-into-deal-that-benefits-game-and-story/"&gt;Turning Character Deaths in D&amp;amp;D Into Deals that
Benefit Game and Story&lt;/a&gt;, David Hartlage (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dmdavid.com/"&gt;DM David&lt;/a&gt;) points out an
interesting quote from Gary Gygax in the &lt;cite&gt;DMG&lt;/cite&gt; on Character Death.  (The
whole post is worth reading, as are &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://dmdavid.com/tag/start-here-my-most-popular-and-favorite-posts/"&gt;many of his others&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went looking for the quote so I could give a more complete reference
for it.  (PDF versions of old gaming books are wonderful!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first edition &lt;cite&gt;AD&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeon_Master%27s_Guide#Advanced_Dungeons_&amp;amp;_Dragons"&gt;Dungeon Master's Guide&lt;/a&gt;, on p. 110, in the
section “Conducting the Game”, subsection “Rolling the Dice and
Control of the Game”, Gary Gygax wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now and then a player will die through no fault of his own. He or
she will have done everything correctly, taken every reasonable
precaution, but still the freakish roll of the dice will kill the
character. In the long run you should let such things pass as the
players will kill more than one opponent with their own freakish
rolls at some later time. Yet you do have the right to arbitrate
the situation. You can rule that the player, instead of dying, is
knocked unconscious, loses a limb, is blinded in one eye or invoke
any reasonably severe penalty that still takes into account what
the monster has done. It is very demoralizing to the players to
lose a cared-for-player character when they have played well. When
they have done something stupid or have not taken precautions,
then let the dice fall where they may!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a side note, every time I read the original &lt;cite&gt;DMG&lt;/cite&gt; I'm amazed at
everything that Gygax managed to fit into that book.  Of course, when
I read the three booklets of original &lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/cite&gt; I'm amazed at what he
managed to fit in those as well.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>1e</category><category>ad&amp;d</category><category>d&amp;d</category><category>gygax</category><category>od&amp;d</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/20/gygax-on-character-death/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 18:27:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Powers &amp; Perils is Oddly Fascinating</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/14/powers-perils-is-oddly-fascinating/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I bought &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://powersandperils.org/"&gt;Powers &amp;amp; Perils&lt;/a&gt; when it first came out.  While I was
never able to complete building a character, I did have fun reading
the rules and the setting details.  It was oddly fascinating.  So
complicated.  Every so often, I circle back to look at it again,
usually starting at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://powersandperils.org/"&gt;Powers &amp;amp; Perils&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I noticed this time is that a second edition is available on the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://powersandperils.org/books.htm"&gt;rules&lt;/a&gt; page, which includes both a PDF of the complete rules and a
PDF of the &lt;cite&gt;Perilous Lands&lt;/cite&gt; setting information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rules are extensively hyperlinked, both in the table of contents
and in cross-references, which should make using such a complicated
system easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now I can't imaging finding a group that would be interested in
playing &lt;cite&gt;Powers &amp;amp; Perils&lt;/cite&gt;, but there is always a lingering impulse to
do something with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>powers &amp; perils</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/14/powers-perils-is-oddly-fascinating/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 03:15:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>BESM 4E - Initial Look</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/12/besm-4e-initial-look/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I took advantage of the Late Pledges option on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/370924922/besm-fourth-edition-big-eyes-small-mouth-rpg"&gt;BESM 4th
Edition&lt;/a&gt; kickstarter and have access to the PDFs they've released so
far.  It is a further refinement of &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt; with some point costs
re-balanced.  Interestingly, the combat system in the BESM 4E core
book is very, very simple, with only an Attack roll versus a Defence
roll.  And the detailed list of skills from &lt;cite&gt;BESM 2ER&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;
have been replaced with 12 “Skill Groups”, separated into three types
based on how expensive the skill group is, rated by utility.  I'm
hoping that the planned &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/370924922/besm-fourth-edition-big-eyes-small-mouth-rpg/posts/2569713"&gt;BESM Extras&lt;/a&gt; book will include more combat
options and the more detailed skill rules.  (The &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E Character
Folio&lt;/cite&gt; seems to indicate the detailed skills will be in &lt;cite&gt;BESM
Extras&lt;/cite&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;'s switch to roll over, which is continued in &lt;cite&gt;BESM
4E&lt;/cite&gt;. There are 25 race templates and 25 class templates, up from &lt;cite&gt;BESM
3E&lt;/cite&gt;'s 20 each, and 20 Humanoid Companions templates that can easily be
converted into race or class templates. &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt; introduces &lt;em&gt;edges&lt;/em&gt;
and &lt;em&gt;obstacles&lt;/em&gt;, which add 1 (for minor) or 2 (for major) dice to a
roll, keeping the 2 best (for edges) or 2 worst (for obstacles),
similar to &lt;cite&gt;D&amp;amp;D 5E&lt;/cite&gt;'s advantage and disadvantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way Standard and Custom Variables and Restrictions in &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;
worked has changed and been renamed.  They are now Enhancements and
Limiters, and instead of having a character point cost they reduce or
increase the Effective Level of an attribute.  For instance, If you
have bought the Weapon Attribute up to 10 Levels and add the Accurate
Weapon Enhancement (1 assignment) and the Area standard Enhancement
for 10 metres radius (2 assignments) and the Range standard
Enhancement for 100 metres (3 assignments) and Ammo Weapon Limiter for
2-3 shots available (2 assignments) makes the Effective Level 6 (10 -
1 - 2 - 3 + 2).  This makes the cost of Enhancements and Limiters
proportional to the base cost of an Attribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like the point costs for things are one-third to one-quarter
those of &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;, which keeps things a little simpler.  Here are the
suggested power levels:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 47%"&gt;
&lt;col style="width: 53%"&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Power Level&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Character Points&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sub-Human&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-24&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;25-49&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Adventurer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;50-74&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Heroic&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;75-99&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mythical&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;100-149&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Superhuman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;150-199&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Superpowered&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;200-249&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Godlike&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;250+&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a 10 page index, which I was happy to see, but alas the
entries are not hyperlinked.  There are copious cross references by
page number, which is very useful, but again not hyperlinked.  The
table of contents is reasonably detailed, though again not
hyperlinked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt; is firmly in the “GMs should fudge dice rolls if it will
make the game better.”  I'm ambivalent about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an 8-page section on Shojo roleplaying that seems
interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “Anime Multiverse” chapter seems identical between 3E and 4E and
presents an interesting short take on a multiverse cosmology, if you
need one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like &lt;cite&gt;BESM 3E&lt;/cite&gt;, &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt; has lots of colors.  Lots and lots of
colors.  (I can see no reason for one column of text on each page to
have a background color.)  I recognize most of the art from earlier
editions.  I liked it then and still like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a simple character sheet, in color and black-and-white
versions in the PDF of the core rulebook, or for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dyskami.ca/downloads/BESM4_character_sheets.pdf"&gt;download&lt;/a&gt; from the
Dyskami &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dyskami.ca/besm.html"&gt;BESM RPG&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the &lt;cite&gt;Dramatis Personae&lt;/cite&gt; PDFs give 15 example characters, with
backgrounds, personalities, discussion of their Attributes and
Defects, three Adventure Hooks, and a personal quote.  These are
useful in seeing how the various Attributes work.  The backgrounds are
tied into the Anime Multiverse from the core book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I think it looks good.  If the things are in &lt;cite&gt;BESM Extras&lt;/cite&gt;
that I hope are there, I can definitely see switching from &lt;cite&gt;BESM 2ER&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>besm</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/12/besm-4e-initial-look/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 18:13:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Slings in RPGs: Often Nerfed</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/07/slings-in-rpgs-often-nerfed/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In response to reading &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-4541318/Roman-sling-bullets-deadly-44-Magnum.html?fbclid=IwAR2IZhVYW4-4_BcuQDOq2yGXwwurzBd3HNSo1BzN7XUwZLKHF4XZ54yy0VU"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; article, headlined “Roman sling bullets
used against Scottish tribes 2,000 years ago were as deadly as a .44
Magnum”, I was thinking about slings in RPGs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've often thought that sling bullets are woefully nerfed in many
RPGs, especially D&amp;amp;D.  In D&amp;amp;D 5E, for instance, they're only 1d4,
while a short bow is 1d6 and a long bow is 1d8. For comparison,
daggers are 1d4 and longswords are 1d8.  In OD&amp;amp;D using Greyhawk's
“Damage Done by Weapon Type” table sling &lt;em&gt;stones&lt;/em&gt; are 1d4, and the
same in B/X D&amp;amp;D's optional “Variable Weapon Damage” table.  AD&amp;amp;D has
sling &lt;em&gt;bullets&lt;/em&gt; as 1d4+1 and sling &lt;em&gt;stones&lt;/em&gt; as 1d4.  D&amp;amp;D 3.5E has them
as 1d4.  So the D&amp;amp;D editions pretty consistently have it as
1d4. Definitely nerfed.  Except in 3-book OD&amp;amp;D and B/X D&amp;amp;D without the
“Variable Weapon Damage” table, where all weapons did 1d6 damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savage_Worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt; slings are Str+d4, while a bow is 2d6.  For
comparison, a dagger is Str+d4 and a long sword is Str+d8.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RuneQuest"&gt;RuneQuest&lt;/a&gt; 2E they are 1d8, similar to a Composite bow at 1d8+1
and broadsword at 1d8.  In Elric! (a member of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stormbringer_(role-playing_game)"&gt;Stormbringer&lt;/a&gt; line
of games, appearing between 4th Edition and 5th Edition, but the rules
were substantially equivalent to Stormbringer 5E; It is relative of
RuneQuest mechanically, part of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Role-Playing"&gt;Basic Roleplaying (BRP)&lt;/a&gt; family
of games) a sling is 1d8+1, similar to a Desert Recurve Bow at 1d8+2,
and a broadsword at 1d8+1.  So in the BRP games they are not nerfed.
In DragonQuest their Damage Modifier is +1, while a dagger is +0, a
long bow is +4 and a broadsword is +4.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talislanta"&gt;Talislanta&lt;/a&gt; 4E a sling's Damage Rating is 4, as is a dagger, while a
long bow and broadsword are 8.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hero_System"&gt;Hero&lt;/a&gt; 5E, sling damage is 1d6+1, same as a medium bow or a light
long bow, while a medium long bow is 1 ½ d6 (that's 1 and ½ d6)
and a heavy long bow is 2d6.  A dagger is 1d6-1 and a broadsword is
1d6+1.  Note that strong enough characters add damage to this based on
how strong they are. Not nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GURPS#Prior_RPG_history"&gt;GURPS&lt;/a&gt; 4E, damage is based on your strength, and the only dice used is
d6.  We'll use an average Strength 10 character as an example.  Their
Thrust damage is 1d-2 and their Swing damage is 1d. An opponent's
Damage Resistance (DR) is subtracted from the rolled damage and any
damage left is multiplied by a modifier for each type of damage.
Piercing damage has a ×1 modifier, cutting has a ×1.5 modifier, and
impaling has a ×2 modifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, sling damage is swing piercing, and the damage for that for our
average character is 1d.  A longbow is thrust+2 impaling. and the
damage for that is 1d, and whatever makes it past DR is doubled.  A
regular bow is thrust+1 impaling, and the damage for that is 1d+1
(minus DR) ×2.  A dagger is thrust-1 impaling, so that is 1d-3 (minus
DR) ×2.  A thrusting broadsword is swing+1 cutting (1d+1 (minus DR)
×1.5) or thrust+2 impaling (1d+2 (minus DR) ×2).  I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; that's
nerfed a little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I'd like to note that when actually playing GURPS I think this is
simpler to do at the table than it sounds like. The damage values for
each attack is figured out at character creation :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fantasy_Trip"&gt;The Fantasy Trip&lt;/a&gt;, which like GURPS only uses d6, slings do
1d-2, small bows do 1d-1, longbows do 1d+2, daggers do 1d-1, and
broadswords do 2d.  A little bit nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Eyes,_Small_Mouth"&gt;Big Eyes Small Mouth (BESM)&lt;/a&gt; 2nd Edition Revised, slings are not
listed, but a long bow does 5 damage, a longsword does 10 damage, and
a dagger does 5 damage.  In BESM 3rd Edition, an average person has an
Attack Combat Value (ACV) of 4 and a Damage Multiplier of 5.  Each weapon has
a Level, which is multiplied by the Damage Multiplier and added to the
ACV for the final damage.  Slings are Level 1 (1 × 5 + 4 = 9), as are
daggers.  Longbows are Level 3 (3 × 5 + 1 = 16), as are longswords.
Definitely nerfed.  (It is the same in &lt;cite&gt;BESM 4E&lt;/cite&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H%C3%A2rnMaster"&gt;HarnMaster&lt;/a&gt;, weapon impact (damage) for Melee weapons has three
Aspects, Blunt (B), Edge (E), and Point (P).  A dagger's impact is B
1, E 2, P 5, while a broadsword is B 3, E 5, and P 3.  A Missile
weapon's impact depends on the type of missile weapon and the range:
short, medium, long, and extreme.  Slings are Short 4, Medium 3, Long
2, and Extreme 2.  Shortbows are Short 6, Medium 5, Long 4, Extreme 3.
Longbows are Short 8, Medium 8, Long 6, Extreme 5.  Nerfed.  I'll note
that these weapon or missile impacts are added to a Strike Impact is
decided by a table indexed by how well the attacker did on opposed
rolls of attack skill against the defender's skill in Block,
Counterstrike, Dodge, or if the defender ignored the attack. For Melee
attacks this can result in the defender having blocked the attack,
either the attacker or the defender fumbling or stumbling, the
defender gaining a Tactical Advantage (a free action), or either or
both having made a Strike, which generates from 1 to 4 d6s.  For
Missle attacks this can result in a Miss (with a chance to hit an
adjacent combatant, a Wild (a fumble roll), a Block, or a Strike,
which generates from 1 to 3 d6s.  The Armor Protection value is
subtracked and the result is the total Effective Impact, which is then
referenced on the Injury Table to determine where the on the body the
injury is and how serious it is.  There are no Hit Points like D&amp;amp;D or
Wounds like Savage Worlds.  Instead the character accumulates injuries
like “1 Minor Slash Left Upper Arm, 1 injury level”.  The total injury
level determines the difficulty of the character staying conscious and
penalty to any skill roll.  Some of the injuries may immediately kill
the injured character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a good thread by Robert S. Conley (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://batintheattic.blogspot.com/"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.batintheattic.com/index.php"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rpggeek.com/rpgdesigner/22847/robert-conley"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;) on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.rpgpub.com/threads/the-one-where-i-sing-the-praises-of-harnmaster.2363/"&gt;RPG PUB&lt;/a&gt;
that talks some more about HarnMaster combat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In West End Games' &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D6_Fantasy"&gt;D6 Fantasy&lt;/a&gt;, attributes are measured in d6s and 2D
is an average human.  Bow and sling damage and melee damage as d6s
added to a number of d6s determined by your Strength Damage, which is
determined by your Physique attribute or Lifting skill (both measured
in d6s), drop any adds, divided by 2.  So our average human's Strength
Damage is 1D.  Then longbows add +2D+2, shortbows add +1D+2, and
slings add +1D.  For comparison, daggers add +1D and broad/long swords
ad +2D+2.  So, nerfed, although it is hard to make precise
distinctions at this level of resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tunnels_%26_Trolls"&gt;Tunnels &amp;amp; Trolls&lt;/a&gt; only uses d6s and weapons are measured in “Dice +
Adds”, that is the number of d6s to roll and the number of points to
add to the dice total.  The common sling is 2d.  A very light self bow
is 2d, a light self bow is 3d, a medium self bow is 4d, a heavy self
bow is 5d, and a extra-heavy self bow is 6d.  These all have
increasing Strength Required to use the weapon.  For comparison, a
Dirk is 2D+1 and a broadsword is 3d+4.  Nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dragon_Warriors"&gt;Dragon Warriors&lt;/a&gt; weapon damage has two parts: an armor
penetration die (measured in dice: d4, d6, d8, etc.) and damage
points.  The armor penetration die is rolled against the Armour Factor
of the defender's armour: a Gambeson has an Armour Factor of 2 while
Plate has an Armor Factor of 5, and the attacker has to roll &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt;
than the Armour Factor to inflict damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A sling has Damage (d6, 3 points) while a Bow has Damage (d6, 4
points).  For comparison, a dagger has Damage (d4, 3 points) and a
sword has Damage (d8, 4 points).  Slightly nerfed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I GM games that I think nerf slings, like D&amp;amp;D, I often use a
house rule that sling bullets are higher damage than sling stones, and
more similar to the damage of a short bow, 1d6, for example.  I may
have been underestimating them and should consider them closer to a
long bow, 1d8, as Chaosium's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Role-Playing"&gt;Basic Roleplaying (BRP)&lt;/a&gt; variants
(RuneQuest, Elric) do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>d&amp;d</category><category>dragonquest</category><category>rpg</category><category>runequest</category><category>slings</category><category>talislanta</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2020/02/07/slings-in-rpgs-often-nerfed/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Feb 2020 19:40:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ulisses Spiele updates Heliograph Space 1889 pdfs with bookmarks and document outlines</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/07/ulisses-spiele-updates-heliograph-space-1889-pdfs-with-bookmarks-and-document-outlines/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today I got notices from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://ulisses-spiele.de/"&gt;Ulisses Spiele&lt;/a&gt; via &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/"&gt;DriveThruRPG&lt;/a&gt; that
each of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.heliograph.com/"&gt;Heliograph&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space:_1889"&gt;Space 1889&lt;/a&gt; PDFs had been updated, saying:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“An updated PDF with bookmarks and meta information is now available.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm a little surprised to see this at this late date — is there that
much demand for these PDFs?  Still, I'm pleased to get the updates,
and glad there's still interest.  I've never tried the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://rpggeek.com/rpgsystem/742/ubiquity-roleplaying-system"&gt;Ubiquity&lt;/a&gt; based
version, though I‘ve been thinking about buying the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savage_Worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt;
versions of those adventures, but the original system has charms of
its own.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>rpg</category><category>space 1889</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2019/11/07/ulisses-spiele-updates-heliograph-space-1889-pdfs-with-bookmarks-and-document-outlines/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 15:10:36 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>