<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about tekumel)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/tekumel.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 09:33:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Béthorm: The Plane of Tékumel</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/06/bthorm-the-plane-of-tkumel/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;My physical copy of &lt;cite&gt;Béthorm: The Plane of Tékumel&lt;/cite&gt; arrived in the
mail today.  It looks good to my quick scan.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>rpg</category><category>tekumel</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/06/bthorm-the-plane-of-tkumel/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2014 23:45:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>EPT: Way better organization than OD&amp;D</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/06/10/ept-way-better-organization-than-odd/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I've got to say, the organization of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://rpg.drivethrustuff.com/product/2060/Empire-of-the-Petal-Throne"&gt;Empire of the Petal Throne&lt;/a&gt; is
way, way better than the original &lt;cite&gt;Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons&lt;/cite&gt;, even in the
original &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://rpg.drivethrustuff.com/product/99646/Empire-of-the-Petal-Throne-%28Original-Manuscript%29"&gt;manuscript&lt;/a&gt; The art in the published version is better, too.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ept</category><category>od&amp;d</category><category>rpg</category><category>tekumel</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2012/06/10/ept-way-better-organization-than-odd/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2012 04:29:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Triad: OD&amp;D, Tékumel, T&amp;T</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/10/01/triad-odnd-tekumel-tnt/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, for grins and giggles, last time my local gaming group met I
brought copies of the first three commercially published roleplaying
games for show and tell: Original &lt;em&gt;Dungeons and Dragons&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;Empire of the
Petal Throne&lt;/em&gt;; and &lt;em&gt;Tunnels and Trolls&lt;/em&gt;.  (The order of the last two
is debatable.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The release of 4E and the choruses of “It's not real D&amp;amp;D” had actually
interested me in looking back at what D&amp;amp;D really was, so I bought PDFs
of Original D&amp;amp;D (from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rpgnow.com/"&gt;RPGNow&lt;/a&gt;) and its supplements and printed them all
out and bound them in 8.5”x5” pamphlets, in more or less the original
form factor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listening to the Whartson Hall Gamers playing &lt;em&gt;Empire of the Petal
Throne&lt;/em&gt; from the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rpgmp3.com/"&gt;RPGMP3&lt;/a&gt; Community Podcast rekindled my interesting in
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tekumel.com/"&gt;Tékumel&lt;/a&gt;, so I bought a PDF of it from RPGNow and printed it.  (This
really drove home how much bigger and better presented EPT was than
OD&amp;amp;D.  Also, how even less Politically Correct it was.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tunnels_and_Trolls"&gt;T&amp;amp;T&lt;/a&gt; had been in my thoughts since Ron Edwards' wrote a series
of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.indie-rpgs.com/viewtopic.php?t=6272"&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.indie-rpgs.com/viewtopic.php?t=6355"&gt;on&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.indie-rpgs.com/viewtopic.php?t=7104"&gt;his&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.indie-rpgs.com/viewtopic.php?t=7863"&gt;T&amp;amp;T&lt;/a&gt; game.  I played T&amp;amp;T a bit in my youth,
so I already had a copy of it, the 5th edition, so I let that stand in
for the 1st edition, a not unreasonable bit of flexibility, since T&amp;amp;T
seems to have changed much less over five editions than D&amp;amp;D did over
4.5 or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Later: I can't imagine why I didn't bring my copy of FFE/QLI's
republication of the original Traveller Books 1, 2, and 3 along, and
have one of the first SF RPGs too!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>d&amp;d</category><category>gaming</category><category>t&amp;t</category><category>tekumel</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/10/01/triad-odnd-tekumel-tnt/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2008 04:50:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Recent Reading; S&amp;S RPGing; Tékumel RPGing</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2005/03/05/2005-03-05/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="section" id="recent-reading"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recent Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Witherwing&lt;/em&gt;, by David Jarret; Warner Books, September 1979.  This is
one of those books that is more interesting for the glimpses of the
underpinnings of the setting than for anything that the characters do
or that happens to them. Enjoyable in an abstract way, for someone
interested in Swords &amp;amp; Sorcery fiction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="swords-sorcery-roleplaying"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Sorcery Roleplaying&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;em&gt;Witherwing&lt;/em&gt; because, like Gardener F. Fox's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2005/02/21/2005-02-21-recent-reading-and-viewing/#kothar"&gt;Kothar&lt;/a&gt;, it was in the
reading list of Swords &amp;amp; Sorcery books in the &lt;em&gt;Sorcerer &amp;amp; Sword&lt;/em&gt;
supplement for the &lt;em&gt;Sorcerer&lt;/em&gt; roleplaying game, both which were
written by Ron Edwards. It was listed as one of the references for the
“Mutant-Future” example setting. &lt;em&gt;Sorcerer &amp;amp; Sword&lt;/em&gt; (as is typical
of &lt;em&gt;Sorcerer&lt;/em&gt; and its supplments) approaches Swords &amp;amp; Sorcery very
differently from most roleplaying games: it concentrates on the
original Swords &amp;amp; Sorcery authors (for instance, it considers only
those &lt;em&gt;Conan&lt;/em&gt; stories actually written by Robert E. Howard, which by
now is probably the smaller part of the &lt;em&gt;Conan&lt;/em&gt; series), includes RPG
mechanics only for things that can't be handled by concepts from other
RPGs, ignores the loot and level basis of the widespread monster-
killing style of roleplaying, &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2005/03/05/2005-03-05/#id3" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt; and only including things that will
be directly useful in play. This later means, for instance, that there
is no detailed, specific background material included, since it takes
than stance that most of that material is never used in play. Instead,
there are examples of starting with a minimal setting and creating the
details during play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, I thoroughly recommend &lt;em&gt;Sorcerer &amp;amp; Sword&lt;/em&gt; for anyone who
is playing grim, intense, Swords &amp;amp; Sorcery-based roleplaying games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as source material for “Mutant-Future” games, &lt;em&gt;Witherwing&lt;/em&gt; is
full of ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="tekumel-roleplaying"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tékumel Roleplaying&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've read more of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.guardiansorder.com/"&gt;Guardians of Order&lt;/a&gt;'s new &lt;em&gt;Tékumel: Empire of the
Petal Throne&lt;/em&gt; roleplaying game and it is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; good. I've noticed a
few typos so far, but nothing serious, and the game itself seems
pretty clearly explained. Moreover, the world background material is
very good. The old &lt;em&gt;Swords and Glory&lt;/em&gt;, Volume 1, the &lt;em&gt;Tékumel
Sourcebook&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2005/03/05/2005-03-05/#id4" id="id2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; still has more detailed information, but the new game
provides a distilled essence that provides enough detail for newcomers
to understand Tékumel and have some idea of how to play a character
from the setting. It concentrates on Tsolyánu, which is the area of
Tékumel on which we have the most information, and has information
for the more common non-human races as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mechanically, the system is derived from the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.guardiansorder.com/"&gt;Guardians of Order&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.guardiansorder.com/games/tristat/"&gt;Tri-Stat&lt;/a&gt;
game system,
although it uses 1d10 instead of 2d6 or 2d&lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt;, and it uses 6
stats, instead of 3. The list of attributes available to starting
characters has been simplified and specialized for Tékumel and the
skills list has been expanded and specialized for Tékumel. Magic is
handled separately with a system that seems to capture the flavor of
Tékumel's ritual and spell-based magic very well. Character creation
includes those social aspects that dominate Tsolyánu culture: clans
and careers in the legions, temples, or government, as well as an
extensive subsytem for dealing with resources, a subject which can be
complicated in Tsolyánu since property tends to be owned by the clan
rather than individuals, as well as smaller subsystems for dealing
with teamwork, respect, and favors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I'd say the game is somewhat crunchier than BESM (there are
stat requirements for weapons and some careers, and spells can have
multiple levels with different enhancements and various specialties),
but much, mucher lighter than &lt;em&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Glory&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Garásiyal&lt;/em&gt;, or 3rd
edition &lt;em&gt;Dungeons and Dragon&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Verdict so far: the new game makes me want to play &lt;em&gt;Tékumel: Empire
of the Petal Throne&lt;/em&gt;, and provides the right material so that it's
possible to see how to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="id3"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2005/03/05/2005-03-05/#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;This does not mean, as some have assumed, that the author is
against loot and level gaming: he elsewhere praises &lt;em&gt;T&amp;amp;T&lt;/em&gt;, which is
one of the most loot and level based games of all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="id4"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2005/03/05/2005-03-05/#id2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which is still available from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tekumel.com/tita"&gt;Tita's House of Games&lt;/a&gt;, by the way, and well worth it for
the Tékumel aficionado.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>old blog</category><category>recent reading</category><category>tekumel</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2005/03/05/2005-03-05/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Mar 2005 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>I got Tékumel: Empire of the Petal Throne!</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2005/03/02/2005-03-02/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I got my copy of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.guardiansorder.com/"&gt;Guardians of Order&lt;/a&gt;'s new roleplaying game,
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.guardiansorder.com/games/tekumel/"&gt;Tékumel: Empire of the Petal Throne&lt;/a&gt;. This is the first
time since the original TSR Tékumel roleplaying game that there has
been an edition of the game that was complete and playable in one
book. While I haven't had time to read it completely I've skimmed
through it and it looks very good.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>old blog</category><category>rpg</category><category>tekumel</category><category>tekumel: empire of the petal throne</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2005/03/02/2005-03-02/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2005 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Consistent Game Worlds and Levels of Detail</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/04/14/2003-04-14/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is easier to create a consistent game world if it is not too
detailed, and it is arguably easier to start playing in such a world,
since each roleplaying game group will create their own vision of the
world with their own details, and will feel a greater connection to
the world and it's unfolding history.  However, if game play generates
additional detail (as opposed to simply generating new history) then
inconsitences can arise.  This is not a problem for gamers who don't
care about details at all, but most care at least a little about the
details: they don't want taverns to switch from one side of the river
to another, for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When gaming in more detailed worlds, the gamers have to expend more
effort up front to work within the details: learning how &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tekumel.com/"&gt;Tékumel&lt;/a&gt; societies work, or the religions of the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.glorantha.com/library/history/hle-0wane.html"&gt;Lunar Empire&lt;/a&gt; of Glorantha, but the additional detail can add depth
to the roleplaying experience and can provide additional inspiration
for the game.  How can such detail be best presented to prevent the
gamer from becoming overloaded and turned away by the detail? Is it
possible to present things in such a way that there is as little up
front work for the gamer to start playing in a detailed world as an
undetailed world, and can the continuing effort of working within the
details be kept close to the level of effort required to play in an
undetailed world?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>glorantha</category><category>old blog</category><category>tekumel</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/04/14/2003-04-14/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2003 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>