<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about tiles)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/tiles.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 19:01:24 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Gaming Weekend: 2008/07/20: The Eternal Nazi</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/20/gaming-weekend-2008-07-20-the-eternal-nazi/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;section id="savage-worlds"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I ran &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/Downloads/SWEX/Eternal%20Nazi.pdf"&gt;“The Eternal Nazi”&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/pages/roleplaying-games-played-with-the-kids/#savage-worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt; pulp one-sheet
for them.  Like many of the one-sheets, it didn't come with a map, so
I made one a couple of nights before using printable PDF tiles.  The
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt; had fun, but I can see why Kator the Ape Boy wasn't in the most
recent pregenerated pulp characters download intended for use with
“The Eternal Nazi”: as the sole melee-only character he was at a serious
disadvantage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this was actually the first time I've used modern weapons in
Savage Worlds.  It went ok, although I did forget each shot on
auto-fire counts as three bullets expended.  I think I'll add some
grenades to the PCs gear the next time I run it, suggest the PCs other
than Buck pick up some of the germain submachine guns, and up the
number of extras with the big bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- and make sure to set up a situation with strafing? --&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>one-sheet</category><category>pulp</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>tiles</category><category>tools</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/20/gaming-weekend-2008-07-20-the-eternal-nazi/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2008 05:00:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaming Weekend: 2008/07/20: Toon &amp; Savage Worlds: Reflections</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/20/gaming-weekend-2008-07-20-part2/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;section id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was trying out some new technology (for me): using printable
PDF tiles from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.skeletonkeygames.com/"&gt;Skeleton Key Games&lt;/a&gt; (SKG) for the battle mats.  I
especially like the SKG tiles for a couple of reasons.  First, the
tile graphics in the PDF files can be easily extracted (just
right-click and choose copy) and munged to produce custom tiles.
Secondly, the tile sets include thumbnail catalogs of the tiles, which
can easily be extracted and added to the tilesets of programs like
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dungeonmapping.com/df/public_html/"&gt;DungeonForge&lt;/a&gt;.  This makes it a lot easier to design the map layouts
to begin with (virtual tile flipping replaces physical tile flipping)
and makes it easy to produce small scale maps for reference for laying
out the tiles on the table by exporting the maps from DungeonForge as
&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;.PNG&lt;/code&gt; files and adding labels with the tile numbers with the GIMP.
(This is especially useful when using wilderness tiles!)  On the
printed tiles I wrote the tile number on the back, again to make
things easier when laying them out on the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the tiles worked pretty well.  The worst problem was that the
tiles tended to curve up at the edges, a common problem with cardstock
printed on inkjet printers: as the large surface area of ink dries the
edges curl up.  This didn't prevent their use, and curling them in the
opposite direction before laying them out helped, but I think I'll try
laminating them and see if that helps.  My first map designs using the
tiles were not as interesting as I wanted, but the tiles themselves
looked good and worked pretty well.  The &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt; occasionally dislodged
the tiles a little, but that was easily fixed, and once while dealing
initiative cards I accidently slide one under the tiles, which got a
laugh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we played I redesigned the maps to give a more dynamic
environment, since I'm planning on running “The Eternal Nazi” for
another other gaming group.  I got a couple more of the SKG sets, and
used GIMP to make three custom tiles.  This let me make a much more
interesting environment.  Part of the problem I had with designing the
map in the first place was inexperience with the tiles, but part was
because the tile sets I had were heavily slanted towards fantasy, and
I was constructing something more out of the “lost race” pulp
adventure stories, set in the 1940s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that I'd like to see is a bunch of tiles with items that
could be dropped on top of other tiles, like piles of metal barrels
and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dungeonmapping.com/df/public_html/"&gt;DungeonForge&lt;/a&gt; has a couple of annoying bugs, but it's free and works
well enough, as long as I remember to save often and not put tiles
against the edges of the map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Todo: I'll try to edit more actual play details into this post when I've got a
moment and my notes are handy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>one-sheet</category><category>pulp</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>tiles</category><category>tools</category><category>toon</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/20/gaming-weekend-2008-07-20-part2/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2008 05:00:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaming Weekend: 2008/07/20: Toon &amp; Savage Worlds</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/20/gaming-weekend-2008-07-20-part1/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;On Sunday we continuing the weekend of gaming, with L.B., D.B., T.A.,
E.A., and M.A. attending again.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>one-sheet</category><category>pulp</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>tiles</category><category>tools</category><category>toon</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/20/gaming-weekend-2008-07-20-part1/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jul 2008 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>