<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about timewarp)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/timewarp.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2020 19:07:29 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Christmas shopping online in 2011</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/12/20/christmas-shopping-online-2011/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I did most of my Christmas shopping online again this year.  Very
convenient.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>timewarp</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2011/12/20/christmas-shopping-online-2011/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2011 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tomb of the Iron God, Session #1</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/10/10/s001-s-n-w/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing &lt;em&gt;Tomb of the Iron God&lt;/em&gt;, so if you haven't
played that you might want to skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a little bit of time to play, but not all our usual players
were available, so we rolled up &lt;cite&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry&lt;/cite&gt; characters, and
started down into the &lt;strong&gt;Tomb of the Iron God&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B., the Dungeon Master&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.B., playing (with T.K.B.'s help)
- Red Gorm, a human fighter&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A., playing
- Bub, a male human cleric, soon surnamed the Naked for skinny dipping
- Cedric, a male human fighter&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A., playing
- Nameless, a male human magic-user
- Wolfgar, a male human fighter&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A., playing
- Errin' (as in erring), a female human fighter with a 3 INT
- Bob-Jo, a female human magic user&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="bathing-and-blood"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bathing and Blood&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E.A. had fun playing an immensely strong character with no sense at
all, clearing the steps down to the first level with ease, but taking
no care to avoid her comrades when flinging the boulders up out of the
stairs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were suitably creeped by out the goblin head in the entrance room,
but eventually moved on through the door to the left, and entered the
first room.  There M.A. decided he was going to bathe in the fountain,
and stripped down to nothing and splashed about.  The splashing and
the resultant argument attracted the attention of a couple of striges
resting in a large crack up near the ceiling, and before it was over
Bub was jumping around in combat naked and and Nameless was down to 1
hit point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that Bub got back into his clothes and armor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that was all we had time for that afternoon.  Everybody seemed to
have fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>gaming</category><category>rpg</category><category>spoilers</category><category>swords &amp; wizardry</category><category>timewarp</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/10/10/s001-s-n-w/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2009 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Keep on the Borderlands, a Labyrinth Lord Campaign</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/04/24/ll-campaign/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have decided I'm going to run some classic &lt;em&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/em&gt; modules this summer
for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;.  I'd actually planned on using &lt;em&gt;Rules Cyclopedia
Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons&lt;/em&gt;, but unfortunately I'd not yet bought the PDF for
it when Wizards of the Coast took all their PDFs off the market,
saying they were “saving the RPG industry from pirates.”  &lt;strong&gt;Jerks.&lt;/strong&gt;
These days I pretty much have to have a PDF of a game I'm going to
run, so, instead of &lt;em&gt;RC D&amp;amp;D&lt;/em&gt;, we're playing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.goblinoidgames.com/labyrinthlord.htm"&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/a&gt;, a
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/pages/rpg-vocabulary/#retro-clone"&gt;retro-clone&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;em&gt;Basic/Expert D&amp;amp;D&lt;/em&gt;.  This has some advantages over RC
anyway: there is a free PDF, it's actually in print through &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lulu.com"&gt;Lulu&lt;/a&gt;, and
several adventures have been published for it recently.  I'd
considered using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.swordsandwizardry.com/"&gt;Swords &amp;amp; Wizardry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to run &lt;em&gt;B10 — Night's Dark Terror&lt;/em&gt;, which I think is one of
the classic &lt;em&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/em&gt; modules, but I didn't want to start with it — it's a
module for 2nd level characters, and I wanted to get a feel for how
&lt;em&gt;LL&lt;/em&gt; ran, since it has been over 20 years since I last ran a pre-3.5E
&lt;em&gt;D&amp;amp;D&lt;/em&gt; game.  So, I'm going to start with a different module, and then
either move the characters on to &lt;em&gt;B10&lt;/em&gt;, or have them create new
characters.  I'm not sure if I'm going to run &lt;em&gt;B2 — Keep on the
Borderlands&lt;/em&gt; or one of the &lt;em&gt;LL&lt;/em&gt; adventures yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to have the kids roll up two characters each, inspired by a
&lt;em&gt;OD&amp;amp;D&lt;/em&gt; (or is it &lt;em&gt;BD&amp;amp;D&lt;/em&gt; — sometimes it's hard to tell) character sheet
(landscape, double-sided) with two character sheets on it
side-by-side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've printed up the character creation sections of &lt;em&gt;LL&lt;/em&gt; and some &lt;em&gt;LL&lt;/em&gt;
reference sheets I found online, so each kid will their own booklet to
use during character creation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/05/03/after-the-fact/"&gt;after-the-fact&lt;/a&gt; entry; I could have sworn I'd written something
about this already, but if so I've lost it.  Sigh.]&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>b2</category><category>character generation</category><category>d&amp;d</category><category>gaming</category><category>keep on the borderlands</category><category>labyrinth lord</category><category>rpg</category><category>timewarp</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/04/24/ll-campaign/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2009 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Return to Alusia, Part 5</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/12/23/return-to-alusia-part-5/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;We played part 5 of an adventure that returned to the setting of a
campaign I ran in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/pages/alusia-campaign/"&gt;Frontiers of Alusia&lt;/a&gt; from 1985 to 1994.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't found my notes for this session yet, but we did finally
finish the adventure, with much loot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/07/new-blog-first-post/"&gt;timewarp&lt;/a&gt; post, and the date is just a wild guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>alusia</category><category>kids</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>timewarp</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/12/23/return-to-alusia-part-5/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2008 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Secret of Smuggler's Cove</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/05/smugglers-cove-2008-07-05/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smuggler's Cove, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/"&gt;PEG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday after the 4th I ran another &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt; game for the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;.  This time it was “The Secret of Smuggler's Cove”, lightly
adapted for the &lt;em&gt;Savage Worlds: Explorer's Edition&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;L.B., playing Amy and Josiah&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A., playing Billy and David&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A., playing Catherine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A., playing Devlin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCs in this adventure are all kids, and T.A. wasn't any too happy
that none of the characters had any weapons more effective than a
slingshot!  Still, they all had fun with the first two sections of the
adventure.  In the first they raced small sailboats, and they managed
to split the characters up so that all the characters run by the two
boys were in one boat and all the characters run by the two girls were
in the other boat, and each had fun taunting and distracting the
others.  I ran it as a chase and let good taunts and distractions
affect the &lt;em&gt;Boating&lt;/em&gt; rolls of the two captains, and I let every
&lt;em&gt;success&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;raise&lt;/em&gt; on the &lt;em&gt;Boating&lt;/em&gt; roll move the boat one range
increment forward &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/05/smugglers-cove-2008-07-05/#chase-and-ranges" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, which may not be strictly by
the book, but did allow for dramatic changes in position.  The girls
won on the last &lt;em&gt;Boating&lt;/em&gt; roll, and then it was time to eat a picnic
lunch.  They observed the thug hide the map and papers, dug them up,
figured out the notes were in German, reburied them, followed the man
who picked them up back to Rydel Mount &amp;amp; figured out that he was the
gardener, headed back home (very, very, late), saw the Gypsies cooking
fire beyond the old Roman fort &amp;amp; traipsed over to see what was
happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- There are notes on what bennies each character has in my “Current
Gaming” notebook.  I have no idea where the character sheets and
figure flats are, though. --&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/07/new-blog-first-post/"&gt;timewarp&lt;/a&gt; post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="chase-and-ranges"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/05/smugglers-cove-2008-07-05/#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think the actual rules move a range increment
only for a &lt;em&gt;success&lt;/em&gt; and the first &lt;em&gt;raise&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>kids</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>spoilers</category><category>timewarp</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/05/smugglers-cove-2008-07-05/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2008 03:25:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Recent Reading: Heinlein</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/05/recent-reading-heinlein/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I recently decided that I need to read Heinlein's juvenile novels.
I'd read some of them in my youth (thanks to the Weston and Clarksburg
public libraries), but not all, and I wondered how they would stand up
in the 21st century to my middle-aged eyes, and how interesting they
might be to younger eyes as well.   (I'll have to wait a bit to see
the later, though.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, inexpensive compilations published by the Science Fiction
Bookclub are easily available from online sellers, and I got four
volumes that include all the juveniles, as well as &lt;cite&gt;Starship
Troopers&lt;/cite&gt;.  &lt;cite&gt;Four Frontiers&lt;/cite&gt; is the first of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Four Frontiers&lt;/cite&gt;, by Robert A. Heinlein; First Science Fiction Book
Club printing: June 2005.  Published by arrangement with “The
Robert A. &amp;amp; Virginia Heinlein Prize Trust” and “The Robert A. &amp;amp;
Virginia Heinlein Library Foundation”, and Tor Books, and The
Berkley Publishing Group, a division of Penguin Group (USA) Inc.
ISBN 0-7394-5345-9.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Rocket Ship Galileo&lt;/cite&gt;, copyright 1947 by Robert A. Heinlein,
copyright renewed 1974 by Robert A. Heinlein, Copyright 1988 by
the Robert A. &amp;amp; Virginia Heinlein Library Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had never read this one.  As you might expect, the earliest is
the roughest, and probably the least interesting to current crop
of juveniles.  It's still a fun adventure story, though current
social mores would have made it impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Space Cadet&lt;/cite&gt;, copyright 1948 by Robert A. Heinlein,
copyright renewed 1975 by Robert A. Heinlein, Copyright 1988 by
the Robert A. &amp;amp; Virginia Heinlein Library Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't remember reading this one, but may have.  It's interesting
how much of this is about learning to deal with others, which
moves from dealing with other cadets to, eventually, dealing with
aliens.  Knowledge, brains, and morals win out over brains, money,
and greed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Red Planet&lt;/cite&gt;, copyright 1949 by Robert A. Heinlein,
copyright renewed 1976 by Robert A. Heinlein, Copyright 2003 by
the Robert A. &amp;amp; Virginia Heinlein Library Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm almost positive that I'd read this one, but if so I'd
forgotten how subversive it was.  And I love the skating, for some
reason.  (I don't skate myself.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Farmer in the Sky&lt;/cite&gt;, copyright 1950 by Robert A. Heinlein,
copyright renewed 1977 by Robert A. Heinlein, Copyright 2003 by
the Robert A. &amp;amp; Virginia Heinlein Library Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This situation on earth in this one, sadly, looks more and more
likely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a fair amount of discussion of the actual technology of space
travel and related planetary science in these first four books, and
that's probably what has aged the worst.  The adventures are still
fun, and I think an open-minded juvenile could still enjoy them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/07/new-blog-first-post/"&gt;timewarp&lt;/a&gt; post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>heinlein</category><category>recent reading</category><category>science fiction</category><category>timewarp</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/05/recent-reading-heinlein/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2008 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Return to Alusia, part 4</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/04/return-to-alusia-part-4/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div class="section" id="introduction"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the games I ran over the holiday continued a &lt;em&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/em&gt;
adventure that I started at Christmas 2007.  The adventure is set in
the &lt;em&gt;Frontiers of Alusia&lt;/em&gt; sometime during the later stages of my
original &lt;em&gt;Frontiers of Alusia&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;DragonQuest&lt;/em&gt; campaign, but set away
from the scenes and characters of that earlier series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="prehistory"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prehistory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December 2007 I was looking for an adventure to run for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt; at
the family get-together at Christmas.  I'd been looking at my notes
from my old &lt;em&gt;Frontiers of Alusia&lt;/em&gt; campaign and decided it would be
neat to revisit &lt;em&gt;Alusia&lt;/em&gt; since my brother, one of the players in my
original &lt;em&gt;Alusia&lt;/em&gt; campaign &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/04/return-to-alusia-part-4/#no-alusia-supplements" id="id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, would be in for
Christmas and would probably be playing with the kids.  Of course,
instead of using &lt;em&gt;DragonQuest&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;GURPS&lt;/em&gt;, the systems I'd used in the
original campaign, I wanted to use &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt;, especially since I
was giving all the kids who were old enough copies of &lt;em&gt;Savage Worlds:
Explorer's Edition&lt;/em&gt; that Christmas.  I decided to reuse &lt;em&gt;The Tomb
of Aghyar&lt;/em&gt;, an adventure I'd written for another group that had
adventured for a short time in my version of &lt;em&gt;The Frontiers of
Alusia&lt;/em&gt;, and have my original group's characters feature prominently
in the city's gossip but not actually appear in the adventure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took the map I drew for the original adventure, added some more
rooms, worked up &lt;em&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/em&gt; stats for the opposition (borrowing
from &lt;em&gt;Noble Deceit&lt;/em&gt; for some thieves guild types), and printed out
copies of the pre-generated characters from &lt;em&gt;Against the Orcs&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;Noble Deceit&lt;/em&gt; for the players to choose from, and off we went.  It
went well, my brother was pleasantly surprised when he figured out
what was happening, and everybody had fun being chased by the Thieves
Guild, figuring out where the tomb was located, and finally venturing
into the tomb itself.  As is not uncommon when playing with the kids
we didn't finish the adventure that evening, and so had to wait for
the next time my brother and his family were in town to continue it.
My nephew from out-of-state repeated mentioned how he was looking
forward to playing “those games with dice” when he came back for the
summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="revamp"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Revamp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the summer 2008 visit.  The night before we played I
decided to remap the dungeon and redo the encounters to add a bit more
zing.  I was interested by D&amp;amp;D 4E's increased emphasis on encounters
with more dynamic aspects, having followed some of the Internet
discussions and read &lt;em&gt;H1 – Keep on the Shadowfell&lt;/em&gt;, and wanted to see
what I could do with &lt;em&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/em&gt; to make encounters be more
dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wizards.com/"&gt;Wizards of the Coast&lt;/a&gt; sells &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wizards.com/default.asp?x=products/dndacc/0786943483"&gt;Dungeon Tiles&lt;/a&gt;, heavy cardboard
&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/04/return-to-alusia-part-4/#real-cardboard" id="id2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt; tiles with pretty dungeon and outdoor scenes marked
off in 1 inch squares.  They've also released similar tiles in the D&amp;amp;D
Basic Game sets in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a browser-based Javascript program called &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.jailoco.net/jai.hordelings/dungeontilesmapper.htm"&gt;Dungeon Tiles
Mapper&lt;/a&gt; that lets you design dungeons by dragging and dropping the
pictures of the tiles from all those sets onto a grid.  It lets you
print off pictues of the dungeons you've created along with a list of
the tiles needed to build it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I download the program and spend some time fiddling with it.
It has some quirks and some outright bugs, but overall it is very
useful.  I was able to make a more interesting dungeon layout pretty
easily.  I then spent some time rethinking the encounters, looking for
ways to make them more dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play-part-1"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play, Part 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first room I changed the least.  I already had an WC ooze and a
fire trap, but I added a vicious bug swarm in a pile of skulls in one
corner near the entrance.  When they looted the pile of skulls they
disturbed the swarm and after a couple of rounds where the two looters
failed to stop the swarm and the swarm failed to damage the looters,
everybody moved away to the other side of the room while one of them
used &lt;em&gt;fear&lt;/em&gt; to send the swarm scurrying.  Of course, in the process
they moved into the area of the ooze, which was actually dispersed
under the dirt floor of the room.  It oozed up through and around
their legs, and they had to make &lt;em&gt;Strength&lt;/em&gt; rolls to break free while
the ooze got to try to completely envelope one of them and all had a
chance of being damgaged by the acid ooze around their legs.  They
managed to break free, and one got off a lucky shot with their
crossbow, &lt;em&gt;acing&lt;/em&gt; their &lt;em&gt;Shooting&lt;/em&gt; roll and then &lt;em&gt;acing&lt;/em&gt; the damage
roll so high I ruled that the shot hit the plum-sized brain of the
creature and killed it outright.  After that they searched the room,
avoiding the depression left by the ooze erupting from the floor and
the acidic liquid left by the dying ooze, and finally found a secret
door out.  Unfortunately, the rogue set off the trap on the door, a
fire blast, and caught fire and fell back into the remains ooze,
setting it on fire in turn.  Now they had to hurry to rescue him and
leave the room before the burning ooze rendered it unihabitable.  They
left through the new tunnel, which lead a few feet to a a shaft down
to another short corridor that opened up into a larger room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's where we broke for lunch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="actual-play-part-2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play, Part 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After lunch we switched play to a different house (mine, just next
door), and one of the younger players, M.A., wanted to play.  I had a
character sheet he could use &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/04/return-to-alusia-part-4/#spare-sheets" id="id6"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;, so on the spur of the
moment I added a mystical column of light in the next room as a prison
where the adventurers would find his new character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That room was much larger, but I'd set it up with with a pool in the
middle that took up much of the room, and around several of the walls
were a number of alcoves.  When I added the mystical column of light,
I put it on a short circular pedestal on a square base in the middle
of the pool.  The PCs could easily jump (not even requiring a roll)
from the six-inch tall lip around the pool to the base, but could only
balance and move around the base with difficulty.  An early experiment
with poking the column of light with an unlit torch destroyed the
torch and revealed that the rather-more-viscous-than-water liquid in
the pool was very caustic.  Cautious investigation by T.B.'s combat mage
revealed the proper method of manually disabling the mystic column,
and after some careful manipulations by T.A.'s rogue, M.A.'s new PC, a
paladin of the Holy Light, was with the group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While improvising a description of his &lt;span class="target" id="cuirbouilli-armor"&gt;cuirbouilli armor&lt;/span&gt; during the
initial get-to-know-you conversation the serendipitous juxtaposition
of my description of a design on his armor and a &lt;em&gt;aced&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Smarts&lt;/em&gt; roll
by L.B., who was playing a priestess of the Holy Light, inspired me to
add to the new paladin's backstory that he was the &lt;em&gt;last&lt;/em&gt; living
paladin of the Holy Light, imprisoned here in agony for — his captors
thought — all eternity as punishment by the pirates who destroyed the
last stronghold of the order of the Paladins of the Holy Light, and
who it was thought had killed last Paladin of the Holy Light.  L.B.'s
priestess informed the rest of the group of the paladin's identity and
his importance, and several of the players immediately assumed the
paladin would set about reforming the Order of the Paladins of the
Holy Light.  M.A. thought all this was neat.  (He's 6, BTW.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During all of this the PCs had dispersed around the room, and it was
at this point that they finally noticed that the liquid in the pool
had become very agitated, with waves as tall as a man, and suddenly it
was flinging globs of acidic gloop at them.  Several were hit, some
were injured, and one had his precious chainmail damaged by the gloop.
Luckily, they had the example of the earlier ooze's remains catching
on fire and had plenty of oil, and proceeded to set the gloop pool
ablaze, which quickly killed it, to my dismay. &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/04/return-to-alusia-part-4/#ooze-wc" id="id7"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just before the beginning of the glooping, B.B.'s fighter made a
&lt;em&gt;Notice&lt;/em&gt; roll and figured out that the dusty cobwebs in the alcoves at
both ends of the room concealed leathery corpses.  He wanted to start
stabbing the corpse in each alcove before moving on to the next.
Knowing that this would simply bring the corpses out to fight him as
he moved toward the alcove I decided it would be better to charge a
“Divine Inspiration” tax and take one of his &lt;em&gt;Bennies&lt;/em&gt; and tell him it
was a &lt;strong&gt;bad&lt;/strong&gt; idea, so they didn't end up fighting the eighteen
zombies at the same time as the &lt;em&gt;Wild Card&lt;/em&gt; gloop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as soon as they opened the door out of the room, the eighteen
zombies came out to attack.  Since B.B.'s fighter had noticed the
corpses earlier and warned the others of the alcoves' contents I gave
them a &lt;em&gt;Notice&lt;/em&gt; role with a bonus, so they had a round to decide where
they would be when the zombies actually attacked.  Most lined up at
the end of the room with the door out, but D.B.'s dwarven fighter
moved back halfway through the room, planing to get a first shot at
the ones coming from the other side with his crossbow, then switch to
his axe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was M.A.'s paladin's turn to shine: he got the Joker for initiative
early in the fight and proceeded to &lt;em&gt;ace&lt;/em&gt; his &lt;em&gt;Fighting&lt;/em&gt; roll &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;ace&lt;/em&gt; his damage roll.  I decided that the return of the
Last Paladin of the Holy Light to the world and his almost immediate
return to the fight against Darkness was such a momentous occasion
that he had been inspired by the Holy Light and began to glow and his
sword, swung for the first time in over 200 years, cut through the
heads of the three nearest zombies even before they had completely
left the alcoves.  The paladin retained the glow and a small bonus
through-out the rest of the fight.  B.B. remarked that his fighter was
inspired by this, and slightly later in the fight when he &lt;em&gt;aced&lt;/em&gt; one
of his rolls I ruled that &lt;em&gt;he&lt;/em&gt; picked up a slight glow for the moment.
At the end of the fight B.B. decided he wanted to become a Paladin of
the Holy Light as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, everybody else had been whacking at the zombies.
D.B.'s dwarf was doing wonders with &lt;em&gt;Sweep&lt;/em&gt;, keeping a significant
number of the zombies from attacking the others from behind.  T.A.'s
rogue was stabbing away &lt;em&gt;Two-fisted&lt;/em&gt; with his knives and both of the
girls (who had independently and without me knowing at the beginning
had picked two female clerics with &lt;em&gt;Pacifist&lt;/em&gt;; I might have suggested
one or the other take one of the other female pregens without
&lt;em&gt;Pacifist&lt;/em&gt; had I known) were quite happy to be taking out these
unnatural creatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T.B.'s combat mage had been plagued with really bad rolls all night,
and he was getting perturbed.  I had actually missed pointing out a
couple of bonuses he should have got that would have made one or two
of his earlier attacks hit, so I gave him a small bonus on his last
attack roll, which got him a hit with &lt;em&gt;raise&lt;/em&gt; and with the extra &lt;em&gt;d6&lt;/em&gt;
of damage he &lt;em&gt;aced&lt;/em&gt; a couple of his damage dice and got to totally
disintegrate the last zombie, which made up for the bad time he had
earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the zombies truly dead and the gloop still blazing, it was time
again for some quick looting and then out the door to the next
encounter.  Unfortunately, we had to end things there, to be resumed
at Christmas 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="remarks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, switching houses in the middle of the game was a bad
thing for the game &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/04/return-to-alusia-part-4/#good-overall" id="id8"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;: we lost a lot of time moving
things and setting up again.  On the other had, it did help get rid of
distractions.  I think in the future at this big family gatherings at
the farm I'll just plan to have gaming set up at my house, and we can
just migrate people there when it's time to play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Dungeon Tiles&lt;/em&gt; make nice looking dungeons, but are tedious to
organize; finding the right tiles takes too much time unless you can
do it before the game, and they are surprisingly bulky.  I still
haven't figured out if I've lost any of the tiles.  I need to try some
PDF tile sets to see if it's more convenient when I can just print out
as many tiles as I want on cardstock, instead of having a limited
number of much thicker tiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When playing with the kids, I tend to let really high &lt;em&gt;aces&lt;/em&gt; do things
that are just plain cool, like letting a damage roll that &lt;em&gt;aced&lt;/em&gt; with
enough raises to do a half-a-dozen wounds if the PC had been attacking
a &lt;em&gt;Wild Card&lt;/em&gt; to instead take out several side-by-side &lt;em&gt;Extras&lt;/em&gt;, and/or
add some cool &lt;strong&gt;special effects&lt;/strong&gt;, like the glow and bonus for M.A.'s
paladin, the much shorter glow for B.B's fighter, and T.B.'s combat
mage's disintegration of the last zombie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also tend to be fairly lenient with bonuses if I realize I'd made a
mistake in an earlier round that could have made an earlier attack a
success, retconning those earlier misses into “you spent a couple
rounds getting this attack set up right, and boy did you hit it this
time!”  It's not going to do me any good to not recognize my mistakes
and hide behind the letter of rules and send a kid away from the table
unhappy.  All but one of the kids I play with regularly is 11 or
younger, and we often don't get to play more than once month, if that.
If I was playing with adults or older kids, or we played often enough
that even the younger kids had the rules down perfectly I'd be
stricter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/em&gt; doesn't have all of &lt;em&gt;D&amp;amp;D 4e&lt;/em&gt;'s mechanics for dynamics,
such as special rules for &lt;em&gt;shifting&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;pushing&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;pulling&lt;/em&gt;, and
I didn't really do anything particular in these sessions to do that
with &lt;em&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/em&gt; other than trying to have more terrain obstacles
and have more than one opponent per room.  Things seemed to be pretty
dynamic in play.  I think the things that &lt;em&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/em&gt; does have
still let you do dynamic things easily, though with more recourse to
GM judgement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/07/new-blog-first-post/"&gt;timewarp&lt;/a&gt; post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="no-alusia-supplements"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/04/return-to-alusia-part-4/#id1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;The original campaign was based only on
the original &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/pages/dragonquest-and-i/#frontiers-of-alusia-adventure-map"&gt;The Frontiers of Alusia&lt;/a&gt;  supplement, which was just
a map and 4 pages of terse descriptions that accompanied
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="real-cardboard"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/04/return-to-alusia-part-4/#id2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; cardboard, heavy and stiff and
about one sixteenth inch thick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="spare-sheets"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/04/return-to-alusia-part-4/#id6"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several of the &lt;em&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Savage Tales&lt;/em&gt;
adventures come with pre-generated characters and figure flats for
the characters (as well as the monsters for the adventure) so back
at Christmas when I'd quickly put this adventure together I just
printed out the sheets from a couple of the adventures and let the
players pick which ones they liked the best.  That left me with
several from which new players could pick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="ooze-wc"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/04/return-to-alusia-part-4/#id7"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps using an ooze and a gloop that both could burn
as &lt;em&gt;Wild Cards&lt;/em&gt; in nearby rooms was not a good idea...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="good-overall"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/04/return-to-alusia-part-4/#id8"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;It was still a good thing overall, since it got
most of the kids and their commotion out of the house with most of
the adults, so the stess levels for those adults went down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>alusia</category><category>kids</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>timewarp</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/04/return-to-alusia-part-4/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2008 02:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Actual Play: Buggin'</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/06/28/buggin-2008-06-28/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another of the roleplaying games I played over the July 4th holiday
was &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.pigames.net/store/product_info.php?cPath=43_50_53&amp;amp;products_id=127"&gt;Buggin'&lt;/a&gt;, .  This game had T.B. as a scorpion named Scorp;
T.A. as Dragon the dragonfly; M.A. as a pillbug, Bill the Pill; my
brother A.B. and his youngest O.B. teamed up to run Bob the cyborg
grasshopper &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/06/28/buggin-2008-06-28/#original-buggin" id="id1"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;; E.A. as an Aunty the Ant; and
L.B. as Maria the bee.  Several of these characters had been played in
earlier games of &lt;em&gt;Buggin'&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The characters, having done some troubleshooting for the local ant
colony in the past, were assigned to find out why communication with a
neighboring ant colony had stopped.  They escaped an Ant Lion trap,
lots of fun was had with the ant lion throwing sand at the PCs and the
flying PCs trying to rescue the non-flying ones who'd fallen in the
trap. They made a new trail around the trap and moved on.  They found
the neighboring ant colony deserted, passed through the strangely
rectangular rooms and corridors of the lowest levels, found the huge
cubic room and black floating rectangular monolith, climbed up the
ledges and across the bridge and passed oddly through the black
monolith, to find themselves huge jellyfish-like creatures floating in
the upper atmosphere of Jupiter, where they set about building cities
for new homes, along with lots of other jellyfish-like creatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then they woke up, and found themselves back to normal and
remembering the Ant Lion trap as the only problem with other colony.
And then they woke up, and they were Jellyfish Colonists on Jupiter
again.  And so forth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt; thought this was funny, and others thought it was
just strange.  M.A. thought it was really neat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L.B. was very worried that those characters would be constantly
flipping back and forth between being Jellyfish Colonists on Jupiter
whenever they went to sleep, so I assured her that it was just for
this one game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="remarks"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Remarks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that &lt;em&gt;Buggin'&lt;/em&gt; is less work for me to run than &lt;em&gt;Toon&lt;/em&gt;.  The
system is simpler, a character sheet and the character creation rules
all fit on one page of paper &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/06/28/buggin-2008-06-28/#pg" id="id2"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, and I don't have to worry about
making things funny, since the genre doesn't &lt;strong&gt;require&lt;/strong&gt; humor
(although the players usually add plenty of it themselves). It's
usually pretty easy to come up with adventure ideas on the fly, since
the genre is ubiquitous in TV and movies; I'd still find an adventure
generator useful for inspiration, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/07/new-blog-first-post/"&gt;timewarp&lt;/a&gt; post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="pg"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/06/28/buggin-2008-06-28/#id2"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;... which is a goal of the &lt;em&gt;1 Page Game&lt;/em&gt; system used in
&lt;em&gt;Buggin'&lt;/em&gt; and the other &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://deep7.com/?cat=4"&gt;1PGs&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.deep7.com"&gt;Deep7&lt;/a&gt; and its partners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;dl class="footnote brackets"&gt;
&lt;dt class="label" id="original-buggin"&gt;&lt;span class="brackets"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/06/28/buggin-2008-06-28/#id1"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the very first &lt;em&gt;Buggin'&lt;/em&gt; game I ran
N.A.B. created a grasshopper, Bob.  During the course of the game
he lost his arm.  At the end of game the ant colony “repaired” him,
and he ended up with a cyborg arm.  He also ended up with a pair of
Frankenstein bolts on his head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>buggin'</category><category>kids</category><category>rpg</category><category>timewarp</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/06/28/buggin-2008-06-28/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2008 22:45:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaming during the Week of the July 4th Holiday, 2008</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/06/27/week-of-july-4th-gaming-2008/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;My brother who lives out of state usually comes in from out-of-state
twice a year, once during the summer and once at Christmas.  One of
his sons is old enough to play Savage Worlds these days, and since I'd
given him, along with rest of the kids who were old enough, their own
copies of the &lt;em&gt;Savage Worlds: Explorer's Edition&lt;/em&gt; I wanted to make
sure we got to play some roleplaying games while they were in town,
especially &lt;em&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running for kids is a lot different than running for adults.  One of
the kids is in his middle teens, but the rest of them are under 11 and
one is 6.  They're very enthusiastic when they're interested, but if
things slow down the younger ones (literally) wander off until things
speed up again.  They also have sometimes have a little difficulty
switching between the neat stuff that is happening and the mechanical
stuff we're using to make the neat stuff happen, which can make things
take longer than it should.  They all enjoy it, though, and it's
definitely worth doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometime I'd like to make some character sheets specifically for the
younger kids who don't read very much yet, with pictures of, for
instance, their sword and the dice they need to roll to attack and do
damage with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my nephews is very into a particular collectable card game, and
we didn't get a chance to play it this summer.  Maybe at the Winter
gathering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/07/new-blog-first-post/"&gt;timewarp&lt;/a&gt; post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>gaming</category><category>rpg</category><category>timewarp</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/06/27/week-of-july-4th-gaming-2008/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2008 01:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Recent Reading: Sterling</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/06/27/recent-reading-sterling/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Schismatrix Plus&lt;/cite&gt;, Bruce Sterling&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured out part way through this that I actually read this before.
(Or rather, the &lt;cite&gt;Schismatrix&lt;/cite&gt; part of it, since it's a collection of
a novel and some related short stories.)  Looking back at my &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2005/02/24/2005-02-24/"&gt;log&lt;/a&gt;,
I'd actually read it &lt;em&gt;recently&lt;/em&gt;, just 3½ years ago.  Worth
rereading, though.  I found them thought provoking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/07/new-blog-first-post/"&gt;timewarp&lt;/a&gt; post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>recent reading</category><category>science fiction</category><category>timewarp</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/06/27/recent-reading-sterling/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2008 21:51:09 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>