<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about warren zevon)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/warren-zevon.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 16:45:44 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Remembrance &amp; Choices</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/09/08/2003-09-08/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;section id="remembrance"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Remembrance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Warren Zevon died Sunday; he'll be missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="choices"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choices&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is more, it appears to me that this is a critical time for him, a
lesser climacteric — a time that will settle him in that particular
course he will never leave again, but will persevere in for the rest
of his life.  It has often seemed to me that towards this period (in
which we all three li, more or less) men strike out there permanent
characters; or have those characters struck into them.  Merriment,
roaring high spirits before this: then some chance concatenation, or
some hidden predilection (or rather inherent bias) working through,
and the man is in the road he cannot leave but must go on, making it
deeper and deeper (a groove, or channel), until he is lost in his mere
character — persona — no longer human but an accretion of qualities
belonging to this character.  James Dillon was a delightful being.  Now
he is closing in.  It is odd — will I say heart-breaking?  — how
cheerfulness goes: gaiety of mind, natural free-springing joy.
Authority is its great enemy — the assumption of authority.  I know few
men over fifty that seem to me entirely human: virtually none who has
long exercised authority. — Stephen Maturin, writing in his diary,
&lt;cite&gt;Master and Commander&lt;/cite&gt;, by Patrick O'Brian&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>i'll sleep when i'm dead</category><category>old blog</category><category>warren zevon</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2003/09/08/2003-09-08/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2003 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>