<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../../../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about brigand-crypt)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/rpg/actual-play/the-kids/brigand-crypt.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2023 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2023 19:01:01 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Fabled Curse of the Brigand Crypt, Play Session #4</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/10/03/brigand-crypt-part-4/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Played &lt;cite&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/cite&gt; with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;.  E.A. went to the Jubilee, but
T.A. and M.A. stayed to play &lt;cite&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://primerequisitegames.blogspot.com/"&gt;Prime Requisite Games&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lulu.com/product/file-download/fabled-curse-of-the-brigand-crypt/4503745"&gt;DLD2 — Fabled Curse of the
Brigand Crypt&lt;/a&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to
skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Labyrinth Lord&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. played &lt;em&gt;Arlow&lt;/em&gt; (an Elf) and &lt;em&gt;Grimmin&lt;/em&gt; (a Dwarf), and also played
&lt;em&gt;James&lt;/em&gt; (a Thief), who was created by D.B.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. played &lt;em&gt;Elsie&lt;/em&gt; (an Elf) and Leanna (a Dwarf), and also played
&lt;em&gt;Hermes&lt;/em&gt; (A Magic User), who was created by D.B.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. played John (a Cleric) and Zedd (a Magic User).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1st day:&lt;/strong&gt; They all hunted, since Mad Sammy's stores were running
low.  They found 20 days worth of food, which they shared with Mad
Sam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2nd day:&lt;/strong&gt; They went back to the crypt, to the room with the orange
and green painted keyholes.  The two shadows attacked them, but
luckily for the PCs, by this point in the adventure many had magic
weapons, and they were able to land some good solid hits.  The shadows
faded into the gloom, and then attacked again when the PCs attention
was diverted.  This time the party handily disposed of the shadows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They then used the Green &amp;amp; Orange Rod Keys, and the secret door
opened.  The climbed down the chain (a couple slipped, but caught
themselves) to the lower level and opened the double doors into what
turned out to be the final room of the crypt.  It contained two stone
coffins with statues atop each.  They were talking about pulling down
the statutes so they could open the coffins when the statue on the
left coffin attacked — it was actually a gargoyle.  They killed it
without much trouble, and turned to the statue on the right.  That
statue was firmly fixed to the coffin and they were unable to pull it
down.  They turned back to the other coffin, which opened easily.
They pulled out the treasure and read the note wrapped around the
ring, and heard the banging and screeching start in the right-side
coffin, while simultaneously the statue from that coffin fell and
struck two of the party glancing blows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the noises from the coffin, they opened it with the key
none-the-less — the lid was pushed back, and a medusa sat up,
surprising them all.  All but one of the PCs were turned to stone by
the baleful gaze of the medusa.  Grimmin was the lucky adventurer, and
he resisted the gaze once again, while he ran around behind the other
coffin, where he quickly rifled through his backpack and found the
silver mirror.  Standing up with the mirror before him, he avoided the
medusa's gaze, while she looked full into the mirror and was turned to
stone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grimmin was left alone, surrounded by the petrified bodies of his
friends.  The &lt;span class="scroll"&gt;Stone to Flesh&lt;/span&gt; scrolls they had found earlier
were also, unfortunately petrified, as was all the treasure they had
accumulated before this room.  Fortunately, there was plenty of
treasure in this room.  After spending a night with Mad Sam, Grimmin
set off for civilization to find more scrolls of &lt;span class="scroll"&gt;Stone to
Flesh&lt;/span&gt; and a novice wizard to accompany him back and read the scrolls
to free his comrades.  Eventually he did, but it cost him all the loot
from the last room.  He traveled back to the crypt with Harlan, his
hired magic user, but as they came down the steps they were attacked
by skeletons.  Grimmin, knowing that if Harlan was killed it was all
up for his companions, bravely threw himself in the path of the blow
intended for Harlan, and was stuck by the other skeleton as well, and
luckily survived both.  After that, with help from Harlan's Magic
Missile, it was easy to finish off the skeletons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once they got to the statues, the magic user read the scrolls and the
PCs were restored.  After a night's rest in Mad Sammy's basement they
all (except for Sammy) set off for civilization.  However, on the
first night out, on the sleeping Grimmin's watch, they were attacked
by wolves.  Once awake they fought back valiantly.  When the Guardian
of the Crypt, a great glowing orb with one eye, appeared they were at
first taken aback, and feared the Guardian had killed Harlan when it
sent a bolt of magical energy into the tree where Harlan had hidden.
However, Arlow ended up killing it with one &lt;span class="spell"&gt;Magic Missile&lt;/span&gt;,
and they finished off the wolves without too much difficulty  They
returned to tell Sammy that his nightmare was over, and then all
(including Sammy, this time) left for civilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="loot-xp"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Loot &amp;amp; XP&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The loot for the final room was 5930 gp, all used to buy scrolls and
hire Harlan to read them.  The previous loot was 3108 gp, so everybody
got 388.5 gp.  Total monster XP for the whole adventure was &lt;strong&gt;797 XP&lt;/strong&gt;
divided by eight PCs and rounded to &lt;strong&gt;100 XP&lt;/strong&gt;.  Total XP with the
loot (once they got it back to civilization), per PC, was &lt;strong&gt;1230 XP&lt;/strong&gt;
each.  Not even James the Thief leveled!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So ended the &lt;strong&gt;Fabled Curse of the Brigand Crypt&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="afterward"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Afterward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I pointed out to the kids that very little of their final XPs came
from killing monsters, that most of it came from taking their
stuff, and that if they could do the later without the former they'd
be better off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We talked about what game to play next, during the school year when
L.B. isn't here, and they eventually decided on &lt;cite&gt;Evernight&lt;/cite&gt;, the
&lt;cite&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/cite&gt; campaign, at T.A.'s suggestion.  That was fine with
me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next week, when L.A. &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; in, we'll work on &lt;em&gt;Keep on the Borderlands&lt;/em&gt;.
We are getting near the end, and L.A. has said that she doesn't want
it to end.  I'll have to see what I can do about that.  Perhaps I'll
populate one of the dungeon maps I've drawn recently, and make it the
&lt;em&gt;Cave of the Unknown&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>dld2</category><category>gaming</category><category>labyrinth lord</category><category>rpg</category><category>spoilers</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/10/03/brigand-crypt-part-4/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Oct 2010 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fabled Curse of the Brigand Crypt, Play Session #3</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/09/05/brigand-crypt-part-3/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Played &lt;cite&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/cite&gt; with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/08/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;.  E.A. went to the Jubilee, but
T.A. and M.A. stayed to play &lt;cite&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://primerequisitegames.blogspot.com/"&gt;Prime Requisite Games&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lulu.com/product/file-download/fabled-curse-of-the-brigand-crypt/4503745"&gt;DLD2 — Fabled Curse of the
Brigand Crypt&lt;/a&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to
skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Labyrinth Lord&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A played &lt;em&gt;Arlow&lt;/em&gt; (an Elf) and &lt;em&gt;Grimmin&lt;/em&gt; (a Dwarf), and also played
&lt;em&gt;Hermes&lt;/em&gt; (A Magic User) and &lt;em&gt;James&lt;/em&gt; (a Thief), who were created by D.B.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. played John (a Cleric) and Zedd (a Magic User), and also played
&lt;em&gt;Elsie&lt;/em&gt; (an Elf) and Leanna (a Dwarf), who were created by E.A.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1st day:&lt;/strong&gt; They found the crypt doors locked again.  Pick Locks
failed, so they went back to the Temple.  Hermes: Red Stone. James:
Key, so /bite (he immediately dropped the key, so was only bitten
once), then Blue Stone.  Zedd: Gray Stone. John: Key, so Bite (and
dropped the key).  Arlow: Gold Stone.  Elsie: Green Stone.  Grimmin:
Key.  Since some were injured they went back to Mad Sammy's, go
thealed, and slept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2nd day:&lt;/strong&gt;  Back to crypt.  Door in room &lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt; was locked again and
when they opened it they surprised 8 giant rats.  R1 rats surprised,
Leanna and Grimmin step forward and attack, killing 3 rats, while the
rest of the party falls back and takes position in room &lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;.  R2
Hermes casts &lt;em&gt;sleep&lt;/em&gt;, sending the remaining 5 rats off to their last
slumber, then the rest of the party coup-de-graced the rats.  They
decided to pick them up on the way back out to smoke-dry for rations.
Off to area &lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;, the pit.  Wandering Monster: 4 skeletons in the
pit.  They animate when James starts down into the pit.  John turns 5
HD, so all the skeletons tried to flee over the north edge of the pit,
which repeatedly dumps them back into the pit.  It takes the party 6
rounds to destroy the skeletons, but James took 4 wounds and fell
unconscious. Zedd had the Green Rod Key.  He put it in the
green-daubed hole and pulls upward.  Everybody hears the click.  He
takes the key out.  The party members in the pit climb out on the
north side, which now &lt;em&gt;doesn't&lt;/em&gt; dump them back in the pit, and the
rest of the party steps around the corner from the west site of the
pit.  Leanna picks up James and carries him, and they all head off to
the door to room &lt;strong&gt;11&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Wandering Monster: Dwarf, 3 HD, Reaction Roll 9, Hostile. --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They had reached the doors when they noticed, coming up the hallway
behind them, a rather surly looking dwarf.  After an exchange where
the dwarf insisted they shouldn't be here and tried to intimidate them
into leaving, he turned and left.  T.A. immediately has Arlow (?)
agitating for the party to attack the retreating dwarf.  Upon learning
that the dwarf is wearing plate mail, Grimmin and Leanna fire their
crossbows at the dwarf, and Arlow joins in.  They score one hit, but
the dwarf steps round the corner over the pit, and Arlow, Grimmin, and
Leanna chase after him.  They chase him in the dark until he vanishes
out of their range of sight at the bottom of the stairs in room
&lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt;.  They hesitate at the top of the stairs, Leanna retreating to
find the others, and Grimmin and Arlow hear a scream in the room
below, then sounds of struggle, then silence.  They wait, listening,
and then Grimmin is surprised by the shadow and taken to –1 HP in the
first attack.  Arlow picks up Grimmin and flees to room &lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;, where
they paused.  The others (carrying James) are already in room &lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;.
Here they are all surprised again when &lt;em&gt;2&lt;/em&gt; shadows attack!  The
shadows attacked Arlow (and missed) and Zedd (and hit).  In the second
round the shadows attacked Hermes (and missed) and Leanna (and hit).
Party fled and left crypt door open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They spent two days just resting and healing.  Every night they had
wolves howling outside and clawing at the Mad Sammy's cellar door.
Mad Sammy shrieked and howled, babbling that they had offended “the
eye”.  On the third day some of them hunted, because their supplies
were gone and Mad Sammy's supplies were running low.  They found
enough to feed four people for the day.  On the fourth day they found
enough food to feed three people for the day.  On the fifth day John
was able to heal Leanna of the last of her wounds, and the party was
finally completely healed.  On the sixth day they found enough rations
for 12 people, and after eating had 3 days rations to smoke dry that
evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the seventh day they headed back to the crypt.  They went directly
to room &lt;strong&gt;11&lt;/strong&gt;, where they were surprised by 2 ghouls hidden in the
loose dirt near a ¾ buried chest.  Grimmin was paralyzed on the first
round (for 7 rounds), but the rest of the party was able to kill the
ghouls in three more rounds.  John cast &lt;em&gt;cure light wounds&lt;/em&gt; on
Grimmin, which also cured his paralysis.  Leanna took the magic flail,
and Hermes took both scrolls.  Back to mad Sam's, where there were
still wolves at the door every night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made an effort this time to follow the &lt;cite&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/cite&gt; Labyrinth
Play Sequence, Time and Movement, Rest, Monster Reaction, Wandering
Monsters, and Morale Checks rules more closely than I have
hitherto.&lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/09/05/brigand-crypt-part-3/#back-in-the-day" id="footnote-reference-1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;1&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The dwarf was a wandering monster roll,
straight from the Level 1 column on the Wandering Monster Table on
p. 104 of &lt;cite&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/cite&gt;, with everything after that improvised on
the fly — I decided he was another treasure hunter, upset at finding
competition, and once he started to flee the PCs it seemed inevitable
that he end up in the room with the shadow, and get killed and turned
into a shadow himself. I thought it added a lot to the game, and made
me look on wandering monsters with much more approval.  I do think
that I ought to make location-specific wandering monster tables,
though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="footnote-list brackets"&gt;
&lt;aside class="footnote brackets" id="back-in-the-day" role="note"&gt;
&lt;span class="label"&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a role="doc-backlink" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/09/05/brigand-crypt-part-3/#footnote-reference-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't remember how closely I used to follow
AD&amp;amp;D's equivalents back in the day when I primarily played AD&amp;amp;D.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;!-- Why not link://category/gaming/actual-play/the-kids ? --&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>dld2</category><category>gaming</category><category>labyrinth lord</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/09/05/brigand-crypt-part-3/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2010 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fabled Curse of the Brigand Crypt, Play Session #2</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/08/07/brigand-crypt-part-2/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;More gaming with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/08/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;.  D.B. left the farm after lunch, before we
had a chance to play, but E.A. and M.A. were available and eager to
play.  They created some new characters to add to the party —
E.A. created Leanna (a Dwarf) and M.A. created Zedd (a Magic User).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://primerequisitegames.blogspot.com/"&gt;Prime Requisite Games&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lulu.com/product/file-download/fabled-curse-of-the-brigand-crypt/4503745"&gt;DLD2 — Fabled Curse of the
Brigand Crypt&lt;/a&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to
skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Labyrinth Lord&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A played &lt;em&gt;Arlow&lt;/em&gt; (an Elf) and &lt;em&gt;Grimmin&lt;/em&gt; (a Dwarf), and also played
&lt;em&gt;Hermes&lt;/em&gt; (A Magic User), who was created by D.B.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. played &lt;em&gt;Elsie&lt;/em&gt; (an Elf) and Leanna (a Dwarf), and also played
&lt;em&gt;James&lt;/em&gt; (a Thief), who was created by D.B.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. played John (a Cleric) and Zedd (a Magic User).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The characters from &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/08/06/brigand-crypt-part-1/"&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; spent several days healing and resting.
Some friends who'd had the same idea about finding the brigands'
treasure showed up (M.A.'s Zedd and E.A's Leanna) and were welcomed to
the party.  Zedd brought his pony, who sleeps with them in Mad Sammy's
cellar at night.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reason I think the first fight in the sarcophagus
happened right after the fight with the ghouls, but my notes say
it happened in the second session.  I'll put it both places for
now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They went back to room &lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;, and decided to open one of the closed
stone coffins, and while pushing the heavy lid off, Elsie, along with
several others, fell into the coffin on top of the skeleton.  The
others managed to (eventually) exit the coffin, but poor Elsie was too
entangled with the skeleton.  Eventually the party killed the
skeleton, but Elsie ended in the negative hit points, so
they went back to Mad Sammy's with Elsie on a floating disk to
recover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After healing up, they went back to room &lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt; and opened coffin #2,
where a couple fell in again, but got pulled out more quickly.  They
killed the skeleton and opened the rest of the coffins and found the
treasure and a key.  They move through room &lt;strong&gt;7&lt;/strong&gt;, empty since its
occupants were killed in room &lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt; in the first session, and enter
room &lt;strong&gt;8&lt;/strong&gt;, where the piercers drop, impaling Zedd &amp;amp; Leanna &amp;amp; missing
Arlow.  They eventually pull the piercers out (doing more damage in
the process, and kill the piercers.  Then it was back to Mad Sammy's
to rest again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When they returned to the crypt they entered room &lt;strong&gt;9&lt;/strong&gt; where they
pulled down the hanging bodies and were attacked by the 2 blue cave
spiders.  John is bit and paralyzed, but the others kill the spiders.
John recovers from the paralysis in 6 rounds, and makes his save
vs. poison, so lives.  (Maybe here is when they went back to Sam's,
instead, or also?)  Next they're down the stairs to room &lt;strong&gt;10&lt;/strong&gt;.  John
puts the key in first, gets bit, and tries to bash the statue with his
flail, and gets bit again.  Finally he drops the key, which rolls to
the floor after the statue releases John's arm.  Next they put the
stones in: Elsie the green (one of her weapons glows), Arlow the gray
(and he gets gray hair), James the gold (he gets a ring from the
statute, which Zedd puts on then returns to James, who puts it in the
statue's mouth, whereupon it falls out again), Grimmin the red (stung
for 1 HP of damage), Hermes the blue (he made his save), and then
Elsie put the key in.  They heard the chain beyond the wall, and got
the Green Rod Key, and then were attacked by the shadow.  By the time
they got it off Elsie, she was in the negatives, and by the time they
got it off Leanna (injuring her with their non-magical weapons in the
process and figuring out they could only injure the shadow the magic)
she was in the negatives took, so they grabbed the girls and fled,
leaving the shadow.  Each time the shadow attacked from the shadows
and the party was surprised.  Of course, they ran back to Mad Sam's,
although they did close the crypt doors on the way out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>dld2</category><category>gaming</category><category>labyrinth lord</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/08/07/brigand-crypt-part-2/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Aug 2010 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fabled Curse of the Brigand Crypt, Play Session #1</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/08/06/brigand-crypt-part-1/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I had originally planned to start off the school year campaign for the
A. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/08/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;em&gt;B5 — Horror on the Hill&lt;/em&gt;, by Douglas Niles, but since
D.B. was in and M.A. and E.A. were not available, I started instead
with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://primerequisitegames.blogspot.com/"&gt;Prime Requisite Games&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lulu.com/product/file-download/fabled-curse-of-the-brigand-crypt/4503745"&gt;DLD2 — Fabled Curse of the Brigand
Crypt&lt;/a&gt;, by R. Lawrence Blake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://primerequisitegames.blogspot.com/"&gt;Prime Requisite Games&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lulu.com/product/file-download/fabled-curse-of-the-brigand-crypt/4503745"&gt;DLD2 — Fabled Curse of the
Brigand Crypt&lt;/a&gt;, so if you haven't played that you might want to
skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T.A., E.A., and M.A. had created characters earlier, but D.B. had to
create characters before we started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Labyrinth Lord&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;D.B. played &lt;em&gt;James&lt;/em&gt; (a Thief) and &lt;em&gt;Hermes&lt;/em&gt; (a Magic User), and also
played &lt;em&gt;John&lt;/em&gt; (a Cleric) who was created by M.A.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A played &lt;em&gt;Arlow&lt;/em&gt; (an Elf) and &lt;em&gt;Grimmin&lt;/em&gt; (a Dwarf), and also played
Elsie (an Elf), who was created by E.A.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They reached the village of Iron City, where the bandits were supposed
to have lived, in the late afternoon.  They searched several of the
houses, until they reached the storehouse.  They broke in the door
(the tongue of the lock tore out of the jamb) and questioned poor mad
Sammy, who was frightened by them but called down enough to talk once
they showed him no harm.  He babbled about everything but several
times repeated to them that they should &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; let “the eye” see them,
and that it roamed at night.  They decided to spend the night with
him, and barred the door, as best they could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next day they searched the rest of the town, found the well, and
entered the temple.  They pulled out the stones and the key, and
luckily pulled the key out last, so no one got bit.  James pulled out
the &lt;em&gt;red&lt;/em&gt; stone, but gave it to Grimmin.  Elsie pulled out the &lt;em&gt;green&lt;/em&gt;
stone.  Arlow pulled out the &lt;em&gt;gray&lt;/em&gt; stone.  James pulled out the
&lt;em&gt;gold&lt;/em&gt; stone.  Hermes pulled out the &lt;em&gt;blue&lt;/em&gt; stone.  John pulled out
the &lt;em&gt;key&lt;/em&gt;.  After that they opened the Crypt with the key and explored
room &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;, and over the course of several days opened all the burial
vaults in that room, killed the undead, and found the treasure and the
keys.  They had to rest and heal at least twice and each time took at
least two days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After clearing out the burial vaults in room &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;, they went down the
stairs to room &lt;strong&gt;2&lt;/strong&gt;, where T.A. insisted on searching for secret
doors, repeatedly, using up almost five hours of daylight.  Eventually
they opened the door with the key from burial vault &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;.  Entering,
they heard the sound from the east end of the corridor, investigated,
and found the pit, &lt;strong&gt;4&lt;/strong&gt;.  Seeing the green-daubed hole, they decided
to investigate and James slid down a rope held by Elsie and Hermes.
The 2 skeletons immediately attacked, and Grimmin slid down to help,
but fell.  John slid down too.  Grimmin blunted his battle ax on the
stone wall and dropped it, while John dropped his flail after also
hitting the wall.  After that John turned both of the skeletons, who
spent several rounds trying to uselessly climb up the east wall of the
pit, while James, John, and Grimmin tried fruitlessly to hit the
skeletons, seeming to fling their weapons repeatedly into the corners
of the pit.  Eventually they managed to kill the skeletons.  James
decided, looking at the green-daubed keyhole, that it was larger than
any of the keys they had found so far, and probably hooked up to some
mechanism, rather than a lock for a door, and that whatever it might
be, it was beyond his current skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They crawled back up out of the pit, and one of D.B.'s characters (I
think it was John) tried to step around the corner to the north
corridor, which tilted and dumped him back into the pit, for more
damage.  Next they explored the western end of corridor &lt;strong&gt;3&lt;/strong&gt;, where
James set off the arrow trap, which luckily missed.  They went in to
the crawlspace in &lt;strong&gt;5&lt;/strong&gt; with Grimmin in the lead and he killed the
skeleton with ease!  They came out of the crawlspace into &lt;strong&gt;6&lt;/strong&gt;, a
long narrow room with 12 coffins.  T.A.'s characters went to look at
the 4 open coffins and were attacked by two ghouls and a skeleton from
room &lt;strong&gt;7&lt;/strong&gt;.  D.B.'s characters, more cautious, had stayed by the
crawlspace, but moved up to help their comrades.  Luckily, the ghouls
attacked Arlow and Elsie, who as elves were able to ignore the
paralyzing effects of the ghouls.  The resulting fight destroyed the
ghouls and the skeleton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reason I think the first fight in the sarcophagus
happened right after the fight with the ghouls, but my notes say
it happened in the second session.  I'll put it both places for
now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They decided to open one of the closed stone coffins, and while
pushing the heavy lid off, Elsie, along with several others, fell into
the coffin on top of the skeleton.  The others managed to (eventually)
exit the coffin, but poor Elsie was too entangled with the skeleton.
Eventually the party killed the skeleton, but Elsie ended in the
negative hit points &lt;a class="footnote-reference brackets" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/08/06/brigand-crypt-part-1/#negative" id="footnote-reference-1" role="doc-noteref"&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;1&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, so they went back to
Mad Sammy's with Elsie on a floating disk to recover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="footnote-list brackets"&gt;
&lt;aside class="footnote brackets" id="negative" role="note"&gt;
&lt;span class="label"&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a role="doc-backlink" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/08/06/brigand-crypt-part-1/#footnote-reference-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="fn-bracket"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Negative hit points&lt;/em&gt;: I've been using a house rule that the
characters don't die until they hit –CON.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>dld2</category><category>gaming</category><category>labyrinth lord</category><category>rpg</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/08/06/brigand-crypt-part-1/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 07 Aug 2010 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>