<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about goblin-gully)</title>
  <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/rpg/actual-play/the-kids/goblin-gully.atom</id>
  <updated>2023-02-06T15:22:13Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/rpg/actual-play/the-kids/goblin-gully.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/rpg/actual-play/the-kids/goblin-gully/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Goblin Gully, Play Session #1</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/08/19/goblin-gully-part-1/</id>
    <updated>2010-08-19T23:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2010-08-19T23:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2010/08/19/goblin-gully-part-1/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;B.B. and his girlfriend C. came down to the farm to visit before going
off to Utah for college.  After dinner with the families, B.B. and
C. and the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/07/08/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt; rolled up &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.goblinoidgames.com/labyrinthlord.html"&gt;Labyrinth Lord&lt;/a&gt; characters and set out on
an adventure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're playing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://rpgcharacters.files.wordpress.com/2009/08/onepagedungeon-goblin-gully.pdf"&gt;Goblin Gully&lt;/a&gt;, from the blog &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://rpgcharacters.wordpress.com/2009/08/21/friday-map-goblin-gully-a-deadly-one-page-dungeon/"&gt;A character for every
game&lt;/a&gt; so if you haven't played that you might want to skip this
entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T.A., E.A., and M.A. had created characters earlier, but D.B. had to
create characters before we started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clockwise round the table:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Labyrinth Lord&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;C.DW. — a Thief named Aria&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;B.B. — a Dwarf named Urgo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — a Magic User named Octavian&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. — an Elf named Trista&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. — a Cleric named Jude&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They trekked through the hills for 4 days (Trista downing a dear when
their rations were gone), until they finally found the huge tree said
to be the entrance to the old pit.  Unfortunately, they were unable to
find the entrance, and as they were looking they were attacked by
javelins thrown from above, in the tree.  Not able to see their
assailants in the leafy boughs, they fled.  At a safe distance they
decided to run back and have the dwarf climb the tree, while the elf,
thief, and cleric used their missile weapons.  With the goblins
concentrating on the dwarf climbing towards them, the others were
finally able to pinpoint the goblins, and managed to kill one of them,
by the time the heavily wounded dwarf managed to climb up to the
goblins and miss his first attack.  The dwarf managed to scare the
remaining goblin into surrendering, and they climbed down out of the
tree.  The goblin swore he would leave and go back to the deep
mountains, if they would let him go.  When the dwarf swore he would
let him go if the goblin told them how to enter the pit, the goblin
did so.  An argument ensued among the PCs, Octavian in particular not
wanting to let the goblin go, but Urgo finally did (having sworn) and
the goblin high-tailed it out of there.  Several of the PCs had been
injured, but Urgo had taken the worst of the damage while climbing up
the tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They headed down the narrow dirt tunnel the goblin had shown them,
concealed behind a cleverly hinged section of a huge root, and the
tunnel quickly opened up into a stairway cut from stone.  They passed
through one empty room, where they paused to light Octavian's lantern,
then down another stair to a much larger room.  At the far side of the
room they could just make out a demonic face carved on the wall, its
huge mouth gaping blackly.  As they stared at the demonic face they
were surprised by 4 goblins springing down from niches high on the
wall where the stairway entered, behind them.  After a few rounds,
they were attacked by archers in the dark beyond the demonic mouth,
too. Soon all the PCs were badly injured, the dwarf at 0 HP, Octavian
at negative HP, and then Aria was brought to negative HP.  Urgo bound
Aria's wounds, and fell unconscious himself, bleeding to death, while
Trista and Jade attacked the two goblins beyond the mouth, Jade
throwing himself through the gaping mouth.  Jude killed one of the two
goblin archers, but fell to the other, who finally fled in the face of
Trista's deadly arrows.  This left Trista the only conscious
adventurer, with four unconscious companions to care for in this
deadly dungeon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She bound up her comrades' wounds, then searched the dead goblins,
finding a single vial of thick green liquid.  She gave it to the
dwarf, Urgo, and when he revived they carried their comrades partway
back up the winding stairs, out of easy bowshot, and secured them to
iron spikes, so they wouldn't slip down the steps.  There they each
guarded one approach.  Urgo fell asleep, but luckily Trista's keen
elvish senses noticed his snores and woke him, for in the night he
heard goblins approaching up the stair.  He hurtled himself down the
stair into the 4 goblins, killing one outright and injuring another
and setting them and himself tumbling to the bottom of the stairs.
Dazed and confused by the tumble, they all traded blows in the dark,
flailing madly and futilely until Urgo finally killed 2 more of them,
and the last remaining goblin fled back through the mouth before Urgo
could catch up with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually Jude recovered from his wounds enough to wake and pray, and
then healed Aria.  The companions then fled, carrying the unconscious
and deeply wounded Octavian with them, headed for town!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to continue this adventure when B.B. &amp;amp; C. are next in, perhaps
on fall break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</summary>
    <category term="actual-play" label="actual-play"/>
    <category term="dld2" label="dld2"/>
    <category term="gaming" label="gaming"/>
    <category term="labyrinth-lord" label="labyrinth lord"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
