<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../../../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about pirates)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/rpg/actual-play/the-kids/pirates.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2024 04:12:31 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Pirates! Session #5: Revenge is Sweet (and so are pies!)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/03/29/pirates-session-5-revenge-is-sweet-and-so-are-pies/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I guess I've got a &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Spanish Main&lt;/em&gt; campaign on my hands…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew the A. kids wanted to play a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/pages/roleplaying-games-played-with-the-kids/#savage-worlds"&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/a&gt; Pirates! game
when L.B. came to visit next, but I still hadn't anything the Thursday
before I was to pick L.B. up.  Luckily I had lunch that day with a
coworker who plays RPGs, and together we brainstormed an adventure
outline.  (Thanks, M.A.H.!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. playing Isaiah Kestrel, former captain of the &lt;em&gt;Lady Faire&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. playing Alice Pettigrew&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. playing Captain (Scarred) Jack&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;L.B. playing Phelicity Phillipe Gujon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew that losing the &lt;em&gt;Lady Faire&lt;/em&gt; still rankled, so I made the
villans of the damsel in distress plot suggested by M.A.H. the
mutinous crew of the &lt;em&gt;Lady Faire&lt;/em&gt; and the evil pirate who had taken
over the ship after the mutiny.  So, while the kids' struggling
pirates were looking for their next smuggling job (all their current
tiny boat would let them manage) they heard a rumor that their former
crew had kidnapped the daughter of a wealthy merchant.  They tracked
down the fisherman who had witnessed the attack on the yacht and
confirmed it had been their mutineers.  After this they set sail for
Tortuga, looking for information about where those mutinous dogs were
now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first time I'd bothered to use the sailing rules from the
rulebook, and they very quickly learned why somebody needs Knowledge
(Navigation)!  Eventually they reached Tortuga, and as soon as they
landed they started looking for information.  They very quickly
learned why somebody needs Streetwise!  Luckily for them, many people
had gone to a yearly pie-eating contest held by a local eatery.  They
entered, and Phelicity should have won, but another pirate was
initially declared the winner; however, the resulting pie-fight
conclusively proved he was cheating (and Phelicity got the prize
money!), and in the end he turned out to be Deadeye Dave, one of their
former crew.  He'd been dropped there to arrange ransom, while the
rest of the crew had gone off to a safe haven in the Virgin Islands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So off they went to the Virgin Islands.  After some excellent
navigating by former captain Isaiah they arrived, snuck up the side of
the former &lt;em&gt;Lady Faire&lt;/em&gt;, now named the &lt;em&gt;Saucy Wench&lt;/em&gt; (which the kids
universally agreed was a &lt;strong&gt;terrible&lt;/strong&gt; name), nailed their erstwhile
crew under hatches, and disposed of the interloping pirate captain and
his chief henchman just in time to intimidate their former crew as
they burst the hatches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually they left Deadeye Dave on one deserted island, the other
pirates on another, and sailed back to collect the reward for from the
damsel's relived father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They decided that since they had the &lt;em&gt;Lady Faire&lt;/em&gt; back that Isaiah
was captain of her again, while Captain Jack remained captain of the
smaller boat.  M.A. was charmingly nervous that the girls would
abandon Captain Jack's boat for Isaiah Kestrel's, since it was bigger,
but I think the fact that they now had a small fleet, rather than just
a single boat made everybody happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I have to figure out if this has affected their Fame, and how much
money the reward came to!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>kids</category><category>pirates of the spanish main</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/03/29/pirates-session-5-revenge-is-sweet-and-so-are-pies/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 29 Mar 2009 20:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Pirates! Session #4: Smuggler's Song</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/12/20/pirates-session-4-smugglers-song/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/Downloads/POTSM/Smuggler%27s_Song.pdf"&gt;“Smuggler'S Song”&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/"&gt;PEG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. playing Isaiah Kestrel, former captain of the Lady Faire&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. playing Alice Pettigrew&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. playing Captain (Scarred) Jack&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;L.B. playing Phelicity Gujon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="recap"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Recap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last time out the kids had lost their ship, lost the treasure, and
deposed their captain.  They'd had to build themselves a new boat to
escape the once-cursed island.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time out I decided that they'd forced by their dismal economic
situation into working for another pirate delivering smuggled goods,
and ran them through the &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Spanish Main&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/onesheets.html"&gt;one-sheet&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/Downloads/POTSM/Smuggler%27s_Song.pdf"&gt;Smuggler's Song&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They did pretty well, though they did end up running from the watch
several times.  And they mostly got paid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amusingly, my sister was not happy when they told her they'd been
fighting in a bar, so I've promised to steer closer to a “G” rating
next time…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>kids</category><category>one-sheet</category><category>peg</category><category>pirates of the spanish main</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>spoilers</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/12/20/pirates-session-4-smugglers-song/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2008 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Actual Play: Dead Men Tell No Tales, Part 3</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/11/28/dead-men-tell-no-tales-part-3/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I finally got to finish the &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Spanish Main&lt;/em&gt; one-sheet
“Dead Men Tell No Tales” that I've been running for the
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E.A. and L.B. were both here for this one, so the roster was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. playing Isaiah Kestrel, Captain of the Lady Faire&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. playing Alice Pettigrew&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. playing Scarred Jack&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;L.B. playing Phelicity Gujon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/Downloads/POTSM/DeadMen.pdf"&gt;“Dead Men Tell No Tales”&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/"&gt;PEG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we've had to split the adventure up over three sessions, and
they'd finished the last one the skeletons, and I wanted a big start
to this session, I told the kids their PCs had been arguing about what
to do with the treasure and hanged lady for about an hour.  They spent
a few minutes talking about it, and then I had them make Notice rolls
to avoid being surprised by the skeletons, reanimated after an hour.
They picked up a few wounds in the fight, but managed to finish the
skeletons off.  T.A.'s bad luck with initiative cards and low rolls
continued, though not as badly as before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They then tried to figure out how they could free themselves of the
curse and the skeletons, and decided the lady needed buried, which
they proceeded to do, right outside the mine entrance.  I had them
make Strength roles to avoid becoming Fatigued, which a couple of the
characters failed.  And that finished out another hour, and a few
minutes later the skeletons attacked again.  M.A. failed Scarred
Jack's Notice roll, so he didn't get dealt in the round, and got hit
by the one of the skeletons.  T.A. forgot to have Isaiah boast the
first round, and ended up owing me a bennie.  Eventually they killed
the skeletons again, and decided, since the curse obviously hadn't
been lifted, that they needed to bury the hanged lady in a cemetery at
the church in town.  Meanwhile, the weather was working up to a storm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, they dug the lady up, but in doing so T.A. and L.B. failed enough
Strength rolls to fall unconscious (remember that the curse has been
aging them rapidly), and they knew if they left the unconscious
characters there they would be killed when the skeletons reanimated,
so M.A. and E.A. had Jack and Alice pile the hanged lady's body on
Isaiah and dragged them to the town.  Unfortunately, part way through
digging the &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; grave, E.A. failed Alice's Strength roll and fell
unconscious.  Jack was able to get her most of the way out of the
grave, and finished burying the hanged lady with the six skeletons
only 20 yards away &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the zombie pirate captain only 60 yards away.
(Apparently, the zombie pirate captain had been chasing them for days
across the bottom of the sea).  Unfortunately for our heroes, the rest
of the crew, who'd been left on the sloop offshore, picked this moment
to come ashore.  Upon seeing the sorry state of their captain and
officers (and failing their Spirit rolls, they were overcome by greed,
whacked Jack on the head with the shovels, stole the map from their
unconscious captain, and set off for the treasure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCs awoke to a hurricane (which I'd earlier rolled using my
weather die from Flying Buffalo), and found shelter in the church
crypts.  I actually wanted to end the adventure there, but the kids
insisted we continue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few days the weather finally subsided and they immediately
headed back to the mine to look for the treasure.  It was gone, except
for a bent half-farthing piece that had been overlooked in a crack in
the floor.  At this point they were all suffering from Fatigue from
not eating or drinking for days, and so they went back to the town to
search for water.  When T.A. failed a roll to avoid Fatigue, I ruled
he'd gone delirious, wandered out on the dock, and falling into the
water, to be washed out into the bay.  L.B. had Phelicity swim out to
save him, but by the time she reached him T.A. had failed his swimming
roll and was drowning.  Phelicity swam down and brought him to the
surface and back to shore, but he had died.  Luckily, M.A. tried to
resuscitate, and failing the first roll spent a bennie (the last
bennie among the group) to reroll, and aced well enough to overcome
the –4 penalty from drowning and the –2 penalty from being untrained
in Healing, and saved Isaiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point I pointed out Isaiah's consistent bad luck, loosing the
treasure, loosing his ship, and Jack's comparative good luck, and like
proper little pirates they voted Isaiah out as captain and Jack in.
After that Jack climbed some palm trees and found some weird fruit so
they could eat.  I decided that the island had &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; living creatures
at all, due to the curse, but that they could find enough edible
plants so they wouldn't starve for the weeks it would take while they
built a small boat (with both oars &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; a sail) from timber scavenged
from the houses in the village to take them off the island to begin
their search for their traitorous crew and their treasure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's were we left them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this actually ran pretty long, once all sessions were
considered, I gave them all 5 XP.  Not wanting T.A. to be too
discouraged, I let him trade his “Captain” edge in for something else.
I didn't let him buy off his “Cocky” Hindrance, though. &lt;img alt="(:-)" src="https://tkurtbond.github.io/images/smiley-small.png" style="height: 2ex;"&gt;
Judging by everybody's reactions, I've got a &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Spanish
Main&lt;/em&gt; campaign to run now.  I can already see how to work the
“Smuggler's Song” one-sheet in as the next adventure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add Wound Penalties to Fatigue Penalties and things really start
getting grim fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>kids</category><category>one-sheet</category><category>peg</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>spoilers</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/11/28/dead-men-tell-no-tales-part-3/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2008 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Actual Play: Dead Men Tell No Tales, Part 2</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/11/25/dead-men-tell-no-tales-part-2/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I ran another session using the the &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Spanish Main&lt;/em&gt;
one-sheet “Dead Men Tell No Tales” with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/Downloads/POTSM/DeadMen.pdf"&gt;“Dead Men Tell No Tales”&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/"&gt;PEG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E.A. couldn't attend, but L.B. could, so she played Phillipe Gujon and
Alice Pettigrew, and out of deference to her dislike of playing
“boys”, it was revealed that “Phillipe” was actually “Phelicity”!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the roster was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. playing Isaiah Kestrel, Captain of the Lady Faire&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. playing Scarred Jack&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;L.B. playing (as her main character) Phelicity Gujon and (as her
secondary character) Alice Pettigrew&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We picked up a couple of days from the island on the map.  Not liking
the look of the decayed dock, they anchored offshore and left the crew
to guard the sloop.  On shore they found everybody 50 years dead.
They easily found the mine, ignored the skeletons wrapped in pirate
flags, and were shocked to find the lady hanging above the treasure in
the depths of the mines.  And of course, they were then attacked by
the six skeletons wrapped in pirate flags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;T.A. was plagued by poor initiative card draws and low rolls, and
earned the unhappy nickname “Captain Slowpants”, and eventually ended
up “Captain Slow-anything”, much to his dismay.  Eventually, however,
they managed to kill the skeletons, and that's where the game ended.
(We only had a short time to play.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We played in my living room around a low, 2 foot diameter table,
keeping dice, tokens, and cards on the table and character sheets
off.  We didn't bother to user miniatures.  I used gaming stones to
represent wound and shaken statuses, and check track of the skeletons
just by removing the d6 that I rolled for their fighting attacks, so
there was no book keeping.  I thought that all worked well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(My bones and joints, on the other hand, did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; work well when
getting up off the floor after a couple of hours of play.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>kids</category><category>one-sheet</category><category>pirates</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>spoilers</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/11/25/dead-men-tell-no-tales-part-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2008 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Actual Play: Dead Men Tell No Tales, Part 1</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/11/15/dead-men-tell-no-tales-part-1/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Some of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/actual-play/the-kids/"&gt;kids&lt;/a&gt; and I played through about half of the &lt;em&gt;Pirates of
the Spanish Main&lt;/em&gt; Savage Worlds one-sheet “Dead Men Tell No Tales”
this afternoon and evening, before and after supper.  This is one of
the free downloads &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/"&gt;Pinnacle Entertainment Group&lt;/a&gt; did for the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roster was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. playing Isaiah Kestrel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;E.A. playing Alice Pettigrew and Phillipe Gujon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;M.A. played Scarred Jack&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/Downloads/POTSM/DeadMen.pdf"&gt;“Dead Men Tell No Tales”&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.peginc.com/"&gt;PEG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They found the dying pirate with the chest manacled to his foot, and
after he died opened the chest and found the treasure map, and decided
to head for the island.  Along the way they found and boarded the
decaying pirate ship, from which they deduced had come the dying
pirate.  They had a hard time with the zombie pirate captain wildcard,
who had the luck of the initiative most of the time, ending up with
the Joker &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; times, and the high card of the draw most of the
rest of the time.  The zombie wildcard incapacitated Alice with one
blow that ended up doing five wounds at a whack, and things were
looking dire.  However, the zombie pirate captain's luck with the
iniative cards finally left him However, E.A., rolling for the crew
extras who showed up after hearing Alice scream as she went down, aced
an attack roll, then aced all three of the damage dice, and then aced
at least one of the rerolls, putting the wildcard down decisively.
After that M.A. had Scarred Jack try an untrained Healing roll and
aced it big time, so most of Alice's wounds got healed and M.A. wants
Jack to learn Healing for real now, which is neat.  After they
returned to their ship the other ship collapsed and sank.  They
decided to continue to follow the treasure map, even though a storm
came up.  Alice was unconscious for four days.  After couple of days
it was obvious that they and their ship were suffering from the curse,
and that's were we had to leave the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="reflections"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should have looked up all the details of the edges and hindrances
and wrote them on the kids character sheets, and on my copies, before
the kids came over for the game.  I had to do it while they were
there, and of course they wanted to get on to the gaming.  However, I
knew we'd be looking them up in the middle of game if I didn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also need to play more often so I can keep the details in mind
better.  Maybe next weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>actual-play</category><category>kids</category><category>one-sheet</category><category>peg</category><category>pirates</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><category>spoilers</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2008/11/15/dead-men-tell-no-tales-part-1/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2008 04:29:42 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>