<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/assets/xml/atom.xsl" type="text/xsl media="all"?>
<feed xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about 04)</title>
  <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_books/read/2009/04.atom</id>
  <updated>2022-08-05T18:11:29Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
  </author>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_books/read/2009/04.atom"/>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_books/read/2009/04/"/>
  <generator uri="https://getnikola.com/">Nikola</generator>
  <entry>
    <title>Recent Reading: Marc Miller and Game Designers' Workshop</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/04/28/marc-miller-and-game-designers-workshop/</id>
    <updated>2009-04-28T21:41:27-05:00</updated>
    <published>2009-04-28T21:41:27-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/04/28/marc-miller-and-game-designers-workshop/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;, by Marc Miller &amp;amp; Game Designers' Workshop, copyright
1977, 1981 by Game Designer's Workshop.  &lt;cite class="subtitle"&gt;Books 1–3&lt;/cite&gt;,
&lt;cite class="subtitle"&gt;The Basic Books&lt;/cite&gt;, Classic &lt;strong&gt;Traveller&lt;/strong&gt; Reprint Series,
copyright 2001 by Far Future Enterprises; a joint publication of Far
Future Enterprises and QuikLink Interactive, ISBN 1-55878-218-4.
“The Olympia Incident” by Martin J. Dougherty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a reprint of the 1981 second edition of &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;, along
with a little bit about the publishing history of &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;, and a
short story, “The Olympia Incident”, set in the &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;
universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was first getting into gaming, I remember going on a trip to
Morgantown, WV with my brother and some of his friends from high
school who were in the gaming group that I'd recently joined.  We
visited a couple of places that sold gaming materials, and one of the
group, R.S. if I remember correctly, bought a copy of &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;.  I
remember reading the books in his basement rec room and trying to make
characters.  Unfortunately, at that point the only RPGs that our group
had seen were variants of D&amp;amp;D (T&amp;amp;T and DQ were still a couple years
away), and I, at least, never really figured out &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; and what
you could do with it, and, again if I remember correctly, our group
never did much with &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something must have struck a cord, however, because over the years I
bought several editions of the game, from &lt;cite&gt;Megatraveller&lt;/cite&gt; to
&lt;cite&gt;Traveller: the New Era&lt;/cite&gt; (also known as &lt;cite&gt;T:NE&lt;/cite&gt;), to &lt;cite&gt;GURPS Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;,
to &lt;cite&gt;Marc Miller's Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; (also known as &lt;cite&gt;T4&lt;/cite&gt;), and even including
&lt;cite&gt;2300AD&lt;/cite&gt;, which was originally published as &lt;cite&gt;Traveller: 2300&lt;/cite&gt;, even
though the mechanics and setting were in no way related to the
&lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; mechanics or setting.  Many of this I probably picked up
during a long period where I wasn't doing any gaming, and just reading
game books. (This would almost certainly have been before the
explosion of RPG stores on the net.)  I probably picked
&lt;cite&gt;Megatraveller&lt;/cite&gt; up after it was out of print; my copy seems to have
the (infamous) errata fixed.  I may have picked up &lt;cite&gt;T:NE&lt;/cite&gt; when it
first came out.  I know I picked up almost all of the &lt;cite&gt;GURPS
Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; books as they came out.  I'm sure I picked up &lt;cite&gt;2300AD&lt;/cite&gt; off
the discount rack.  I remember being saddened when GDW closed their
doors, although that was in part due to really enjoying their &lt;cite&gt;Space:
1889&lt;/cite&gt; line and Frank Chadwick's &lt;cite&gt;Cadillacs &amp;amp; Dinosaurs&lt;/cite&gt; RPG, based on
Mark Schultz's comic books, which I had read and enjoyed.  I never got
a chance to play any of GDW's games while they were still in
operation, but have always wanted to play a game with &lt;cite&gt;Space: 1889&lt;/cite&gt;'s
background.  I never figured out what to do with &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;,
though. I came closest with &lt;cite&gt;GURPS Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;, having enjoyed playing
&lt;cite&gt;GURPS&lt;/cite&gt; before my gaming hiatus.  I enjoyed reading all the &lt;cite&gt;GURPS
Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; books, but I had no gaming group at that time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, years later, after I'd gotten back to gaming regularly, in
2007, I had been reading about a number of people who had been playing
Classic &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;, which is what folks called the original system,
with or without the Traveller Universe.  They praised the game for its
simplicity and completeness and for its relatively small size.  I had
know about the Far Future Enterprises Classic &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; reprint
line, but couldn't afford them when they first came out.  I did,
however, find a an inexpensive reprint of just Books 1–3, published
jointly by Far Future Enterprises and QuikLink Interactive (also know
as QLI/RPGRealms), and I ordered it in October 2007.  After some
problems with QLI's order system, I finally received my copy in
November, 2007.  It was a reprint of the 1981 2nd edition of
&lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;, which apparently cleaned up the rules a little bit.  I
read it quickly, and my reaction was: “Huh.  Why didn't we play the
heck out of this back in high school?  I could see playing this
&lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt; and having a blast!”  I liked the basic simplicity of the
system, having moved away from complex systems like &lt;cite&gt;GURPS&lt;/cite&gt; to systems
that were much simpler, like &lt;cite&gt;Savage Worlds&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometime later I got Mongoose Publishing's new edition of
&lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;,and though it was a reasonable version.  Certainly it was
closest of any system to the original, definitely since
&lt;cite&gt;Megatraveller&lt;/cite&gt;, and possibly since the original itself.  And the fact
Mongoose released it with several licenses that allowed free use of
the system, and some use of the background made it more attractive.
It prompted me to go back and read most of my other versions of
&lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt;, including the FFE/QLI reprint of Books 1–3.  After
looking at them all, it was Classic &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; I wanted to play.  Since
then I've gathered some of the original &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; publications, and
a couple volumes of the FFE reprint volumes.  (I wish they were all
still in print.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to have to run a Classic &lt;cite&gt;Traveller&lt;/cite&gt; game sometime soon.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary>
    <category term="gaming" label="gaming"/>
    <category term="recent-reading" label="recent reading"/>
    <category term="rpg" label="rpg"/>
    <category term="science-fiction" label="science fiction"/>
    <category term="traveller" label="traveller"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Recent Reading: Williams</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/04/09/williams/</id>
    <updated>2009-04-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2009-04-09T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/04/09/williams/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The Gifts of the Gorboduc Vandal&lt;/cite&gt;, by Paul O. Williams, copyright
1989; Del Rey/Ballantine Books, May 1989; ISBN 0-345-35597-0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting science fiction novel by the author of the
post-apocalyptic &lt;cite class="series"&gt;Pelbar Cycle&lt;/cite&gt; series of novels.  Like the Pelbar
novels, I enjoyed this more for the ideas than the style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently there is a sequel to this, &lt;cite&gt;The Man from Far Cloud&lt;/cite&gt;,
published in 2004.  I really ought to see about finding a copy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary>
    <category term="pelbar-cycle" label="pelbar cycle"/>
    <category term="recent-reading" label="recent reading"/>
    <category term="science-fiction" label="science fiction"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Recent Reading: Stross</title>
    <id>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/04/06/stross/</id>
    <updated>2009-04-06T20:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <published>2009-04-06T20:30:00-05:00</published>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kurt Bond</name>
    </author>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2009/04/06/stross/"/>
    <summary type="html">&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Accelerando&lt;/cite&gt;, by Charles Stross, copyright 2005; Ace/The Berkley
Publishing Groupo/Penguin Group (USA) Inc./Penguin Books Ltd., July
2006; ISBN 0-441-01415-1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crash! Bang! Ouch!  The idea of sentient corporations and ponzi
schemes taking over makes this a dystopia to me.  Very interesting,
however; and quite dense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary>
    <category term="recent-reading" label="recent reading"/>
    <category term="science-fiction" label="science fiction"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
