<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../../../../../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lacking Natural Simplicity (Posts about t.a.-pirates)</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://tkurtbond.github.io/categories/cat_gaming/rpg/actual-play/the-kids/kids-gming/ta-pirates.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2024 &lt;a href="mailto:tkurtbond@gmail.com"&gt;T. Kurt Bond&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 18:49:46 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>T.A.'s PotSM: The Scarlet Rose</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/08/t.a.s-potsm-the-scarlet-rose/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We played “The Scarlet Rose”, an adventure from off the net, so if
you haven't played that you might want to skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — GameMaster&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Capt. Jack Savage, Rowena Blackwood&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heard rumors of Cutthroat Henry Hobbs' treasure; key under Santa
Domingo's Lion's Gate (St. Leon's church).  Go there.  Try to climb
down well in church.  Rowena falls, but quietly.  Find box with sand
casting of key with the number 4 on the handle.  Took it to a
blacksmith, who recognizes it as a key from a gold collection site
from mines of Santa Domingo — he warns us that the spirits of natives
who died in the mines infest them to this day.  11$ to make the key.
Can't find any way to protect us from the spirits. Bought Lantern and
Bullseye Lantern and 6 pints of oil for 89$.  Went to mines.  5 main
passages.  Some men came out of one of the other passages.  Their
leader is Catfish Carlos Peña, and they say they can't let us get away
knowing about them.  We fire and kill Peña and others flee.  Number 4
area opens to our key.  Only thing of interest is the Shipping
Security Log.  The 13th shipment lists Robyn H Besh (an anagram for
Henry Hobbs) is in charge.  He must have changed the log and took
command of the ship to took it to Santiago (destination listed on the
log).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jack has a one-masted sloop with 4 crew.  On the 3rd day one of the
crew sees a ship; 2 days later another crew member sees it.  We've
also been having bad luck.  We reach Santiago.  Lots of taverns to
investigate.  We find an old man, Smiling Jack, who sells us for 5$
the information that William Wilks sailed with Besh, boasted of
Spanish treasure, but lost money and couldn't pay.  Smiling Jack leads
us to the gambling house wher Wilks, known as Whistling Willy, is
playing.  He's about to be shot.  Captain Jack Savage walks up to the
shooter and shoots him first, killing him.  His friends weren't
happy.  We kill 3 more, and 1 runs.  Question Whistling Willy.
Cutthroat double-crossed his crew.  Willy had a pine box Besh gave him
that turned out to have a false-bottomed, with a treasure map.  It
looks like Besh hid the treasure on the Isle of Pines.  We head
there.  A day's trek inland.  Come to the location where think
Hobbs/Besh buried the treasure.  Find large pine with H.H. and an
arrow pointing down carved on it, but it's surrounded by fire ants!
Drove the ants out with burning oil.  Takes 3 hours to dig down to 6
large chests with 5000$ each.  Took us several days to transfer the
chests to the ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;+5 XP.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>potsm</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/08/t.a.s-potsm-the-scarlet-rose/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2014 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>T.A.'s PotSM: The Lady's Favor</title><link>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/01/t.a.s-potsm-the-ladys-favor/</link><dc:creator>T. Kurt Bond</dc:creator><description>&lt;aside class="admonition admonition-spoilers"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Spoilers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We played “The Lady's Favor”, the adventure from the back of the
&lt;cite&gt;Pirates of the Spanish Main&lt;/cite&gt; book, so if you haven't played that
you might want to skip this entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;
&lt;section id="attending"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Attending&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.A. — GameMaster&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;T.K.B. — Capt. Jack Savage, Rowena Blackwood&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="actual-play"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Actual Play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PCs rescued Virginia Cotton from rowdy pirates.  (+1 Fame) They
escorted her to the Royal Crown Tavern.  Her contact, Knox (???), told
her that her dad Jebidiah was a pirate, to her shock, and that he'd
buried a pirate treasure then got captured, and is being held captive
at the house of Baron Pettigrew.  When Virginia tells him that she
knows nothing of the treasure, he grabs her and tells his two thugs to
attack.  We manage to down Knox and one of the thugs and the other
flees.  We take their weapons and leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decide to sneak into Pettigrew's mansion.  Virginia suggests we
have our ship ready to go, so Capt. Jack gives the orders.  We went to
the mansion after dark and snuck up to the back door.  Sneak into the
kitchen, dining room, through the hall past a maid, and found a
sleeping guard.  We tried to knock the guard out and failed, but
intimidated him and tied him up, got the keys from him, opened the
door and found Jebidiah.  We untied Jebidiah and snuck out with him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We agreed to split the treasure and headed off in the ship.  Jack
healed up.  We were trailed by another ship, but managed to give them
the slip.  We arrived at the island, but had to ride out a storm
offshore.  Then we took a longboat ashore, and dug up the treasure.
There were five chests, each containing 500$.  We distributed the
treasure, one chest each to Jebidiah, Virginia, our crew, Rowena, and
Capt. Jack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="aftermath"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aftermath&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;+5 XP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description><category>potsm</category><category>rpg</category><category>savage worlds</category><guid>https://tkurtbond.github.io/posts/2014/11/01/t.a.s-potsm-the-ladys-favor/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>